<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Poems &amp;c. written by Mr. Ed. Waller ... ; and printed by a copy of his own hand-writing ; all the lyrick poems in this booke were set by Mr. Henry Lawes ...</title>
            <title>Poems. Selections</title>
            <author>Waller, Edmund, 1606-1687.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 187 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 107 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67344</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W513</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13495</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">14573987</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 14573987</idno>
            <idno type="VID">102619</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67344)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 102619)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1079:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Poems &amp;c. written by Mr. Ed. Waller ... ; and printed by a copy of his own hand-writing ; all the lyrick poems in this booke were set by Mr. Henry Lawes ...</title>
                  <title>Poems. Selections</title>
                  <author>Waller, Edmund, 1606-1687.</author>
                  <author>Lawes, Henry, 1596-1662.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 180, [3], 10 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I.N. for Hu. Mosley ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1645.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Printed and published according to order."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:102619:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:102619:1"/>
            <p>POEMS, &amp;c. WRITTEN BY Mr. <hi>ED. WALLER</hi> of <hi>Beckonsfield,</hi> Eſquire; Lately a Member of the Honourable Houſe of Commons.</p>
            <p>And Printed by a Copy of his own hand-writing.</p>
            <p>All the Lyrick Poems in this Booke were ſet by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. HENRY LAVVES, Gent. of the Kings Chappell, and one of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Private Muſick.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed and Publiſhed according to Order.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>I. N.</hi> for <hi>Hu. Moſley,</hi> at the Princes Armes in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, 1645.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:102619:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:102619:2"/>
            <head>To my Lady.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Our Commands for the ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering of theſe ſticks in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Paggot, had ſooner been obeyed, but intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to preſent you with my whole Vintage: I ſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d till the lateſt Grapes were ripe, for here <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>our Ladiſhip hath not onely all I have done, but all I ever mean to doe in this kind: Not but that I may defend the attempt I have made upon Poetrie by the examples (not to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rouble you with Hiſtorie) of many wiſe, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orthie perſons of our own times: as Sr. <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ip Sidney,</hi> Sir <hi>Fra. Bacon,</hi> Cardinall <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on,</hi> the ableſt of his Countrie-men; and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ormer Pope, who they ſay, inſtead of the
<pb facs="tcp:102619:3"/>triple Crown, wore ſometimes the Poets Ivie, as an ornament, perhaps of leſser weight, and trouble. But Madam, theſe Nightingales ſung onely in the Spring, it was the diverſion of their youth. As Ladies learn to ſing and play when they are Children, what they forget when they are women; The reſemblance holds further: for as you quit the Lute the ſooner, becauſe the poſture is ſuſpected to draw the body awry: ſo this is not alwayes practiſed without ſome villany to the mind, wreſting it from preſent occaſions, and accuſtoming us to a Still ſomewhat removed from common uſe. But that you may not think his caſe deplora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, who had made verſes: we are told that <hi>Tully</hi> (the greateſt wit among the Romans) was once ſick of this diſeaſe, and yet recovered ſo well<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that of almoſt as bad a Poet as your Servant, he became the moſt perfect Oratour
<pb facs="tcp:102619:3"/>in the world. So that not ſo much to have made verſes, as not to give over in time, leaves a man without excuſe: the former pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting us with an opportunity at leaſt of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wiſely: that is to conceale thoſe we have made, which I ſhall yet doe, if my humble re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest may be of as much force with your La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſhip, as your Commands have been with me; Madam, I onely whiſper theſe in your ears: if you publiſh them, they are your own, and therefore as you apprehend the reproach of a Wit, and a Poet, caſt them into the fire, or if they come where green boughs are in the Chimney, with the help of your faire friends, (for thus bound, it will be to hard a taske for your ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds alone) to tearethem in pieces, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you ſhall honour me with the fate of <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheus,</hi> for ſo his Poems, whereof we onely heare the forme (not his limbs as the ſtorie
<pb facs="tcp:102619:4"/>will have it) I ſuppoſe were ſcattered by the <hi>Thracian</hi> Dames. Here Madam I might take an opportunitie to Celebrate your vertues, and to inſtruct you how unhâppie you are, in that you know not who you are: How much you excell the moſt excellent of your own: And how much you amaze the leaſt inclined to wonder of our Sex. But as they will be apt to take your Ladiſhip for a Roman name: So would they believe that I indeavoured the Character of a perfect Nimph, worſhipt an Image of my own making, and Dedicated this to the Ladie of the brain, not of the heart of your Ladiſhips moſt humble ſervant,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>E. W.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:102619:4"/>
            <head>An advertiſement to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Eader. This parcell of exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit poems, have paſſ'd up and downe through many hands amongſt perſons of the beſt quallity, in looſe imperfect Manuſcripts, and there is lately obtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the world an adulterate Copy, ſurruptitiouſly and illegally imprinted, to the derogation of the Author, and the abuſe of the Buyer. But in this booke they apeare in their pure originalls and true genuine colours. In ſo much that they feare not (as young Eaglets uſe to be tryed whither they are ſpurious, or of a right extraction) to look upon the
<pb facs="tcp:102619:5"/>
               <hi>Sun</hi> in the Meridian, in regard <hi>Apollo</hi> himſelfe, the grand Patron of Poets ſeemd not only to caſt many favourable aſpects, but by his more then ordinary influence to cooperate in their produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; as will appeare to the intelligent and cleare-ſighted Reader, by that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant veine of <hi>gold</hi> (the minerall which that planet ownes more then any other) which runnes through every one of them.</p>
            <p>Thus they go abroad unſophiſticated, and like the preſent condition of the Author himſelfe they are expos'd to the wide world, to travell<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and try their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes: And I beleeve there is no gentle ſoule that pretends any thing to know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and the choyceſt ſort of invention but will give them entertainment and wellcome.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:102619:5"/>
            <head>POEMS.</head>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Of the danger his Majeſtie (being Prince) eſcaped at the rode at St. <hi>Andere.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow had his Highnes bid farewell to Spaine</l>
                  <l>And reach't the ſphere of his owne power, the Main;</l>
                  <l>With Brittiſh bounty in his ſhip hee feaſts</l>
                  <l>Th' Heſperian Princes, his amazed ghueſts.</l>
                  <l>To finde that watry wildernes exceed,</l>
                  <l>The entertainments of their great Madrid.</l>
                  <l>Healths to both Kings, attended with the rore</l>
                  <l>Of Canons, echo'd from th' affrighted ſhore.</l>
                  <l>With loud reſemblance of his Thunder, prove</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>acchus</hi> the ſeed of cloud compelling <hi>Jove;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:102619:6"/>
                  <l>While to his harp divine Arion ſings</l>
                  <l>The loves and conqueſts of our <hi>Albion</hi> Kings:</l>
                  <l>"Of the fourth <hi>Edward</hi> was his noble ſong,</l>
                  <l>"Fierce, goodly, valiant, beautifull and young.</l>
                  <l>"He rent the Crowne from vanquiſht <hi>Henry's</hi> head,</l>
                  <l>"Rais'd the white Roſe, and trampled on the red:</l>
                  <l>"Till love triumphing ore the victors pride</l>
                  <l>"Brought <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Warwick</hi> to the conquer'd ſide.</l>
                  <l>"Neglected <hi>Warwick</hi> (whoſe bold hand like Fate</l>
                  <l>"Gives and reſumes the ſcepter of our State)</l>
                  <l>"Woes for his Maiſter, and with double ſhame</l>
                  <l>"Himſelfe deluded mocks the Princely Dame</l>
                  <l>"The Lady <hi>Bona,</hi> whom iuſt anger burnes</l>
                  <l>"And forein warre with civill rage returnes.</l>
                  <l>"Ah ſpare your ſwords, where beauty is to blame,</l>
                  <l>"Love gave th' affront, and muſt repaire the ſame,</l>
                  <l>"When <hi>Fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce</hi> ſhal boaſt of her whoſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quering eye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>"Have made the beſt of Engliſh hearts their prize,</l>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:102619:6"/>
                  <l>"Have power to alter the decree of fate,</l>
                  <l>"And change againe the Counſells of our State.</l>
                  <l>What the Prophetick Muſe intends; alone</l>
                  <l>To him that feeles the ſecret wound is knowne.</l>
                  <l>With the ſweete ſound of this harmonious lay</l>
                  <l>About the Keele delighted <hi>Dolphins</hi> play;</l>
                  <l>Too ſure a ſigne of ſeas enſuing rage</l>
                  <l>Which muſt anon this Royall troup ingage.</l>
                  <l>To whom ſoft ſleepe ſeemes more ſecure and ſweete</l>
                  <l>Within the Towne commanded by our fleete.</l>
                  <l>Theſe mighty Peeres plac'd in the guilded Barge,</l>
                  <l>Proud with the burden of ſo brave a charge,</l>
                  <l>With painted Oares the youth begin to ſweep</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Neptunes</hi> ſmooth face and cleave the yeilding deep,</l>
                  <l>Which ſoone becomes the ſeate of ſudden warre</l>
                  <l>Betwixt the winde and tide, that fiercely jarre.</l>
                  <l>As when a ſort of luſty ſhepheards try</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>heir force at footeball, care of victory</l>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:102619:7"/>
                  <l>Makes them ſalute ſo rudely breſt to breſt,</l>
                  <l>That their encounters ſeeme too rough for jeſt.</l>
                  <l>They ply their feete, and ſtill the reſtles ball</l>
                  <l>Toſt to and fro is urged by them all:</l>
                  <l>So fares the doubtfull Barge twixt tide and windes,</l>
                  <l>And like effect of their contention findes.</l>
                  <l>Yet the bold <hi>Britans</hi> ſtill ſecurely row'd,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Charles</hi> and his vertue was their ſacred load.</l>
                  <l>Then which a greater pledge heaven could not give,</l>
                  <l>That the good boate this Tempeſts ſhould out live.</l>
                  <l>But ſtormes increaſe, and now no hope of grace</l>
                  <l>Among them ſhines, ſave in the Princes face.</l>
                  <l>The reſt reſigne their courage, skill, and ſight,</l>
                  <l>To danger, horror, and unwelcome night:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The gentle veſſell wont with ſtate and pride</l>
                  <l>On the ſmooth back of ſilver Thames to ride,</l>
                  <l>Wanders aſtoniſht through the angry Main,</l>
                  <l>As <hi>Titans</hi> carre did, while the golden raine</l>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:102619:7"/>
                  <l>Fil'd the young hand of his adventurous ſonne,</l>
                  <l>When the whole world an equall hazard runne.</l>
                  <l>To this of ours, the light of whoſe deſire</l>
                  <l>Waves threaten now as that was skard by fire.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Th' impatient Sea growes impotent and raves,</l>
                  <l>That (night aſſiſting) his impetuous waves</l>
                  <l>Should finde reſiſtance from ſo light a thing,</l>
                  <l>Theſe ſurges ruine, thoſe our ſafety bring.</l>
                  <l>Th' oppreſſed veſſell doth the charge abide,</l>
                  <l>Only becauſe aſſail'd on every ſide.</l>
                  <l>So men with rage and paſſion ſet on fire</l>
                  <l>Trembling for haſte, impeach their mad deſire.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The pale <hi>Iberians</hi> had expir'd with feare,</l>
                  <l>But that their wonder did divert their care,</l>
                  <l>To ſee the Prince with danger mov'd no more,</l>
                  <l>Then with the pleaſures of their Court before;</l>
                  <l>God-like his courage ſeem'd, whom nor delight</l>
                  <l>Could ſoften, nor the face of death affright.</l>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:102619:8"/>
                  <l>Next to the power of making tempeſts ceaſe,</l>
                  <l>Was in that ſtorme to have ſo calme a peace.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Great <hi>Maro</hi> could no greater tempeſt fain,</l>
                  <l>When the lowd winds uſurping on the Main</l>
                  <l>For angry <hi>Juno</hi> labour'd to deſtroy</l>
                  <l>The hated reliques of confounded <hi>Troy:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>His bold <hi>Aeneas</hi> on like billowes toſt,</l>
                  <l>In a tall ſhip and all his countries loſt,</l>
                  <l>Diſſolves with fear, and both his hands upheld</l>
                  <l>Proclaimes them happy whom the Greekes had quell'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In honorable fight: Our Hero ſet</l>
                  <l>In a ſmall ſhallop, Fortune in his debt,</l>
                  <l>So neare a hope of crownes and ſcepters more</l>
                  <l>Then ever <hi>Priam,</hi> when he flouriſh'd, wore.</l>
                  <l>His loines yet full of ungot Princes, all</l>
                  <l>His glory in the bud, lets nothing fall</l>
                  <l>That argues fear: if any thought annoyes</l>
                  <l>The gallant youth 'tis loves untaſted ioyes,</l>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:102619:8"/>
                  <l>And deare remembrance of that fatall glance</l>
                  <l>For which hee lately pawn'd his heart in <hi>France,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Where he had ſeen a brighter Nymph then ſhee</l>
                  <l>That ſprung out of his preſent foe, the Sea.</l>
                  <l>That noble ardour more then mortall fire</l>
                  <l>The Conquer'd <hi>Ocean</hi> could not make expire:</l>
                  <l>Nor angry <hi>Thetis</hi> raiſe her waves above</l>
                  <l>The Heroique Prince his courage or his love.</l>
                  <l>'Twas indignation and not feare hee felt</l>
                  <l>The ſhirine ſhould periſh where that Image dwelt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Ah Love forbid the nobleſt of thy train,</l>
                  <l>Should not ſurvive to let her know his pain,</l>
                  <l>Who nor his perill minding, nor his flame</l>
                  <l>Is entertain'd with ſome leſſe ſerious game</l>
                  <l>Among the bright nymphs of the <hi>Gallick</hi> Court,</l>
                  <l>All highly borne, obſequious to her ſport.</l>
                  <l>They roſes ſeem, which in their early pride</l>
                  <l>But halfe reveale and halfe their beauties hide.</l>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:102619:9"/>
                  <l>Shee the glad morning, which her beames doth throw.</l>
                  <l>Upon their ſmiling leaves, and gild them ſo</l>
                  <l>Like bright <hi>Aurora,</hi> whoſe refulgent ray</l>
                  <l>Foretells the fervour of enſuing day,</l>
                  <l>And warnes the ſhepherd with his flockes retreat</l>
                  <l>To leavy ſhadowes from the threatned heat.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>From <hi>Cupids</hi> ſtring of many ſhafts that fled,</l>
                  <l>Wing'd with thoſe plumes which noble fame had ſhed,</l>
                  <l>As through the wondring world ſhe flew and told</l>
                  <l>Of his adventures haughty, brave, and bold.</l>
                  <l>Some had already toucht the royall Maide,</l>
                  <l>But loves firſt ſummons ſeldome are obey'd.</l>
                  <l>Light was the wound, the Prince his care unknowne,</l>
                  <l>She might not, would not, yet reveale her owne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>His glorious name had ſo poſſeſt her eares,</l>
                  <l>That with delight thoſe antique tales ſhe heares</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Iaſon, Theſeus,</hi> and ſuch worthies old,</l>
                  <l>As with his ſtory beſt reſemblance hold.</l>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:102619:9"/>
                  <l>And now ſhe views as on the wall it hung,</l>
                  <l>What old <hi>Muſeus</hi> ſo divinely ſung,</l>
                  <l>Which art with life and love did ſo inſpire,</l>
                  <l>That ſhee diſcernes and favours that deſire.</l>
                  <l>Which there provokes th' adventerous youth to ſwim,</l>
                  <l>And in <hi>Leanders</hi> danger pitties him,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe not new love alone, but fortune ſeekes</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For from the ſterne of ſome good ſhip appeares</l>
                  <l>A freindly light, which moderates their feares.</l>
                  <l>New courage from reviving hope they take,</l>
                  <l>And climbing o're the waves that taper make,</l>
                  <l>On which the hope of all their lives depends,</l>
                  <l>As his on that faire <hi>Heros</hi> hand extends.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The ſhip at anchor like a fixed rock,</l>
                  <l>Breakes the proud billowes, which her large ſides knock;</l>
                  <l>Whoſe rage reſtrained foming higher ſwells,</l>
                  <l>And from her port the weary barge repells.</l>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:102619:10"/>
                  <l>Threatning to make her forced out againe</l>
                  <l>Repeate the dangers of the troubled Maine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Twice was the cable hurld in vaine, the Fates</l>
                  <l>Would not bee moved for our ſiſter States.</l>
                  <l>For <hi>England</hi> is the third ſuccesfull throw,</l>
                  <l>And then the <hi>Genius</hi> of that land they know.</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Prince muſt bee (as their owne bookes device)</l>
                  <l>Lord of the <hi>Scene</hi> where now his danger lyes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Well ſung the Roman Bard, all humane things</l>
                  <l>Of deareſt value hang on ſlender ſtrings.</l>
                  <l>O ſee the then ſole hope, and in deſigne</l>
                  <l>Of heaven our ioy ſupported by a line,</l>
                  <l>Which for that inſtant was heavens care above</l>
                  <l>The chaine that's fixed to the throne of <hi>Jove,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>On which the fabrick of our world depends;</l>
                  <l>One linke diſſolv'd the whole creation ends.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:102619:10"/>
               <head>Of his Majeſties receiving the newes of the Duke of <hi>Buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inghams</hi> death.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>SO earneſt with thy God! can no new care</l>
                  <l>Nor ſenſe of danger, interrupt thy prayer?</l>
                  <l>The ſacred wreſtler, till a bleſſing given,</l>
                  <l>Quits not his hold, but halting conquers heaven.</l>
                  <l>Nor was the ſtreame of thy devotion ſtop'd</l>
                  <l>When from the body ſuch a limb was lop'd,</l>
                  <l>As to thy preſent ſtate was no leſſe maime,</l>
                  <l>Though thy wiſe choyce has ſince repair'd the ſame.</l>
                  <l>Bold <hi>Homor</hi> durſt not ſo great vertue fain</l>
                  <l>In his beſt patterne for <hi>Patroclus</hi> ſlain.</l>
                  <l>With ſuch amazement as weake mothers uſe</l>
                  <l>And frantick geſture hee receives the newes.</l>
                  <l>Yet fell his darling by th' impartiall chance</l>
                  <l>Of warre impos'd by royall <hi>Hectors</hi> lance.</l>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:102619:11"/>
                  <l>Thine in full peace, and by a vulgar hand</l>
                  <l>Torne from thy boſome, left his high command.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The famous Painter could allow no place</l>
                  <l>For private ſorrow in a Princes face.</l>
                  <l>Yet that his piece might not exceed beleife,</l>
                  <l>Hee caſt a vaile upon ſuppoſed greife.</l>
                  <l>T' was want of ſuch a preſident as this</l>
                  <l>Made the old heathen frame their Gods amiſſe.</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>Phaebus</hi> ſhould not act a fonder part,</l>
                  <l>For the faire boy, then he did for his Hart:</l>
                  <l>Nor blame for <hi>Hyacinthus</hi> fate his owne,</l>
                  <l>That kept him fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wiſh'd death, hadſt thou bin known.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet hee that weighs with thine good <hi>Davids</hi> deeds,</l>
                  <l>Shall finde his paſſion, not his love exceeds.</l>
                  <l>He curſt the Mountaines where his brave friend dy'd,</l>
                  <l>But lets falſe <hi>Ziba</hi> with his heire divide:</l>
                  <l>Where thy immortall love to thy bleſt freinds</l>
                  <l>Like that of heaven upon the ſeede deſcends.</l>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:102619:11"/>
                  <l>Such huge extremes inhabit thy great minde</l>
                  <l>God-like unmov'd, and yet like woman kinde.</l>
                  <l>Which of the ancient Poets had not brought</l>
                  <l>Our <hi>Charles</hi> his pedegree from heaven, and taught</l>
                  <l>How ſome bright dame compreſt by mighty <hi>Jove,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Produc'd this mix'd Divinity and Love.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>To the King on his Navy.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVHere ere thy Navy ſpreads her canvas wings</l>
                  <l>Homage to thee, and peace to all ſhe brings</l>
                  <l>The French and Spaniard, when thy flaggs appeare</l>
                  <l>Forget their hatred, and conſent to feare.</l>
                  <l>So <hi>Jove</hi> from <hi>Ida</hi> did both hoſts ſurvey,</l>
                  <l>And when hee pleas'd to thunder, part the fray.</l>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:102619:12"/>
                  <l>Ships heretofore in ſeas like fiſhes ſped</l>
                  <l>The mightieſt ſtill upon the ſmalleſt fed.</l>
                  <l>Thou on the deepe impoſeſt ſtricter lawes,</l>
                  <l>And by that iuſtice haſt remov'd the cauſe</l>
                  <l>Of thoſe rude tempeſts, which for rapine ſent</l>
                  <l>Too oft (alas) involv'd the innocent.</l>
                  <l>Now ſhall the Ocean as thy Thames bee free</l>
                  <l>From both thoſe fates of ſtormes and Piracy.</l>
                  <l>But wee moſt happy, who can feare no force</l>
                  <l>But winged troopes or <hi>Pegaſean</hi> horſe.</l>
                  <l>Tis not ſo hard for greedy foes to ſpoil</l>
                  <l>Another nation as to touch our ſoil.</l>
                  <l>Should natures ſelfe invade the world againe,</l>
                  <l>And ore the Center ſpread the liquid Maine,</l>
                  <l>Thy power were ſafe, and her diſtractive hand</l>
                  <l>Would but enlarge the bounds of thy command.</l>
                  <l>Thy dreadfull fleete would ſtile thee Lord of all,</l>
                  <l>And ride in triumph ore the drowned ball.</l>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:102619:12"/>
                  <l>Thoſe towers of oake ore fertile plaines might goe,</l>
                  <l>And viſit mountaines where they once did grow.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The worlds reſtorer once could not endure</l>
                  <l>That finiſht <hi>Babel</hi> ſhould thoſe men ſecure,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe pride deſign'd that fabrick to have ſtood</l>
                  <l>Above the reach of any ſecond flood.</l>
                  <l>To thee his choſen more indulgent hee</l>
                  <l>Dares truſt ſuch power with ſo much piety.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Vpon his Majeſties repai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of Pauls.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THat ſhipwrackt veſſell which th' Apoſtle bore,</l>
                  <l>Scarce ſuffer'd more upon <hi>Melita's</hi> ſhore,</l>
                  <l>Then did his Temple in the ſea of time.</l>
                  <l>(Our Nations glory, and our Nations crime)</l>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:102619:13"/>
                  <l>When the firſt Monarch of this happy Iſle,</l>
                  <l>Mov'd with the ruine of ſo brave a pile,</l>
                  <l>This worke of coſt and piety begun,</l>
                  <l>To be accompliſh'd by his glorious ſonne,</l>
                  <l>Who all that came within the ample thought</l>
                  <l>Of his wiſe Sire, has to perfection brought.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>He like <hi>Amphion</hi> makes thoſe quarries leape</l>
                  <l>Into faire figures from a confus'd heape:</l>
                  <l>For in his art of regiment is found</l>
                  <l>A power like that of harmony in ſound.</l>
                  <l>Thoſe antique minſtrills ſure were <hi>Charles</hi>-like Kings,</l>
                  <l>Cities their Lutes, and Subjects hearts their ſtrings,</l>
                  <l>On which, with ſo divine a hand they ſtrooke,</l>
                  <l>Conſent of motion from their breath they tooke:</l>
                  <l>So all our mindes with his, conſpire, to grace</l>
                  <l>The gentiles great Apoſtle, and deface,</l>
                  <l>Thoſe ſtate obſcuring ſheds, that like a chaine,</l>
                  <l>Seem'd to confine, and fetter him againe:</l>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:102619:13"/>
                  <l>Which the glad Saint ſhakes off at his command,</l>
                  <l>As once the viper from his ſacred hand.</l>
                  <l>So ioyes the aged oak when wee divide</l>
                  <l>The creeping Ivy from his injur'd ſide.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Ambition rather would effect the fame</l>
                  <l>Of ſome new ſtructure to have borne her name.</l>
                  <l>Two diſtant vertues in one act we finde,</l>
                  <l>The modeſty and greatneſſe of his minde.</l>
                  <l>Which not content to bee above the rage</l>
                  <l>And iniury of all impayring age;</l>
                  <l>In its owne worth ſecure, doth higher clime,</l>
                  <l>And things halfe ſwallow'd from the jawes of time,</l>
                  <l>Reduce an earneſt of his grand deſigne,</l>
                  <l>To frame no new Church, but the old refine;</l>
                  <l>Which ſpouſe-like may with comely grace command</l>
                  <l>More then by force of argument or hand:</l>
                  <l>For doubtfull reaſon few can apprehend,</l>
                  <l>And warr brings ruine where it ſhould amend.</l>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:102619:14"/>
                  <l>But beauty with a bloodleſs conqueſt findes</l>
                  <l>A welcome ſoveraignty in rudeſt mindes.</l>
                  <l>Not ought which <hi>Sheba's</hi> wondring Queene beheld</l>
                  <l>Among the workes of <hi>Solomon</hi> exceld</l>
                  <l>His Ships and building, Emblems of a heart</l>
                  <l>Large both in magnanimity and art.</l>
                  <l>While the propitious heavens this worke attend,</l>
                  <l>Long wanted ſhowers, they forget to fend:</l>
                  <l>As if they meant to make it underſtood</l>
                  <l>Of more importance then our vitall food.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Sun which riſeth to ſalute the Quire</l>
                  <l>Already finiſh'd, ſetting ſhall admire</l>
                  <l>How private bounty could ſo far extend,</l>
                  <l>The KING built all but <hi>Charles</hi> the weſtern end<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>So proud a Fabrick to devotion given,</l>
                  <l>At once it threatneth and obligeth Heaven.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Laomedon</hi> that had the Gods in pay,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Neptune</hi> with him that rules the ſacred day,</l>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:102619:14"/>
                  <l>Could no ſuch ſtructure raiſe, <hi>Troy</hi> wald ſo high,</l>
                  <l>Th' <hi>Atrides</hi> might as well have forc'd the sky.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Glad, though amazed, are our neighbour Kings,</l>
                  <l>To ſee ſuch power imploy'd in peacefull things.</l>
                  <l>They liſt not urge it to the dreadfull field:</l>
                  <l>The taske is eaſier to deſtroy, then build.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>To the Queene occaſioned upon ſight of her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Picture.</head>
               <l>VVEll fare the hand which to our humble ſight</l>
               <l>Preſents that beauty, which the dazeling light</l>
               <l>Of Royall ſplendor hides from weaker eyes,</l>
               <l>And all acceſſe (ſave by this art) denyes.</l>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:102619:15"/>
               <l>Here only we have courage to behold</l>
               <l>This beame of glory, here we dare unfold</l>
               <l>In numbers thus the wonders wee conceive,</l>
               <l>The gracious Image ſeeming to give leave,</l>
               <l>Propitious ſtands vouchſafing to bee ſeene</l>
               <l>And by our Muſe ſaluted<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> MIGHTY QUEEN.</l>
               <l>In whom th'extreames of power and beauty move,</l>
               <l>The Queen of Britaine and the Queen of Love.</l>
               <l>As the Bright Sun (to which we owe no ſight</l>
               <l>Of equall glory to your beauties light.)</l>
               <l>Is wiſely plac't in ſo ſublime a ſeat</l>
               <l>T'extend his light and moderate his heat.</l>
               <l>So happy t'is you move in ſuch a ſpheare</l>
               <l>As your high Majeſty with awfull feare,</l>
               <l>In humane breſts might qualify that fire,</l>
               <l>Which kindled by thoſe eyes had flamed higher.</l>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:102619:15"/>
               <l>Then when the ſcortched world like hazard run</l>
               <l>By the approach of the ill guided Sun.</l>
               <l>No other nimphs have title to mens hearts</l>
               <l>But as their meanes larger hope imparts.</l>
               <l>Your beauty more the fondeſt lover moves</l>
               <l>With admiration then his private loves.</l>
               <l>With admiration, for a pitch ſo high</l>
               <l>(Save ſacred <hi>Charles</hi> his) never love durſt fly.</l>
               <l>Heaven that perfer'd a ſcepter to your hand</l>
               <l>Favour'd our freedome, more then your command.</l>
               <l>Beauty had Crown'd you, and you muſt have bin</l>
               <l>The whole worlds Miſtreſſe other then a Queen.</l>
               <l>All had bin rivalls, and you might have ſpar'd</l>
               <l>Or kild, and tyraniz'd, without a guard.</l>
               <l>No power atcheiv'd either by arms or birth</l>
               <l>Equalls loves Empire both in heaven and earth.</l>
               <l>Such eyes as yours on <hi>Jove</hi> himſelfe have throwne</l>
               <l>As bright and feirce a lightning as his owne.</l>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:102619:16"/>
               <l>Witneſs our <hi>Jove</hi> prevented by their flame</l>
               <l>In his ſwift paſſage to th' <hi>Heſperian</hi> dame.</l>
               <l>When like a Lion finding in his way</l>
               <l>To ſome intended ſpoile, a fairer pray;</l>
               <l>The Royall youth purſuing the report</l>
               <l>Of beauty found it in the Gallick Court.</l>
               <l>There publique care with private paſſion fought</l>
               <l>A doubtfull Combate in his noble thought.</l>
               <l>Should hee confeſſe his greatnes, and his love,</l>
               <l>And the free faith of your great Brother prove,</l>
               <l>With his <hi>Achates</hi> breaking through the cloud</l>
               <l>Of that diſguiſe which did their graces ſhrow'd,</l>
               <l>And mixing with thoſe gallants at the Ball</l>
               <l>Daunce with the Ladies, and outſhine them all;</l>
               <l>Or on his iourny ore the mountaines ride?</l>
               <l>So when the faire <hi>Leucothoe</hi> he ſpide,</l>
               <l>To check his ſteeds impatient <hi>Phoebus</hi> earn'd,</l>
               <l>Though all the world was in his courſe concern'd.</l>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:102619:16"/>
               <l>What may hereafter her meridian doe,</l>
               <l>Whoſe dawning beauty warm'd his boſome ſo?</l>
               <l>Not ſo divine a flame, ſince deathleſſe Gods</l>
               <l>Forbore to viſit the defil'd abodes</l>
               <l>Of men, in any mortall breſt did burn;</l>
               <l>Nor ſhall, till Piety and they return.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>The Apology of Sleep for not approching the Lady who can doe any thing but ſleepe when ſhe pleaſeth.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>MY charge it is thoſe breaches to repaire,</l>
                  <l>Which nature takes from ſorrow toil and care,</l>
                  <l>Reſt to the limbs, and quiet I confer</l>
                  <l>On troubled minds, but nought can add to her,</l>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:102619:17"/>
                  <l>Whom heaven &amp; her tranſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dent thoughts have plac't</l>
                  <l>Above thoſe ills which wretched mortalls taſte.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Bright as the deathles gods, and happy ſhe</l>
                  <l>From all that may infringe, delight is free;</l>
                  <l>Love at her royall feet his quiver layes,</l>
                  <l>And not his mother with more haſte obeyes</l>
                  <l>Such reall pleaſures, ſuch true ioyes ſuſpence,</l>
                  <l>What dreame can I preſent to recompenſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Should I with lightning fill her awfull hands,</l>
                  <l>And make the Clouds ſeem, all at her commands;</l>
                  <l>Or place her in <hi>Olympus</hi> top a gueſt,</l>
                  <l>Among th' immortalls, who with <hi>Nectar</hi> feaſt;</l>
                  <l>That power would ſeem, that entertainement ſhort</l>
                  <l>Of the true ſplendor of her preſent Court;</l>
                  <l>Where all the ioyes, and all the glories are</l>
                  <l>Of three great Kingdomes ſever'd from the care.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I that of fumes and humid vapours made,</l>
                  <l>Aſcending to the ſeat of ſenſe invade,</l>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:102619:17"/>
                  <l>No cloud in ſo ſerene a manſion finde,</l>
                  <l>To overcaſt her ever ſhining minde,</l>
                  <l>Which holds reſemblance with thoſe ſpotles skies,</l>
                  <l>Where flowing <hi>Nilus</hi> want of rain ſupplyes.</l>
                  <l>That Cryſtall heaven where <hi>Phoebus</hi> never ſhrowds</l>
                  <l>His golden beames, nor wrapps his face in clouds.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But what's ſo hard which numbers cannot force,</l>
                  <l>So ſtoops the Moone, and rivers change their courſe.</l>
                  <l>The bold <hi>Meonian</hi> made mee dare to ſteep</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Joves</hi> dreadfull tempies in the dew of ſleep.</l>
                  <l>And ſince the Muſes doe invoke my power,</l>
                  <l>I ſhall no more decline that ſacred bower;</l>
                  <l>Where <hi>Gloriana</hi> their great miſtris lyes,</l>
                  <l>But gently taming thoſe victorious eyes.</l>
                  <l>Charm all her ſenſes, till the ioyfull Sun</l>
                  <l>Without a Rivall halfe his courſe has run:</l>
                  <l>Who while my hand that fairer light confines,</l>
                  <l>May boaſt himſelfe the brighteſt thing that ſhines.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:102619:18"/>
               <head>The Country to my Lady of Carliſle.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Madam,</salute>
               </opener>
               <lg>
                  <l>OF all the ſacred Muſe inſpir'd</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Orpheus</hi> alone could with the woods comply,</l>
                  <l>Their rude inhabitants his ſong admir'd,</l>
                  <l>And natures ſelfe in thoſe that could not lye.</l>
                  <l>Your beauty next our ſolitude invades</l>
                  <l>And warmes us, ſhining through the thickeſt ſhades.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Nor ought the tribute which the wondring Court</l>
                  <l>Payes your faire eyes, prevaile with you to ſcorne</l>
                  <l>The anſwer and conſent to the report</l>
                  <l>Which Echo-like the Country doth returne.</l>
                  <l>Mirrors are taught to flatter, but our ſprings</l>
                  <l>Preſent th' impartiall images of things.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:102619:18"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>A rurall Judge diſpos'd of beauties prize;</l>
                  <l>A ſimple ſhepherd was prefer'd to <hi>Jove:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Downe to the Mountaines from the partiall skyes</l>
                  <l>Came <hi>Juno, Pallas,</hi> and the Queen of Love,</l>
                  <l>To pleade for that which was ſo iuſtly given</l>
                  <l>To the bright <hi>Carliſle</hi> of the Court of heaven.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Carliſle,</hi> a name which all our woods are taught</l>
                  <l>Loud as his <hi>Amaryllis</hi> to reſound:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Carliſle,</hi> a name which on the barke is wrought</l>
                  <l>Of every tree that's worthy of the wound.</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Phoebus</hi> rage our ſhadowes and our ſtreames</l>
                  <l>May guard us better, then from <hi>Carliſles</hi> beames.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:102619:19"/>
               <head>The Counteſſe of Carliſle in mourning.</head>
               <l>WHen from black clouds no part of sky is clear,</l>
               <l>But juſt ſo much as letts the Sun apear:</l>
               <l>Heaven then would ſeeme thy image, and reflect</l>
               <l>Thoſe ſable veſtments, and that bright aſpect:</l>
               <l>A ſparke of vertue by the deepeſt ſhade</l>
               <l>Of ſad adverſity is fairer made.</l>
               <l>Nor leſſe advantage doth thy beauty get,</l>
               <l>A <hi>Venus</hi> riſing from a ſea of jet.</l>
               <l>Such was th' appearance of new formed light</l>
               <l>While yet it ſtrugled with eternall night.</l>
               <l>Then mourn no more leſt thou admit increaſe</l>
               <l>Of glory by thy noble Lords deceaſe.</l>
               <l>We finde not that the laughter-loving dame</l>
               <l>Mourn'd for <hi>Anchiſes,</hi> t'was enough ſhe came,</l>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:102619:19"/>
               <l>To grace the mortall with her deathles bed,</l>
               <l>And that his living eyes ſuch beauty fed.</l>
               <l>Had ſhee bin there, untimely joy through all</l>
               <l>Mens hearts difus'd, had marr'd the funerall.</l>
               <l>Thoſe eyes were made to baniſh greife; as well</l>
               <l>Bright <hi>Phoebus</hi> might affect in ſhades to dwell,</l>
               <l>As they to put on ſorrow: nothing ſtands</l>
               <l>But power to greive, exempt from thy commands.</l>
               <l>If thou lament, thou muſt do ſo alone,</l>
               <l>Greife in thy preſence can lay hold on none.</l>
               <l>Yet ſtill perſiſt the memory to love</l>
               <l>Of that great Mercury of our mighty <hi>Jove;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who by the power of his enchaunting tongue</l>
               <l>Swords from the hands of threatning Monarchs wru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g.</l>
               <l>Warr he prevented, or ſoone made it ceaſe,</l>
               <l>Inſtructing Princes in the art of peace.</l>
               <l>Such as made <hi>Sheb' as</hi> curious Queen reſort</l>
               <l>To the large-hearted <hi>Hebrews</hi> famous Court.</l>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:102619:20"/>
               <l>Had <hi>Homer</hi> ſat among his wondring gheſts,</l>
               <l>Hee might have learn'd at thoſe ſtupendious feaſts,</l>
               <l>With greater bounty and more ſacred ſtate</l>
               <l>The banquets of the gods to celebrate.</l>
               <l>But ô what elocution might hee uſe,</l>
               <l>What potent charmes that could ſo ſoone infuſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>His abſent Maſters love into the heart</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Henrietta,</hi> forcing her to part</l>
               <l>From her lov'd brother, Countrey, and the ſun,</l>
               <l>And like <hi>Camilla</hi> ore the waves to run</l>
               <l>Into his armes, while the Pariſian dames</l>
               <l>Mourne for their raviſht glory at her flames,</l>
               <l>No leſſe amazed then the amazed ſtars</l>
               <l>When the bold charmer of <hi>Theſſalia</hi> wars</l>
               <l>With heaven it ſelfe, and numbers does repeate</l>
               <l>Which call deſcending <hi>Cynthia</hi> from her ſeate.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:102619:20"/>
               <head>In Anſwer to a libell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt her, &amp;c.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVHat fury has provok'd thy wit to dare</l>
                  <l>With <hi>Diomed</hi> to wound the queen of love?</l>
                  <l>Thy Miſtris envy, or thy owne deſpaire,</l>
                  <l>Not the juſt <hi>Pallas</hi> in thy breſt did move</l>
                  <l>So blind a rage with ſuch a different fate:</l>
                  <l>He honour won, where thou haſt purchaſt hate.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>She gave aſſiſtance to his <hi>Trojan</hi> foe,</l>
                  <l>Thou that without a rivall thou maiſt love,</l>
                  <l>Doſt to the beauty of this Lady owe</l>
                  <l>While after her the gazing world does move.</l>
                  <l>Canſt thou not bee content to love alone?</l>
                  <l>Or is thy Miſtris not content with one?</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:102619:21"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Haſt thou not read of <hi>Tagry Arthurs</hi> ſheild,</l>
                  <l>Which but diſelos'd amaz'd the weaker eyes,</l>
                  <l>Of proudeſt foe, and won the doubtfull field:</l>
                  <l>So ſhall thy rebell with become her prize.</l>
                  <l>Should thy Iambicks ſwell into a book</l>
                  <l>All were confuted with one radiant look.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Heaven hee oblig'd, that plac't her in the skyes,</l>
                  <l>Rewarding <hi>Phoebus</hi> for inſpiring ſo</l>
                  <l>His noble braine, likening to thoſe eyes</l>
                  <l>His ioyfull beames. But <hi>Phoebus</hi> is thy ſo,</l>
                  <l>And neither aydes they fancy, nor thy ſight:</l>
                  <l>So ill thou rhim'ſt againſt ſo faire a light.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:102619:21"/>
               <head>On my Lady Dorothy Sidneys Picture.</head>
               <l>SUch was <hi>Philocleas,</hi> ſuch <hi>Dorus</hi>'s flame,</l>
               <l>The matchleſſe <hi>Sidney</hi> that immortall frame</l>
               <l>Of perfect beauty on two pillars plac't</l>
               <l>Not his high fancy, could one patterne grac't</l>
               <l>With ſuch extreames of excellence compoſe</l>
               <l>Wonders ſo diſtant in one face diſcloſe.</l>
               <l>Such chearefull modeſty, ſuch humble State</l>
               <l>Moves certaine love, but with a doubtfull fate.</l>
               <l>As when beyond our greedy reach we ſee</l>
               <l>Inviting fruite on too ſublime a tree.</l>
               <l>All the rich flowers through his <hi>Arcadia</hi> found</l>
               <l>Amaz'd we ſee in this one garland bound.</l>
               <l>Had but this copy which the Artiſt took</l>
               <l>From the faire picture of that noble book,</l>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:102619:22"/>
               <l>Stood at <hi>Calanders,</hi> the brave friends had jar'd</l>
               <l>And rivals made th' inſuing ſtory mar'd:</l>
               <l>Iuſt nature firſt inſtructed by his thought</l>
               <l>In his owne houſe thus practis'd what hee taught.</l>
               <l>This glorious piece tranſcends what he could think:</l>
               <l>So much his blood is nobler then his Ink.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>To Vandike.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>RAre Artiſan, whoſe pencill moves</l>
                  <l>Not our delight alone, but Loves;</l>
                  <l>From thy ſhop of beauty wee</l>
                  <l>Slaves returne, that enter'd free.</l>
                  <l>The heedleſs lover does not know</l>
                  <l>Whoſe eyes they are that wound him ſo:</l>
                  <l>But confounded with thy art</l>
                  <l>Inquires her name that has his heart.</l>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:102619:22"/>
                  <l>Another who did long refrain,</l>
                  <l>Feeles his old wounds bleed freſh again</l>
                  <l>With deare remembrance of that face</l>
                  <l>Where now he reades new hopes of grace,</l>
                  <l>Nor ſcorne, nor cruelty does find,</l>
                  <l>But gladly ſuffers a falſe wind</l>
                  <l>To blow the aſhes of deſpaire</l>
                  <l>From the reviving brand of care:</l>
                  <l>Foole that forgets her ſtubborne looke;</l>
                  <l>This ſoftnes, from thy finger took.</l>
                  <l>Strange that thy hand ſhould not inſpire</l>
                  <l>The beauty only, but the fire;</l>
                  <l>Not the forme alone and grace,</l>
                  <l>But act and power of a face.</l>
                  <l>Maiſt thou yet thy ſelfe aſwell</l>
                  <l>As all the world beſide excell,</l>
                  <l>So youth' unfained truth rehearſe</l>
                  <l>(That I may make it live in verſe)</l>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:102619:23"/>
                  <l>Why thou couldſt not at one aſſay</l>
                  <l>That face to after times convey,</l>
                  <l>Which this admires: was it thy wit</l>
                  <l>To make her oft before thee ſit?</l>
                  <l>Confeſſe, and wee'l forgive thee this;</l>
                  <l>For who would not repeate that bliſſe,</l>
                  <l>And frequent fight of ſuch a Dame</l>
                  <l>Buy with the hazard of his fame.</l>
                  <l>Yet who can tax thy blameleſſe skill,</l>
                  <l>Though thy good hand had failed ſtill;</l>
                  <l>When Nature's ſelfe ſo often erers?</l>
                  <l>Shee for this many thouſand yeares</l>
                  <l>Seemes to have practis'd with much care</l>
                  <l>To frame the race of women faire,</l>
                  <l>Yet never could a perfect birth</l>
                  <l>Produce before to grace the earth:</l>
                  <l>VVhich waxed old, ere it could ſee</l>
                  <l>Her that amaz'd thy art and thee.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:102619:23"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>But now 'tis done, ô let mee know</l>
                  <l>VVhere thoſe immortall colours grow,</l>
                  <l>That could this deathleſſe piece compoſe</l>
                  <l>In Lillies, or the fading roſe.</l>
                  <l>No, for this theft thou haſt clim'd higher</l>
                  <l>Then did <hi>Prometheus</hi> for his fire.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>At Pens-hurſt.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVHile in this Parke I ſing, the liſtning Deere</l>
                  <l>Attend my paſſion, and forget to feare.</l>
                  <l>VVhen to the Beeches I report my flame,</l>
                  <l>They bow their heads as if they ſelt the ſame.</l>
                  <l>To Gods appealing when I reach their bowes</l>
                  <l>VVith loud complaints, they anſwer mee in ſhowes.</l>
                  <l>To thee a wild and cruell ſoule is given,</l>
                  <l>More deafe then trees, and prouder then the heaven<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:102619:24"/>
                  <l>Loves foe profeſt, why doſt thou faſly faine</l>
                  <l>Thy ſelfe a <hi>Sidney,</hi> from which noble ſtraine</l>
                  <l>Hee ſprung, that could ſo far exalt the name</l>
                  <l>Of Love, and warme our Nation with his flame,</l>
                  <l>That all we can of Love or high deſire</l>
                  <l>Seemes but the ſmoake of amorous <hi>Sidneys</hi> fire?</l>
                  <l>Nor call her Mother, who ſo well does prove</l>
                  <l>One breſt may hold both Chaſtity and Love.</l>
                  <l>Never can ſhee that ſo exceeds the ſpring</l>
                  <l>In ioy and bounty, be ſuppos'd to bring</l>
                  <l>One ſo deſtructive: to no humane ſtock</l>
                  <l>VVe owe this fierce unkindnes, but the rock:</l>
                  <l>That cloven rocke produc'd thee, by whoſe ſide</l>
                  <l>Nature to recompence the fatall pride</l>
                  <l>Of ſuch ſterne beauty, plac'd thoſe healing ſprings,</l>
                  <l>VVhich not more helpe, then that deſtruction brings.</l>
                  <l>Thy heart no ruder then that ragged ſtone</l>
                  <l>I might like <hi>Orpheus</hi> with my num'rous moane</l>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:102619:24"/>
                  <l>Melt to compaſſion, now my trait'rous ſong</l>
                  <l>VVith thee conſpires to doe the ſinger wrong,</l>
                  <l>VVhile thus I ſuffer not my ſelfe to loſe</l>
                  <l>The memory of what augments my woes;</l>
                  <l>But with my owne breath ſtill foment the fire</l>
                  <l>VVhich flames as high as phanſy can aſpire.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This laſt complaint th' indulgent eares does pierce</l>
                  <l>Of juſt <hi>Apollo</hi> preſident of verſe,</l>
                  <l>Highly concerned that the Muſe ſhould bring</l>
                  <l>Damage to one whom he had taught to ſing.</l>
                  <l>Thus he advis'd me, On you aged tree</l>
                  <l>Hang up thy Lute, and hie thee to the Sea,</l>
                  <l>That there with wonders thy diverted minde</l>
                  <l>Some truce at leaſt may with affection finde.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Ah cruell Nymph, from whom her humble ſwaine</l>
                  <l>Flyes for reliefe unto the raging maine!</l>
                  <l>And from the winds and tempeſts doth expect</l>
                  <l>A milder fate then from her cold neglect!</l>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:102619:25"/>
                  <l>Yet there hee'l pray that the unkind may prove</l>
                  <l>Bleſt in her choyce, and vows this endleſſe love</l>
                  <l>Springs from no hope of what ſhee can confer,</l>
                  <l>But from thoſe gifts which heaven has heap'd on her.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>At Pens-hurſt.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>HAd <hi>Dorothea</hi> liv'd when Mortals made</l>
                  <l>Choice of their Deities, this ſacred ſhade</l>
                  <l>Had held an altar to the power that gave</l>
                  <l>The peace and glory which theſe Allyes have;</l>
                  <l>Embrodered ſo with flowers where ſhe ſtood,</l>
                  <l>That it became a garden of a wood.</l>
                  <l>Their preſence has ſuch more then humane grace</l>
                  <l>That it can civilize the rudeſt place:</l>
                  <l>And beauty too and order can impart,</l>
                  <l>Where nature ne're intended it, nor art.</l>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:102619:25"/>
                  <l>The plants acknowledge this, and her admire</l>
                  <l>No leſſe then thoſe of old did <hi>Orpheus</hi> Lyre.</l>
                  <l>If ſhee ſit downe, with tops all towards her bow'd</l>
                  <l>They round about her into Arbours crow'd.</l>
                  <l>Or if ſhee walk, in even rankes they ſtand</l>
                  <l>Like ſome well marſhall'd and obſequious band.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Amphion</hi> ſo made ſtones and timber leape</l>
                  <l>Into faire figures from a confus'd heape.</l>
                  <l>And in the ſymmetry of her parts is found</l>
                  <l>A power like that of harmony in ſound.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yee lofty Beeches tell this matchleſs dame</l>
                  <l>That if together ye fed all one flame,</l>
                  <l>It could not equalize the hundreth part</l>
                  <l>Of what her eyes have kindled in my heart.</l>
                  <l>Goe boy and carve this paſſion on the barke</l>
                  <l>Of yonder tree, which ſtands the ſacred marke</l>
                  <l>Of noble <hi>Sidneys</hi> birth, when ſuch benigne,</l>
                  <l>Such more then mortall-making ſtars did ſhine,</l>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:102619:26"/>
                  <l>That there they cannot but for ever prove</l>
                  <l>The monument and pledge of humble love:</l>
                  <l>His humble love, whoſe hope ſhall ne're riſe higher,</l>
                  <l>Then for a pardon that hee dares admire.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>To my Lord of Leiceſter.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>NOt that thy trees at Penhurſt groane</l>
                  <l>Oppreſſed with their timely load,</l>
                  <l>And ſeem to make their ſilent moane,</l>
                  <l>That their great Lord is now abroad,</l>
                  <l>That to delight his taſt or eye</l>
                  <l>Would ſpend themſelves in fruite and dye.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Not that thy harmleſs Deer repine,</l>
                  <l>And thinke themſelves unjuſtly ſlaine</l>
                  <l>By any other hand then thine,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe arrows they would gladly ſtaine.</l>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:102619:26"/>
                  <l>No nor thy friends which hold too deare</l>
                  <l>That peace with France which keeps thee there.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>All theſe are leſſe then that great cauſe,</l>
                  <l>Which now exacts your preſence here,</l>
                  <l>Wherein there meete the diverſe lawes</l>
                  <l>Of publique and domeſtique care:</l>
                  <l>For one bright Nymph our youth contends,</l>
                  <l>And on your prudent choyce depends.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Not the bright ſhield of <hi>Thetis</hi> ſon,</l>
                  <l>For which ſuch ſterne debate did riſe,</l>
                  <l>That the great <hi>Aiax Talamon</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Refus'd to live without the prize;</l>
                  <l>Thoſe <hi>Achive</hi> Peeres did more ingage,</l>
                  <l>Then ſhee the Gallants of our age,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>That beame of beauty which begun</l>
                  <l>To warme us ſo, when thou wert here,</l>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:102619:27"/>
                  <l>Now ſcorches like the raging Sun</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Sirius</hi> does firſt appeare.</l>
                  <l>O fix this flame, and let deſpaire</l>
                  <l>Redeeme the reſt from endleſs care.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>To my young Lady <hi>Lucy Sidney.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVHy came I ſo untimely forth</l>
                  <l>Into a world which wanting thee</l>
                  <l>Could entertaine us with no worth</l>
                  <l>Or ſhadow of felicity?</l>
                  <l>That times ſhould mee ſo far remove</l>
                  <l>From that which I was borne to love?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet faireſt bloſſome do not ſlight</l>
                  <l>That age which you muſt know ſo ſoone,</l>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:102619:27"/>
                  <l>The roſy morne reſignes her light</l>
                  <l>And milder glory to the Noon;</l>
                  <l>And then what wonders ſhall you doe</l>
                  <l>Whoſe dawning beauty warmes us ſo?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Hope waits upon the flowry prime;</l>
                  <l>And ſummer though it be leſſe gay,</l>
                  <l>Yet is not look'd on as a time</l>
                  <l>Of declination or decay:</l>
                  <l>For with a full hand that doth bring</l>
                  <l>All that was promis'd by the ſpring.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Of the Lady who can ſleep when ſhe pleaſes.</head>
               <l>NO wonder ſleep from carefull Lovers flyes</l>
               <l>To bath himſelfe in <hi>Sachariſſa</hi>'s eyes;</l>
               <l>As faire <hi>Aſtraea</hi> once from earth to heaven</l>
               <l>By ſtrife and loud impiety was driven;</l>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:102619:28"/>
               <l>So with our plaints offended, and our teares,</l>
               <l>Wiſe <hi>Somnus</hi> to that Paradiſe repaires,</l>
               <l>Waits on her will, and wretches does forſake</l>
               <l>To court the Nymph for whom thoſe wretches wake</l>
               <l>More proud then <hi>Phoebus</hi> of his throne of gold</l>
               <l>Is the ſoft God, thoſe ſofter limbs to hold,</l>
               <l>Nor would exchange with <hi>Jove</hi> to hide the skyes</l>
               <l>In darkning clouds the power to cloſe her eyes:</l>
               <l>Eyes, which ſo farre all other lights controul:</l>
               <l>They warme our mortall parts, but theſe our ſoul.</l>
               <l>Let her free ſpirit, whoſe unconquer'd breſt</l>
               <l>Holds ſuch deep quiet, and untroubled reſt,</l>
               <l>Know, that though <hi>Venus</hi> and her Son ſhould ſpare</l>
               <l>Her rebell heart, and never teach her care;</l>
               <l>Yet <hi>Hymen</hi> may inforce her Vigils keepe,</l>
               <l>And for anothers joy ſuſpend her ſleepe.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:102619:28"/>
               <head>Of the miſreport of her being painted.</head>
               <l>AS when a ſort of Wolves infeſt the night</l>
               <l>With their wilde howlings at fair <hi>Cynthia</hi>'s light,</l>
               <l>The noiſe may chaſe ſweet ſlumber from our eyes,</l>
               <l>But never reach the Miſtris of the skyes:</l>
               <l>So with the news of <hi>Sachariſſa</hi>'s wrongs,</l>
               <l>Her vexed ſervants blame thoſe envious tongues,</l>
               <l>Call love to witneſs that no painted fire</l>
               <l>Can ſcorch men ſo, or kindle ſuch deſire;</l>
               <l>While unconcerned ſhe ſeems mov'd no more</l>
               <l>With this new malice, then our loves before:</l>
               <l>But from the height of her great minde looks down</l>
               <l>On both our paſſions without ſmile or frown;</l>
               <l>So little care of what is done below</l>
               <l>Hath the bright Dame, whom heav'n affecteth ſo,</l>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:102619:29"/>
               <l>Paints her 'tis true, with the ſame hand which ſpreads</l>
               <l>Like glorious colours through the flowry meads,</l>
               <l>When laviſh Nature with her beſt attire</l>
               <l>Cloaths the gay Spring, the ſeaſon of deſire.</l>
               <l>Paints her 'tis true, and does her cheek adorn</l>
               <l>With the ſame art wherewith ſhe paints the morn,</l>
               <l>With the ſame art, wherewith ſhe guildeth ſo</l>
               <l>Thoſe painted clouds which forme <hi>Thaumantia</hi>'s bow.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Of her paſsing through a crowd of people.</head>
               <l>AS in old Chaos, heav'n with earth confus'd,</l>
               <l>And ſtars with rocks together cruſh'd &amp; bruis'd,</l>
               <l>The Sun his light no farther could extend</l>
               <l>Then the next hill which on his ſhoulders lean'd;</l>
               <l>So in this throng bright <hi>Sachariſſa</hi> far'd,</l>
               <l>Oppreſs'd by thoſe who ſtrove to be her guard.</l>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:102619:29"/>
               <l>As ſhips, though never ſo obſequious, fall</l>
               <l>Foul in a tempeſt on their Admirall;</l>
               <l>A greater favour this diſorder brought</l>
               <l>Unto her ſervants, then their awfull thought</l>
               <l>Durſt entertain, when thus compell'd they preſt</l>
               <l>The yeelding Marble of her ſnowy breſt,</l>
               <l>While Love inſults diſguiſed in the cloud,</l>
               <l>And welcome force of the unruly croud:</l>
               <l>So th'amorous tree, while yet the ayre is calm,</l>
               <l>Juſt diſtance keeps from his deſired Palm;</l>
               <l>But when the wind her raviſht branches throws</l>
               <l>Into his armes, and mingles all their boughs,</l>
               <l>Though loth he ſeems her tender leaves to preſſe,</l>
               <l>More loth he is the friendly ſtorme ſhould ceaſe,</l>
               <l>From whoſe rude bounty he the double uſe</l>
               <l>At once receives, of pleaſure and excuſe.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="song">
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:102619:30"/>
               <head>Song.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>SAy lovely dream, where couldſt thou finde</l>
                  <l>Shales to counterfeit that face;</l>
                  <l>Colours of this glorious kinde</l>
                  <l>Come not from any mortall place.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In heaven it ſelf thou ſure wert dreſt</l>
                  <l>With that Angel-like diſguiſe:</l>
                  <l>Thus deluded am I bleſt,</l>
                  <l>And ſee my joy with cloſed eyes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But ah! this image is too kinde</l>
                  <l>To be other then a dreame,</l>
                  <l>Cruell <hi>Sachariſſa</hi>'s mindo</l>
                  <l>Never put on that ſweet extreame.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:102619:30"/>
                  <l>Faire dream, if thou intendſt me grace,</l>
                  <l>Change this heavenly forme of thine,</l>
                  <l>Paint deſpis'd love in thy face,</l>
                  <l>And make it to appeare like mine,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Pale, wan, and meager, let it looke</l>
                  <l>With a pity-moving ſhape,</l>
                  <l>Such as wander by the brooke</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Lethe,</hi> or from graves eſcape.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then to that matchleſſe Nymph appeare,</l>
                  <l>In whoſe ſhape thou ſhineſt ſo;</l>
                  <l>Softly in her ſleeping eare,</l>
                  <l>With humble words expreſſe my woe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Perhaps from greatneſſe, ſtate and pride,</l>
                  <l>Thus ſurpriſed ſhe may fall;</l>
                  <l>Sleep does diſproportion hide,</l>
                  <l>And death reſembling equals all.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="song">
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:102619:31"/>
               <head>Song.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>BEhold the brand of beauty toſt,</l>
                  <l>See how the motion does dilate the flame,</l>
                  <l>Delighted Love his ſpoiles does boaſt,</l>
                  <l>And triumph in this game:</l>
                  <l>Fire to no place confin'd,</l>
                  <l>Is both our wonder, and our feare,</l>
                  <l>Moving the minde</l>
                  <l>Like lightning hurled through the ayre.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>High heaven the glory does increaſe</l>
                  <l>Of all her ſhining Lamps this artfull way;</l>
                  <l>The Sun in figures ſuch as theſe</l>
                  <l>Joyes with the Moon to play;</l>
                  <l>To theſe ſweet ſtrains they advance,</l>
                  <l>Which do reſult from their own ſphears,</l>
                  <l>As this Nymphs dance</l>
                  <l>Moves with the numbers which ſhe hears.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:102619:31"/>
               <head>TO AMORET.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>FAire, that you may truly know</l>
                  <l>What you unto <hi>Thirſis</hi> ow,</l>
                  <l>I will tell you how I doe</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sachariſſa</hi> love and you.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Joy ſalutes me when I ſet</l>
                  <l>My bleſt eyes on <hi>Amoret,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But with wonder I am ſtrook,</l>
                  <l>When I on the other look.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If ſweet <hi>Amoret</hi> complains,</l>
                  <l>I have ſenſe of all her pains;</l>
                  <l>But for <hi>Sachariſſa,</hi> I</l>
                  <l>Doe not only grieve, but die.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:102619:32"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>All that of my ſelfe is mine,</l>
                  <l>Lovely <hi>Amoret,</hi> is thine;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sachariſſa</hi>'s captive fain</l>
                  <l>Would untie his iron chain,</l>
                  <l>And thoſe ſcorching beams to ſhun,</l>
                  <l>To thy gentle ſhadow run;</l>
                  <l>If the ſoul had free election</l>
                  <l>To diſpoſe of her affection,</l>
                  <l>I ſhould not thus long have born</l>
                  <l>Haughty <hi>Sachariſſa</hi>'s ſcorn,</l>
                  <l>But 'tis ſure ſome power above,</l>
                  <l>Which controuls our will in love,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If not Love, a ſtrong deſire</l>
                  <l>To create, and ſpread that fire</l>
                  <l>In my breaſt ſolicits mee,</l>
                  <l>Beauteous <hi>Amoret,</hi> for thee.</l>
                  <l>'Tis amazement more then love,</l>
                  <l>Which her radiant eyes doe move;</l>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:102619:32"/>
                  <l>If leſs ſplendour wait on thine,</l>
                  <l>Yet they ſo benignly ſhine,</l>
                  <l>I would turn my dazled ſight,</l>
                  <l>To behold their milder light;</l>
                  <l>But as hard 'tis to deſtroy</l>
                  <l>That high flame as to enjoy,</l>
                  <l>Which how eaſily I may doe,</l>
                  <l>Heaven (as eaſily ſcal'd) does know.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Amoret</hi> as ſweet and good,</l>
                  <l>As the moſt delicious food;</l>
                  <l>Which but taſted does impart</l>
                  <l>Life and gladneſs to the heart;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sachariſſa</hi>'s beautie's wine,</l>
                  <l>Which to madneſs doth incline;</l>
                  <l>Such a liquor as no braine,</l>
                  <l>That is mortall, can ſuſtaine.</l>
                  <l>Scarſe can I to heaven excuſe</l>
                  <l>That devotion which I uſe</l>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:102619:33"/>
                  <l>Unto that adored Dame,</l>
                  <l>For 'tis not unlike the ſame,</l>
                  <l>Which I thither ought to ſend,</l>
                  <l>So that if it could take end,</l>
                  <l>'Twould to heaven it ſelfe be due,</l>
                  <l>To ſucceed her, and not you,</l>
                  <l>Who already have of mee</l>
                  <l>All that's not Idolatry;</l>
                  <l>Which though not ſo fierce a flame,</l>
                  <l>Is longer like to be the ſame:</l>
                  <l>Then ſmile on me, and I will prove,</l>
                  <l>Wonder is ſhorter liv'd then Love.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:102619:33"/>
               <head>The ſtory of <hi>Phoebus</hi> and <hi>Daphne</hi> applyed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <l>
                  <hi>THirſis</hi> a youth of the inſpired train,</l>
               <l>Faire <hi>Sachariſſa</hi> lov'd, but lov'd in vain;</l>
               <l>Like <hi>Phoebus</hi> ſung, the no leſs amorous boy;</l>
               <l>Like <hi>Daphne,</hi> ſhe as lovely and as coy;</l>
               <l>With numbers, he the flying Nymph purſues,</l>
               <l>With numbers, ſuch as <hi>Phoebus</hi> ſelfe might uſe;</l>
               <l>Such is the chaſe, when love and fancy leads</l>
               <l>Ore craggy mountains, and through flowry meads,</l>
               <l>Invok'd to teſtifie the lovers care,</l>
               <l>Or forme ſome image of his cruell Faire:</l>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:102619:34"/>
               <l>Vrg'd with his fury like a wounded Deer</l>
               <l>O're theſe hee fled, and now approching neer,</l>
               <l>Had reach'd the Nymph with his harmonious lay,</l>
               <l>Whom all his charmes could not incline to ſtay.</l>
               <l>Yet what hee ſung in his immortall ſtraine,</l>
               <l>Though unſuccesfull, was not ſung in vaine,</l>
               <l>All but the Nymph that ſhould redreſs his wrong,</l>
               <l>Attend his paſſion, and approve his ſong.</l>
               <l>Like <hi>Phoebus</hi> thus acquiring unſought praiſe,</l>
               <l>Hee catch'd at love, and fill'd his arme with bayſe.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:102619:34"/>
               <head>Of Mris. <hi>Arden.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>BEhold and liſten, while the faire</l>
                  <l>Breakes in ſweete ſounds the willing aire,</l>
                  <l>And with her owne breath fans the fire,</l>
                  <l>Which her bright eyes doe fixſt inſpire.</l>
                  <l>What reaſon can that love controule</l>
                  <l>Which more then one way courts the ſoule?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>So when a flaſh of lightning falls</l>
                  <l>On our aboads, the danger calls</l>
                  <l>For humane ayd, which hopes the flame</l>
                  <l>To conquer, though from heaven it came.</l>
                  <l>But if the winde with that conſpire,</l>
                  <l>Men ſtrive not, but deplore the fire.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:102619:35"/>
               <head>On the diſcovery of a La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies Painting.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>PYgmalions fate reverſt is mine:</l>
                  <l>His marble love tooke fleſh and blood;</l>
                  <l>All that I worſhipt is divine,</l>
                  <l>That beauty now 'tis underſtood</l>
                  <l>Appeares to have no more of life,</l>
                  <l>Then that whereof hee fram'd his wife.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>As women yet, who apprehend</l>
                  <l>Some ſuddaine cauſe of cauſeleſs feare,</l>
                  <l>Although that ſeeming cauſe take end,</l>
                  <l>And they behold no danger neare,</l>
                  <l>A ſhaking through their limbs they finde,</l>
                  <l>Like leaves ſaluted by the wind:</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:102619:35"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o though the beauty doe appeare</l>
                  <l>No beauty which amaz'd mee ſo,</l>
                  <l>Yet from my breaſt I cannot teare</l>
                  <l>The paſſion which from hence did grow;</l>
                  <l>Nor yet out of my phanſy raſe</l>
                  <l>The print of that ſuppoſed face.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>A reall beauty (though too neare)</l>
                  <l>The fond <hi>Narciſſus</hi> did admire:</l>
                  <l>I dote on that which is no where,</l>
                  <l>The ſigne of beauty feedes my fire.</l>
                  <l>No mortall flame was ere ſo cruell</l>
                  <l>As this which thus ſurvives the fuell.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:102619:36"/>
               <head>To a Lady from whom he receiv'd a ſilver pen.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Madam,</salute>
               </opener>
               <lg>
                  <l>INtending to have try'd</l>
                  <l>The ſilver favour which you gave,</l>
                  <l>In inke the ſhining point I dy'd,</l>
                  <l>And drencht it in the ſable wave:</l>
                  <l>When griev'd to be ſo foully ſtain'd</l>
                  <l>On you it thus to mee complain'd:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Suppoſe you had deſerv'd to take</l>
                  <l>From her faire hand ſo faire a boon;</l>
                  <l>Yet how deſerved I to take</l>
                  <l>So ill a change, who ever won</l>
                  <l>Immortall praiſe for what I wrought</l>
                  <l>Inſtructed by her noble thought?</l>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:102619:36"/>
                  <l>I that expreſſed her commands</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>To mighty Lords and Princely Dames,</l>
                  <l>Alwaies moſt welcome to their hands,</l>
                  <l>Proud that I would record their names,</l>
                  <l>Muſt now be taught an humble ſtile</l>
                  <l>Some meaner beauty to beguile.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>So I the wronged Pen to pleaſe,</l>
                  <l>Make it my humble thanks expreſs</l>
                  <l>Vnto your Ladiſhip in theſe,</l>
                  <l>And now 'tis forced to confeſs,</l>
                  <l>That your great ſelfe did nere indite,</l>
                  <l>Nor that to one more noble write,</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:102619:37"/>
               <head>On a brede of divers colours woven by foure Ladies.</head>
               <l>TWice twenty ſlender virgin fingers twine</l>
               <l>This curious web, where all their fancies ſhine:</l>
               <l>As nature them, ſo they this ſhade have wrought,</l>
               <l>Soft as their hands, and various as their thought:</l>
               <l>Not <hi>Juno's</hi> bird, when his faire traine dispred</l>
               <l>Hee woes the female to his painted bed;</l>
               <l>No not the Bow which ſo adornes the skyes,</l>
               <l>So glorious is, or boaſts ſo many dyes.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:102619:37"/>
               <head>On the head of a Stag.</head>
               <l>SO wee ſome antique Hero's ſtrength</l>
               <l>Learn by his Launces weight and length,</l>
               <l>As theſe vaſt beams expreſs the beaſt,</l>
               <l>Whoſe ſhady brows alive they dreſt.</l>
               <l>Such game, while yet the world was new,</l>
               <l>The mighty <hi>Nimrod</hi> did purſue.</l>
               <l>What huntſman of our feeble race,</l>
               <l>Or dogs dare ſuch a monſter chaſe,</l>
               <l>Reſembling with each blow hee ſtrikes,</l>
               <l>The charge of a whole troope of Pikes?</l>
               <l>O fertile head, which every yeare</l>
               <l>Could ſuch a crop of wonder beare!</l>
               <l>The teeming Earth did never bring</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o ſoone, ſo hard, ſo huge a thing.</l>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:102619:38"/>
               <l>Which might it never have been caſt,</l>
               <l>Each years growth added to the laſt,</l>
               <l>Thoſe lofty branches had ſuppli'd</l>
               <l>The Earths bold ſons prodigious pride;</l>
               <l>Heaven with theſe engines had bin ſcal'd,</l>
               <l>When Mountains heap'd on Mountains fail'd.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>To a Lady in retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>SEes not, my Love, how time reſumes</l>
                  <l>The glory which he lent theſe ſlowres?</l>
                  <l>Though none ſhould taſt theſe ſweet perfumes,</l>
                  <l>Yet muſt they live but ſome few houres;</l>
                  <l>Time, what we forbeare, devours.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:102619:38"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Had <hi>Helen,</hi> or th'Aegyptian Queen,</l>
                  <l>Been nere ſo thrifty of their graces,</l>
                  <l>Thoſe beauties muſt at length have been</l>
                  <l>The ſpoil of age, which findes out faces</l>
                  <l>In the moſt retired places.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Should ſome malignant Planet bring</l>
                  <l>A barren drought, or ceaſleſs ſhowre</l>
                  <l>Upon the Autumne, or the Spring,</l>
                  <l>And ſpare us neither fruit nor flowre,</l>
                  <l>Winter would not ſtay an houre.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Could the reſolve of loves neglect</l>
                  <l>Preſerve thee from the violation</l>
                  <l>Of comming years, then more reſpect</l>
                  <l>Were due to ſo divine a faſhion,</l>
                  <l>Nor would I indulge my paſſion.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:102619:39"/>
               <head>The Miſers ſpeech in a Mask.</head>
               <l>BAlls of this metall ſlack'd <hi>Atlanta's</hi> pace,</l>
               <l>And on the amorous youth beſtow'd the race:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Venus</hi> the Nymphs mind meaſuring by her own,</l>
               <l>Whom the rich ſpoils of Cities overthrown</l>
               <l>Had proſtrated to <hi>Mars,</hi> could well adviſe</l>
               <l>Th' adventurous Lover how to gain the prize.</l>
               <l>Nor leſs may <hi>Jupiter</hi> to gold aſcribe;</l>
               <l>For when hee turn'd himſelf into a bribe,</l>
               <l>Who can blame <hi>Danac,</hi> or the braſen towre,</l>
               <l>That they withſtood not the almighty ſhowre?</l>
               <l>Never till then did love make <hi>Jove</hi> put on</l>
               <l>A forme more bright and noble then his owne;</l>
               <l>Nor were it juſt, would hee reſume that ſhape,</l>
               <l>That ſlack devotion ſhould his thunder ſcape:</l>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:102619:39"/>
               <l>'Twas not revenge for griev'd <hi>Apollo's</hi> wrong,</l>
               <l>Thoſe Aſſes eares on <hi>Mida's</hi> temples hung;</l>
               <l>But fond repentance of his happy wiſh,</l>
               <l>Becauſe his meate grew metall like his diſh;</l>
               <l>Would <hi>Bacchus</hi> bleſſe me ſo, I'd conſtant hold</l>
               <l>Vnto my wiſh, and dye creating gold.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>To my Lord of <hi>Northum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berland</hi> upon the death of his Lady.</head>
               <l>TO this great loſſe a ſea of teares is due,</l>
               <l>But the whole debt not to bee paid by you;</l>
               <l>Charge not your ſelfe with all, nor render vain</l>
               <l>Thoſe ſhowres the eyes of us your ſervants rain.</l>
               <l>Shall griefe contract the largeneſs of that heart,</l>
               <l>In which nor ſeare nor anger has a part?</l>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:102619:40"/>
               <l>Vertue would bluſh, if Time ſhould boaſt (which dry's,</l>
               <l>Her ſole child dead, the tender Mothers eys)</l>
               <l>Your minds reliefe, where reaſon triumphs ſo</l>
               <l>Over all paſſions, that they nere could grow</l>
               <l>Beyond their limits in your noble breſt,</l>
               <l>To harme another, or impeach your reſt.</l>
               <l>This wee obſerv'd delighting to obey</l>
               <l>One who did never from his great ſelfe ſtray,</l>
               <l>Whoſe milde example ſeemed to ingage</l>
               <l>Th' obſequious ſeas, and teach them not to rage.</l>
               <l>The brave <hi>Emylius</hi> his charge laid down,</l>
               <l>(The force of <hi>Rome,</hi> and fate of <hi>Macedon</hi>)</l>
               <l>In his loſt ſons did feele the cruell ſtroke</l>
               <l>Of changing fortune; and thus highly ſpoke:</l>
               <l>Before <hi>Romes</hi> people wee did of implore,</l>
               <l>That if the heavens had any ill in ſtore</l>
               <l>For your <hi>Emylius,</hi> they would powre that ill</l>
               <l>On his owne houſe, and let you flouriſh ſtill:</l>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:102619:40"/>
               <l>You on the barren Seas my Lord have ſpent</l>
               <l>Whole ſprings, and ſummers to the publique lent,</l>
               <l>Suſpended all the pleaſures of your life,</l>
               <l>And ſhortned the ſhort ioy of ſuch a wife:</l>
               <l>For which your country's more obliged, then</l>
               <l>For many lives of old leſs happy men.</l>
               <l>You that have ſacrific'd ſo great a part</l>
               <l>Of youth and private bliſs, ought to impart</l>
               <l>Your ſorrow too, and give your friends a right</l>
               <l>As well in your affliction, as delight.</l>
               <l>Then with <hi>Emylian</hi> courage beare this croſs,</l>
               <l>Since publique perſons only publique loſs</l>
               <l>Ought to affect. And though her form and youth,</l>
               <l>Her application to your will and truth,</l>
               <l>That noble ſweetnes and that humble ſtate,</l>
               <l>All ſnatcht away by ſuch a haſty fate,</l>
               <l>Might give excuſe to any common breſt</l>
               <l>With the huge weight of ſo iuſt griefe oppreſt;</l>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:102619:41"/>
               <l>Yet let no portion of your life be ſtain'd</l>
               <l>With paſſion, but your character maintain'd</l>
               <l>To the laſt act; it is enough her ſtone</l>
               <l>May honour'd bee with ſuperſcription</l>
               <l>Of the ſole Lady who had power to move</l>
               <l>The great <hi>Northumberland</hi> to grieve and love.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>To my Lord <hi>Admirall,</hi> of his late ſicknes and recovery.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVIth joy like ours the <hi>Thracian</hi> youth invades</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Orpheus</hi> returning from th' <hi>Elyſian</hi> ſhades,</l>
                  <l>Embrace the Hero, and his ſtay implore,</l>
                  <l>Make it their publique ſuite hee would no more</l>
                  <l>Deſert them ſo, and for his ſpouſes ſake</l>
                  <l>His vaniſht Love tempt the <hi>Lethean</hi> lake:</l>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:102619:41"/>
                  <l>The Ladies too, the brighteſt of that time,</l>
                  <l>Ambitious all his lofty bed to clime,</l>
                  <l>Their doubtfull hopes with expectation feed,</l>
                  <l>Who ſhall the faire <hi>Eurydice</hi> ſucceed:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Eurydice,</hi> for whom his num'rous moan</l>
                  <l>Makes liſtning trees, and ſalvage mountains groan,</l>
                  <l>Through all the ayre his ſounding ſtrings dilate</l>
                  <l>Sorrow like that, which toucht our hearts of late,</l>
                  <l>Your pining ſickneſſe, and your reſtleſs pain</l>
                  <l>At once the Land affecting, and the Main;</l>
                  <l>When the glad news that you were Admirall</l>
                  <l>Scarce through the Nation ſpread, 'twas fear'd by all</l>
                  <l>That our great <hi>Charles,</hi> whoſe wiſdome ſhines in you,</l>
                  <l>Would bee perplexed how to chooſe a new:</l>
                  <l>So more then private was the joy and grief,</l>
                  <l>That at the worſt it gave our ſouls relief,</l>
                  <l>That in our age ſuch ſenſe of vertue liv'd,</l>
                  <l>They joy'd ſo juſtly, and ſo juſtly griev'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:102619:42"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Nature, her faireſt lights eclipſed, ſeemes</l>
                  <l>Her ſelfe to ſuffer in thoſe ſharpe extremes,</l>
                  <l>While not from thine alone thy blood retires,</l>
                  <l>But from thoſe cheeks which all the world admires:</l>
                  <l>The ſtem thus threatned and the ſap in thee</l>
                  <l>Droop all the branches of that noble tree;</l>
                  <l>Their beauty they, and wee our loves ſuſpend,</l>
                  <l>Nought can our wiſhes ſave thy health intend.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>As Lillies overcharg'd with rain, they bend</l>
                  <l>Their beauteous heads, and with high heav'n contend,</l>
                  <l>Fold thee within their ſnowy armes, and cry,</l>
                  <l>Hee is too faultleſs, and too young to dye;</l>
                  <l>So like Immortalls round about thee they</l>
                  <l>Sit, that they fright approching death away:</l>
                  <l>Who would not languiſh by ſo faire a train,</l>
                  <l>To bee lamented, and reſtor'd again?</l>
                  <l>Or thus with-held, what haſty ſoul would go,</l>
                  <l>Though to the bleſt? O're young <hi>Adonis</hi> ſo</l>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:102619:42"/>
                  <l>Fair <hi>Venus</hi> mourn'd, and with the pretious ſhowre</l>
                  <l>Of her warme teares cheriſh'd the ſpringing flowre.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The next ſupport faire hope of your great name,</l>
                  <l>And ſecond pillar of that noble frame,</l>
                  <l>By loſs of thee would no advantage have,</l>
                  <l>But ſtep by ſtep purſues thee to the grave.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And now relentleſs Fate about to end</l>
                  <l>The line, which backward does ſo farre extend</l>
                  <l>That Antique ſtock, which ſtill the world ſupplyes</l>
                  <l>With braveſt ſpirits, and with brighteſt eyes;</l>
                  <l>Kind <hi>Phoebus</hi> interpoſing bid mee ſay,</l>
                  <l>Such ſtormes no more ſhall ſhake that houſe, but they</l>
                  <l>Like <hi>Neptune</hi> and his Sea-borne Neece ſhall bee</l>
                  <l>The ſhining glories of the land and Sea,</l>
                  <l>With courage guard, and beauty warm our Age,</l>
                  <l>And lovers fill with like Poetique rage.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:102619:43"/>
               <head>On the friendſhip be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>Sachariſſa</hi> and <hi>Amoret.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>TEll me, lovely loving Paire,</l>
                  <l>Why ſo kind, and ſo ſevere?</l>
                  <l>Why ſo careleſs of our care,</l>
                  <l>Only to your ſelves ſo deare?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>By this cunning change of hearts,</l>
                  <l>You the power of Love controul,</l>
                  <l>While the Boyes deluded darts</l>
                  <l>Can arrive at neithers ſoul.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For in vain to either breſt</l>
                  <l>Still beguiled Love does come,</l>
                  <l>Where he finds a forain gueſt,</l>
                  <l>Neither of your hearts at home;</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:102619:43"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Debters thus with like deſigne,</l>
                  <l>When they never mean to pay,</l>
                  <l>That they may the law decline,</l>
                  <l>To ſome friend make all away.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Not the ſilver Doves that fly,</l>
                  <l>Yoakt in <hi>Cytharea</hi>'s Carre;</l>
                  <l>Not the wings that lift ſo high,</l>
                  <l>And convey her ſon ſo farre,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Are ſo lovely ſweet and fair,</l>
                  <l>Or doe more ennoble Love,</l>
                  <l>Are ſo choicely matcht a pair,</l>
                  <l>Or with more conſent doe move.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:102619:44"/>
               <head>A la Malade.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>AH lovely <hi>Amoret,</hi> the Care</l>
                  <l>Of all that know what's good or fair,</l>
                  <l>Is Heaven become our Rivall too?</l>
                  <l>Had the rich Gifts confer'd on you</l>
                  <l>So amply thence, the common end</l>
                  <l>Of giving Lovers, to pretend?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Hence to this pining Sickneſs (meant</l>
                  <l>To weary thee to a conſent</l>
                  <l>Of leaving us) no power is given</l>
                  <l>Thy Beauties to impaire, for Heaven</l>
                  <l>Solicites thee with ſuch a care:</l>
                  <l>As Roſes from their ſtalkes we tare,</l>
                  <l>When wee would ſtill preſerve them new</l>
                  <l>And freſh, as on the buſh they grew.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:102619:44"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>With ſuch a grace you entertain,</l>
                  <l>And look with ſuch contempt on pain,</l>
                  <l>That languiſhing you conquer more,</l>
                  <l>And wound us deeper then before.</l>
                  <l>The lightnings which in ſtormes appear.</l>
                  <l>Scorch more then when the skies are clear.</l>
                  <l>And as pale ſickneſs does invade</l>
                  <l>Your frailer part, the breaches made</l>
                  <l>In that faire Lodging ſtill more clear</l>
                  <l>Make the bright Gueſt your Soule appear:</l>
                  <l>So Nymphs o'r pathleſs Mountains born,</l>
                  <l>Their light robes by the Brambles torn</l>
                  <l>From their faire limbs, expoſing new</l>
                  <l>And unknown Beauties to the view</l>
                  <l>Of following Gods, increaſe their flame,</l>
                  <l>And haſt to catch the flying Game.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:102619:45"/>
               <head>Of her Chamber.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THey taſt of Death that doe at Heaven arrive,</l>
                  <l>But we this Paradiſe approch alive:</l>
                  <l>In ſtead of Death, the dart of Love does ſtrike,</l>
                  <l>And renders all within theſe walls alike:</l>
                  <l>The high in titles, and the Shepheard here,</l>
                  <l>Forgets his greatneſs, and forgets his fear:</l>
                  <l>All ſtand amaz'd, and gazing on the Faire</l>
                  <l>Looſe thought of what themſelves or others are,</l>
                  <l>Ambition looſe, and have no other ſcope</l>
                  <l>Save <hi>Carliſles</hi> favour to imploy their hope.</l>
                  <l>The Thracian could (though all thoſe tales were true</l>
                  <l>The bold Greeks tell) no greater wonders doe;</l>
                  <l>Before his feet ſo Sheep and Lyons lay</l>
                  <l>Fearleſs and wrathleſs, while they heard him play;</l>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:102619:45"/>
                  <l>The Gay, the Wiſe, the Gallant, and the Grave,</l>
                  <l>Subdu'd alike all but one paſſion have.</l>
                  <l>No worthy mind but finds in hers there is</l>
                  <l>Something proportioned to the rule of his;</l>
                  <l>While ſhe with cheerfull, but impartiall grace,</l>
                  <l>(Borne for no one, but to delight the race</l>
                  <l>Of men) like <hi>Phoebus</hi> ſo divides her light,</l>
                  <l>And warmes us that ſhe ſtoops not from her height.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Of loving at firſt ſight.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>NOt caring to obſerve the wind,</l>
                  <l>Or the new Sea explore,</l>
                  <l>Snatcht from my ſelf, how farre behind</l>
                  <l>Already I behold the ſhore?</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:102619:46"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>May not a thouſand dangers ſleep</l>
                  <l>In the ſmooth Boſome of this deep?</l>
                  <l>No, 'tis ſo rockleſs, and ſo clear,</l>
                  <l>That the rich Bottome does appear</l>
                  <l>Pav'd all with pretious things, not torn</l>
                  <l>From ſhipwrackt Veſſells, but there born.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Sweetnes, truth, and every grace</l>
                  <l>Which Time and Uſe are wont to teach,</l>
                  <l>The eye may in a moment reach,</l>
                  <l>And read diſtinctly in her face.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Some other Nymph with colours ſaint</l>
                  <l>And pencill ſlow may <hi>Cupid</hi> paint,</l>
                  <l>And a weake heart in time deſtroy;</l>
                  <l>She has a ſtamp and prints the Boy,</l>
                  <l>Can with a ſingle looke inflame</l>
                  <l>The coldeſt breſt, the rudeſt tame.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:102619:46"/>
               <head>The ſelfe baniſh'd.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>IT is not that I love you leſs,</l>
                  <l>Then when before your feet I lay,</l>
                  <l>But to prevent the ſad increaſe</l>
                  <l>Of hopeleſs love, I keep away.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In vaine (alas!) for every thing</l>
                  <l>Which I have knowne belong to you,</l>
                  <l>Your forme does to my fancy bring,</l>
                  <l>And make my old wounds bleed anew.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Who in the Spring from the new Sun</l>
                  <l>Already has a Fever got,</l>
                  <l>Too late begins thoſe ſhafts to ſhun</l>
                  <l>Which <hi>Phoebus</hi> through his veines has ſhot.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:102619:47"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Too late hee would the paine aſſwage,</l>
                  <l>And to thick ſhadowes does retire;</l>
                  <l>About with him hee beares the rage,</l>
                  <l>And in his tainted blood the fire.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But vow'd I have, and never muſt</l>
                  <l>Your baniſh'd ſervant trouble you;</l>
                  <l>For if I breake, you may miſtruſt</l>
                  <l>The vow I made to love you too.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Of, and to the Queen.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THe Larke that ſhun's on lofty boughs to build</l>
                  <l>Her humble neſt, lyes ſilent in the field;</l>
                  <l>But if the promiſe of a cloudleſs day</l>
                  <l>(<hi>Aurora</hi> ſmiling) bids her riſe and play,</l>
                  <l>Then ſtraight ſhee ſhowes 'twas not for want of voyce</l>
                  <l>Or power to climbe ſhee made ſo low a choyce;</l>
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:102619:47"/>
                  <l>Singing ſhee mounts, her ayerie wings are ſtretcht</l>
                  <l>Towards heav'n, as if from heav'n her note ſhee fetcht.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>So wee retiring from the buſie throng,</l>
                  <l>Vſe to reſtraine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th' ambition of our ſong;</l>
                  <l>But ſince the light which now informs our Age</l>
                  <l>Breaks from the Court indulgent to her rage,</l>
                  <l>Thither my Muſe, like bold <hi>Prometheus,</hi> flyes</l>
                  <l>To light her torch at <hi>Gloriana's</hi> eyes,</l>
                  <l>Thoſe ſoveraign beams, which heal the wounded ſoule,</l>
                  <l>And all our cares, but once beheld, controule:</l>
                  <l>There the poore lover that has long indur'd</l>
                  <l>Some proud Nymphs ſcorne, of his fond paſſion cur'd,</l>
                  <l>Fares like the man who firſt upon the ground</l>
                  <l>A gloworme ſpide, ſuppoſing hee had found</l>
                  <l>A moving diamond, a breathing ſtone,</l>
                  <l>(For life it had, and like thoſe Jewels ſhone)</l>
                  <l>Hee held it deare, till by the ſpringing day</l>
                  <l>Inform'd, hee threw the worthleſs worme away.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:102619:48"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>She ſaves the Lover, as wee Gangrenes ſtay,</l>
                  <l>By cutting hope, like a lopt limbe, away<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>This makes her bleeding Patients to accuſe</l>
                  <l>High heav'n, and theſe expoſtulations uſe:</l>
                  <l>Could nature then no private woman grace</l>
                  <l>(Whom wee might dare to love) with ſuch a face,</l>
                  <l>Such a complexion, and ſo radiant eys,</l>
                  <l>Such lovely motion, and ſuch ſharp reply's?</l>
                  <l>Beyond our reach, and yet within our ſight,</l>
                  <l>What envious power has plac'd this glorious light?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus in a ſtarry night fond Children cry</l>
                  <l>For the rich ſpangles that adorne the sky;</l>
                  <l>Which though they ſhine for ever fixed there,</l>
                  <l>With light and influence relieve us here.</l>
                  <l>All her affections are to one inclin'd,</l>
                  <l>Her bounty and compaſſion to mankind;</l>
                  <l>To whom while ſhee ſo far extends her Grace,</l>
                  <l>Shee makes but good the promiſe of her face:</l>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:102619:48"/>
                  <l>For Mercy has (could Mercy's ſelfe be ſeen)</l>
                  <l>No ſweeter looke, then this propitious Queen;</l>
                  <l>Such guard and comfort the diſtreſſed find</l>
                  <l>From her large power, and from her larger mind,</l>
                  <l>That whom ill Fate would ruine, it prefers,</l>
                  <l>For all the miſerable are made hers.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>So the faire Tree whereon the Eagle builds,</l>
                  <l>Poore ſheepe from tempeſt and their ſhepherd ſhields,</l>
                  <l>The Royall bird poſſeſſes all the boughs,</l>
                  <l>But ſhade and ſhelter to the flock allows.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Joy of our Age, and ſafety of the next,</l>
                  <l>For which ſo oft thy fertile wombe is vext,</l>
                  <l>Nobly contented for the publique good</l>
                  <l>To waſt thy ſpirits, and diffuſe thy blood,</l>
                  <l>What vaſt hopes may theſe Ilands entertaine</l>
                  <l>Where Monarchs thus deſcended are to raigne?</l>
                  <l>Led by Commanders of ſo faire a line</l>
                  <l>Our ſeas no longer ſhall our pow'r confine.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:102619:49"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>A brave Romance who would exactly frame,</l>
                  <l>Firſt brings his Knight from ſome immortall Dame,</l>
                  <l>And then a weapon and a flaming ſhield</l>
                  <l>Bright as his mothers eyes hee makes him wield:</l>
                  <l>None might the mother of <hi>Achilles</hi> bee</l>
                  <l>But the faire Pearle and Glory of the Sea:</l>
                  <l>The man to whom great <hi>Maro</hi> gives ſuch fame,</l>
                  <l>From the high bed of heavenly <hi>Venus</hi> came;</l>
                  <l>And our next <hi>Charles</hi> (whom all the ſtars deſigne</l>
                  <l>Like wonders to accompliſh) ſprings from thine.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="song">
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:102619:49"/>
               <head>Song.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>Goe lovely Roſe,</l>
                  <l>Tell her that waſts her time and mee,</l>
                  <l>That now ſhee knowes,</l>
                  <l>When I reſemble her to thee,</l>
                  <l>How ſweet and fayr ſhee ſeems to bee.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Tell her that's young,</l>
                  <l>And ſhun's to have her grâces ſpide,</l>
                  <l>That hadſt thou ſprung</l>
                  <l>In deſerts where no men abide,</l>
                  <l>Thou muſt have uncommended dy'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Small is the worth</l>
                  <l>Of beauty from the light retir'd:</l>
                  <l>Bid her come forth,</l>
                  <l>Suffer her ſelfe to bee deſir'd,</l>
                  <l>And not bluſh ſo to be admir'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:102619:50"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then dye, that ſhee</l>
                  <l>The common fate of all things rare</l>
                  <l>May read in thee,</l>
                  <l>How ſmall a part of time they ſhare,</l>
                  <l>That are ſo wondrous ſweet and faire.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Thirſis. Galatea.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>AS lately I on ſilver Thames did ride,</l>
                  <l>Sad <hi>Galatea</hi> on the bank I ſpide;</l>
                  <l>Such was her look, as ſorrow taught to ſhine,</l>
                  <l>And thus ſhe grac'd me with a voice divine:</l>
               </lg>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gal.</speaker>
                  <l>You that can tune your ſounding ſtrings ſo well</l>
                  <l>Of Ladies beauties, and of Love to tell,</l>
                  <l>Once change your note, and let your Lute report</l>
                  <l>The juſteſt grief that ever touch'd the Court.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:102619:50"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Th.</speaker>
                  <l>Faire Nymph, I have in your delights no ſhare,</l>
                  <l>Nor ought to be concerned in your care;</l>
                  <l>Yet would I ſing, if I your ſorrows knew,</l>
                  <l>And to my ayd invoke no Muſe but you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gal.</speaker>
                  <l>Heare then, and let your ſong augment our grief,</l>
                  <l>Which is ſo great as not to wiſh relief;</l>
                  <l>Shee that had all which Nature gives or Chance,</l>
                  <l>Whom Fortune joyn'd with Vertue to advance</l>
                  <l>To all the joyes this Iſland could afford,</l>
                  <l>The greateſt Miſtris, and the kindeſt Lord;</l>
                  <l>Who with the royall mixt her noble blood,</l>
                  <l>And in high grace with <hi>Gloriana</hi> ſtood,</l>
                  <l>Her bounty, ſweetneſs, beauty, goodneſs ſuch,</l>
                  <l>That none ere thought her happineſs too much,</l>
                  <l>So well inclin'd her favours to conſer,</l>
                  <l>And kind to all as heaven had been to her.</l>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:102619:51"/>
                  <l>The virgins part, the mother and the wife</l>
                  <l>So well ſhe acted in this ſpan of life,</l>
                  <l>That though few years (too few, alas!) ſhe told</l>
                  <l>Shee ſeem'd in all things, but in beauty, old.</l>
                  <l>As unripe fruit, whoſe verdant ſtalk does cleave</l>
                  <l>Cloſe to the tree, which grieves no leſſe to leave</l>
                  <l>The ſmiling pendant which adorns her ſo,</l>
                  <l>And untill Autumne on the bough ſhould grow:</l>
                  <l>So ſeem'd her youthfull Soul not eas'ly forc'd,</l>
                  <l>Or from ſo fair, ſo ſweet a ſeat divorc'd;</l>
                  <l>Her Fate at once did haſty ſeem and ſlow,</l>
                  <l>At once too cruell and unwilling too.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Th.</speaker>
                  <l>Under how hard a law are Mortalls born!</l>
                  <l>Whom now we envie, we anon muſt mourn:</l>
                  <l>What heaven ſets higheſt, and ſeems moſt to prize,</l>
                  <l>Is ſoon removed from our wondring eyes.</l>
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:102619:51"/>
                  <l>But ſince the Siſters did ſo ſoon untwine</l>
                  <l>So faire a thread, I'll ſtrive to peece the line:</l>
                  <l>Vouchſafe (ſad Nymph) to let me know the Dame,</l>
                  <l>And to the Muſes I'll commend her name:</l>
                  <l>Make the wide Countrey echo to your moan,</l>
                  <l>The liſt'ning trees and ſalvage mountains groan;</l>
                  <l>What rocks not moved, when the death is ſung</l>
                  <l>Of one ſo good, ſo lovely, and ſo young?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gal.</speaker>
                  <l>'Twas <hi>Hamilton,</hi> whom I had nam'd before,</l>
                  <l>But naming her, griefe lets me ſay no more.</l>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:102619:52"/>
               <head>Fabula Phoebi &amp; Daphnes.</head>
               <l>ARcadiae juvenis <hi>Thirſis, Phoebi<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>
                  </hi> ſacerdos,</l>
               <l>Ingenti fruſtra <hi>Galateae</hi> ardebat amore:</l>
               <l>Haud deus ipſe olim <hi>Daphne</hi> majora canebat,</l>
               <l>Nec fuit aſperior <hi>Daphne,</hi> nec pulchrior illa.</l>
               <l>Carminibus <hi>Phoebo</hi> dignis premit ille fugacem</l>
               <l>Per rupes, per ſaxa volans, per florida vates</l>
               <l>Paſcua, formoſam nunc his componere Nympham,</l>
               <l>Nunc illis erudelem inſana mente ſolebat:</l>
               <l>Audiit illa procul miſerum, citharam<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſonantem</l>
               <l>Audiit, at nullis reſpexit mota querelis.</l>
               <l>Ne tamen omnino caneret deſertus, ad alta</l>
               <l>Sidera perculſi referunt nova carmina montes:</l>
               <l>Sic non quaeſitis cumulatus laudibus olim</l>
               <l>Elapſa, reperit <hi>Daphne</hi> ſua laurea <hi>Phoebus.</hi>
               </l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:102619:52"/>
               <head>The Battell of the Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Iſlands.</head>
               <div n="1" type="canto">
                  <head>CANTO I. What fruit they have, and how heaven ſmiles Upon thoſe late diſcovered Iſles.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>AYde me, <hi>Bellona,</hi> while the dreadfull fight</l>
                     <l>Betwixt a Nation and two Whales I write;</l>
                     <l>Seas ſtain'd with goare I ſing, advent'rous toile,</l>
                     <l>And how theſe Monſters did diſarme an Iſle.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Bermudas</hi> wall'd with rocks who does not know,</l>
                     <l>That happy Iſland where huge Lemmons grow,</l>
                     <l>And Orange trees, which golden fruit doe beare?</l>
                     <l>Th' <hi>Heſperian</hi> garden boaſts of none ſo faire.</l>
                     <l>There ſhining Pearl, Corall, and many a pound</l>
                     <l>On the rich ſhore of Amber-greece is found:</l>
                     <l>The lofty Cedar, which to heaven aſpires,</l>
                     <l>The Prince of trees, is fuell for their fires:</l>
                     <pb n="96" facs="tcp:102619:53"/>
                     <l>The ſmoak by which their loaded ſpits doe turn,</l>
                     <l>For incenſe might on ſacred Altars burn;</l>
                     <l>Their private roofs on odorous timber born,</l>
                     <l>Such as might Palaces for Kings adorn:</l>
                     <l>The ſweet <hi>Palmetta's</hi> a new <hi>Bacchus</hi> yield</l>
                     <l>With leaves as ample as the broadeſt ſhield;</l>
                     <l>Under the ſhadow of whoſe friendly boughs</l>
                     <l>They ſit carouſing where their liquor grows:</l>
                     <l>Figs there unplanted through the fields doe grow,</l>
                     <l>Such as fierce <hi>Cato</hi> did the Romans ſhow,</l>
                     <l>With the rare fruit inviting them to ſpoil</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Carthage,</hi> the Miſtris of ſo rich a ſpoil:</l>
                     <l>The naked rocks are not unfruitfull there,</l>
                     <l>But at ſome conſtant ſeaſons every yeare</l>
                     <l>Their barren tops with luſcious food abound,</l>
                     <l>And with the eggs of various fowles are crown'd:</l>
                     <l>Tobacco is their worſt of things which they</l>
                     <l>To Engliſh landlords as their tribute pay:</l>
                     <pb n="97" facs="tcp:102619:53"/>
                     <l>Such is the mould, that the bleſt tenant feeds</l>
                     <l>On pretious fruits, and payes his rent in weeds:</l>
                     <l>With candid Plantines, and the ivy Pine,</l>
                     <l>On choiſeſt Melons and ſweete grapes they dine,</l>
                     <l>And with Potatoes fat their wanton ſwine.</l>
                     <l>Nature theſe Cates with ſuch a laviſh hand</l>
                     <l>Powres out among them, that our courſer land</l>
                     <l>Taſts of that bounty, and does cloth returne,</l>
                     <l>Which not for warmth, but ornament is worne:</l>
                     <l>For the kind ſpring, which but ſalutes us here,</l>
                     <l>Inhabits there, and courts them all the yeare:</l>
                     <l>Ripe fruits and bloſſomes on the ſame trees live,</l>
                     <l>At once they promiſe what at once they give.</l>
                     <l>So ſweete the ayre, ſo moderate the clime.</l>
                     <l>None ſickly lives or dyes before his time.</l>
                     <l>Heaven, ſure, has kept this ſpot of earth uncurſt,</l>
                     <l>To ſhew how all things were created firſt.</l>
                     <pb n="98" facs="tcp:102619:54"/>
                     <l>The tardy plants in our could orchards plac't</l>
                     <l>Reſerve their fruits for the next ages taſt;</l>
                     <l>There a ſmall grain in ſome few months will bee</l>
                     <l>A firme, a lofty, and a ſpacious tree.</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Palma-Chriſti</hi> and the faire Papah,</l>
                     <l>Now but a ſeed, (preventing natures law)</l>
                     <l>In halfe the circle of the haſty year</l>
                     <l>Project a ſhade, and lovely fruit doe wear.</l>
                     <l>And as their trees in our dull region ſet</l>
                     <l>But faintly grow, and no perfection get;</l>
                     <l>So in this Northern tract our hoarſer throates</l>
                     <l>Utter unripe and ill conſtrained notes,</l>
                     <l>Where the ſupporter of the Poets ſtile,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Phoebus,</hi> on them eternally does ſmile.</l>
                     <l>O how I long my careleſs limbs to lay</l>
                     <l>Vnder a Plantanes ſhade, and all the day</l>
                     <l>With amorous ayres my fancy entertaine,</l>
                     <l>Invoke the Muſes, and improve my vaine!</l>
                     <pb n="99" facs="tcp:102619:54"/>
                     <l>No paſſion there in my free breſt ſhould move,</l>
                     <l>None, but the ſweete and beſt of paſſions, Love:</l>
                     <l>There while I ſing, if gentle love bee by,</l>
                     <l>That tunes my Lute, and winds the ſtrings ſo high</l>
                     <l>With the ſweete ſound of <hi>Sachariſsa's</hi> name,</l>
                     <l>I'le make the liſtning ſalvages grow tame.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But while I doe theſe pleaſing dreames indite,</l>
                     <l>I am diverted from the promis'd fight.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="canto">
                  <head>CANTO II. Of their affright, and how their foes Diſcovered were, this Canto ſhowes.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>THough rocks ſo high about this Iſland riſe,</l>
                     <l>That well they may the num'rous Turke deſpiſe;</l>
                     <l>Yet is no humane fate exempt from fear,</l>
                     <l>Which ſhakes their hearts, while through the Iſle they hear</l>
                     <pb n="100" facs="tcp:102619:55"/>
                     <l>A laſting noyſe, as horrid, and as lowd</l>
                     <l>As thunder makes before it breaks the clowd:</l>
                     <l>Three dayes they dread this murmure, ere they know</l>
                     <l>From what blind cauſe th' unw<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>oted ſound may grow;</l>
                     <l>At length two Monſters of unequall ſize,</l>
                     <l>Hard by the ſhore, a fiſherman eſpies,</l>
                     <l>Two mighty Whales, which ſwelling ſeas had toſt,</l>
                     <l>And left them pris'ners on the rocky coaſt:</l>
                     <l>One as a mountaine vaſt, and with her came</l>
                     <l>A Cub, not much inferiour to his Dam;</l>
                     <l>Here in a poole among the rocks ingag'd</l>
                     <l>They roar'd like Lions caught in toyles, and rag'd.</l>
                     <l>The man knew what they were, who heretofore</l>
                     <l>Had ſeen the like lye murther'd on the ſhore,</l>
                     <l>By the wild fury of ſome tempeſt caſt,</l>
                     <l>The fate of ſhips, and ſhip-wrackt men to taſt.</l>
                     <l>As careleſs Dames, whom wine and ſleepe betray</l>
                     <l>To frantick dreames, their infants overlay;</l>
                     <pb n="101" facs="tcp:102619:55" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <l>So there ſometimes the raging <hi>Ocean</hi> failes,</l>
                     <l>And her owne brood expoſes, when the Whales</l>
                     <l>Againſt ſharpe rocks, like reeling veſſells quaſht,</l>
                     <l>Though huge as mountaines, are in peeces daſht:</l>
                     <l>Along the ſhore their dreadfull limbs lye ſcatter'd,</l>
                     <l>Like hills with earthquakes ſhaken, torne &amp; ſhatter'd.</l>
                     <l>Hearts ſure of braſs they had, who tempted firſt</l>
                     <l>Rude Seas, that ſpare not what themſelves have nurſt.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The welcome newes through all the nation ſpread,</l>
                     <l>To ſuddaine ioy and hope converts their dread.</l>
                     <l>What lately was their publique terrour, they</l>
                     <l>Behold with glad eyes as a certain prey,</l>
                     <l>Diſpoſe already of th' untaken ſpoyl;</l>
                     <l>And as the purchaſe of their future toyl,</l>
                     <l>Theſe ſhare the bones, and they divide the oyl.</l>
                     <l>So was the huntſman by the Beare oppreſt,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe hide hee fold before hee caught the beaſt.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb n="102" facs="tcp:102619:56"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>They man their boates, and all their young men arm</l>
                     <l>With whatſoever may the monſters harm,</l>
                     <l>Pikes, Holdberts, Spits, and Darts that wound ſo far,</l>
                     <l>The tooles of peace and inſtruments of war:</l>
                     <l>Now was the time for vigorous lads to ſhow</l>
                     <l>What love or honour could invite them to:</l>
                     <l>A goodly theater, where rocks are round;</l>
                     <l>With reverent age, and lovely laſſes crown'd,</l>
                     <l>Such was the lake, which held this dreadfull pare,</l>
                     <l>Within the bounds of noble <hi>Warwicks</hi> ſhare;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Warwicks</hi> bold Earle, then which no title beares</l>
                     <l>A greater ſound among our Britiſh Peeres;</l>
                     <l>And worthy hee the memory to renew,</l>
                     <l>The fate and honour to that title due,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe brave adventures have transfer'd his name,</l>
                     <l>And through the New-world ſpred his growing fame.</l>
                     <l>But how they fought, and what their valour gain'd,</l>
                     <l>Shall in another Canto be contain'd.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="canto">
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:102619:56"/>
                  <head>CANTO III. The bloody fight, ſucceſsleſſe toile, And how the fiſhes ſack'd the Jſle.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>THe boate which on the firſt aſſault did goe,</l>
                     <l>Stroke with a harping-iron the younger foe;</l>
                     <l>Who when hee felt his ſide ſo rudely goar'd,</l>
                     <l>Loud as the Sea that nouriſh'd him, hee roar'd.</l>
                     <l>As a broad Breame, to pleaſe ſome curious taſt,</l>
                     <l>While yet alive, in boyling water caſt,</l>
                     <l>Vext with unwonted heate, bounds, flings about</l>
                     <l>The ſcorching braſs, and hurles the liquour out:</l>
                     <l>So with the barbed javeling ſtung, hee raves</l>
                     <l>And ſcourges with his tayle the ſuff'ring waves:</l>
                     <l>Like Fairy <hi>Talus</hi> with his iron flaile,</l>
                     <l>Hee threatens ruine with his pond'rous taile,</l>
                     <l>Diſſolving at one ſtroke the batter'd boate,</l>
                     <l>And downe the men fall drenched in the moate:</l>
                     <pb n="104" facs="tcp:102619:57"/>
                     <l>With every fierce encounter they are forc't</l>
                     <l>To quit their boates, and fare like men unhoiſt:</l>
                     <l>The bigger Whale like ſome huge carrack lay</l>
                     <l>Which wanteth Sea-roome with her foes to play,</l>
                     <l>Slowly ſhee ſwims, and when provok'd ſhee wou'd</l>
                     <l>Advance her tayle, her head ſalutes the mud;</l>
                     <l>The ſhallow water doth her force infringe,</l>
                     <l>And renders vain her tayles impetuous ſwinge;</l>
                     <l>The ſhining ſteel her tender ſides receave,</l>
                     <l>And there like bees they all their weapons leave.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>This ſees the Cub, and does himſelfe oppoſe</l>
                     <l>Betwixt his cumbred mother and her foes,</l>
                     <l>With deſp'rate courage hee receives her wounds,</l>
                     <l>And men and boates his active tayle confounds;</l>
                     <l>Their furies ioyn'd the Seas with billowes fill,</l>
                     <l>And make a tempeſt, though the winds bee ſtill.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Now would the men with half their hoped pray</l>
                     <l>Bee well content, and wiſh'd this Cub away;</l>
                     <pb n="105" facs="tcp:102619:57"/>
                     <l>Their wiſh they have, Hee to direct his Dam</l>
                     <l>Unto the gap, through which they thither came,</l>
                     <l>Before her ſwims, and quits the hoſtile Lake;</l>
                     <l>A pris'ner there but for his Mothers ſake;</l>
                     <l>Shee by the rocks compell'd to ſtay behind,</l>
                     <l>Is by the vaſtneſs of her bulk confin'd:</l>
                     <l>They ſhout for joy, and now on her alone</l>
                     <l>Their fury falls, and all their Darts are thrown:</l>
                     <l>Their Launces ſpent, One bolder then the reſt</l>
                     <l>With his broad ſword provokes the ſluggiſh beaſt;</l>
                     <l>Her oylie ſide devoures both blade and heft,</l>
                     <l>And there his ſteele the bold <hi>Bermudian</hi> left.</l>
                     <l>Courage the reſt from his example take,</l>
                     <l>And now they change the colour of the Lake,</l>
                     <l>Blood flowes in rivers from her wounded ſide,</l>
                     <l>As if they would prevent the tardie tide,</l>
                     <l>And raiſe the flood to that propitious height,</l>
                     <l>As might convey her from this fatall ſtreight;</l>
                     <pb n="106" facs="tcp:102619:58"/>
                     <l>Shee ſwims in blood, and blood does ſpouting throw</l>
                     <l>To heaven, that heaven mens cruelties might know;</l>
                     <l>Their fixed Javelins in her ſide ſhee wears,</l>
                     <l>And on her back a grove of Pikes appears:</l>
                     <l>You would have thought, had you the Monſter ſeen</l>
                     <l>Thus dreſt, ſhee had another Iſland been.</l>
                     <l>Roaring ſhe tears the ayr with ſuch a noiſe</l>
                     <l>(As well reſembled the conſpiring voice</l>
                     <l>Of routed armies, when the field is won)</l>
                     <l>To reach the ears of her eſcaped Son:</l>
                     <l>Hee (though a league removed from the ſo)</l>
                     <l>Haſts to her ayd: the pious <hi>Trojan</hi> ſo,</l>
                     <l>Neglecting for <hi>Creuſa</hi>'s life his own,</l>
                     <l>Repeats the danger of the burning town.</l>
                     <l>The men amazed bluſh to ſee the ſeed</l>
                     <l>Of Monſters, humane pietie exceed.</l>
                     <l>Well proves this kindneſs what the Grecians ſung,</l>
                     <l>That Loves bright Mother from the Ocean ſprung.</l>
                     <pb n="107" facs="tcp:102619:58"/>
                     <l>Their courage droops, and hopeleſs now they wiſh</l>
                     <l>For compoſition with th'unconquer'd Fiſh;</l>
                     <l>So ſhee their weapons would reſtore again,</l>
                     <l>Through rocks they'd hew her paſſage to the Main:</l>
                     <l>But how inſtructed in each others mind,</l>
                     <l>Or what commerce can men with Monſters find?</l>
                     <l>Not daring to approach their wounded ſo,</l>
                     <l>Whom her couragious Son protected ſo,</l>
                     <l>They charge their Muskets, and with hot deſire</l>
                     <l>Of fell revenge, renew the fight with fire;</l>
                     <l>Standing aloofe with Lead the bruiſe the ſcales,</l>
                     <l>And teare the fleſh of the incenſed Whales;</l>
                     <l>But no ſucceſs their fierce endeavours found,</l>
                     <l>Nor this way could they give one fatall wound.</l>
                     <l>Now to their Forts they are about to ſend</l>
                     <l>For the loud Engines which their Iſle defend;</l>
                     <l>But what thoſe peeces fram'd to batter Walls,</l>
                     <l>Would have effected on thoſe mighty Whales,</l>
                     <pb n="108" facs="tcp:102619:59"/>
                     <l>Great <hi>Neptune</hi> will not have us know, who ſends</l>
                     <l>A tide ſo high that it relieves his friends:</l>
                     <l>And thus they parted with exchange of harms;</l>
                     <l>Much blood the Monſters loſt, and they their arms.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Vpon the death of my Lady <hi>Rich.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>MAy thoſe already curs'd <hi>Eſſexian</hi> plains,</l>
                  <l>Where haſty Death, and pining ſickneſs raigns<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>Prove all a Deſert, and none there make ſtay</l>
                  <l>But ſalvage beaſts, or men as wilde as they:</l>
                  <l>There the faire light, which all our Iſland grac'd;</l>
                  <l>Like <hi>Hero</hi>'s Taper in the windows plac'd,</l>
                  <l>Such fate from the malignant ayr did find,</l>
                  <l>As that expoſed to the boyſtrous wind.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Ah cruell heaven to ſnatch ſo ſoon away</l>
                  <l>Her, for whoſe life had we had time to pray,</l>
                  <pb n="109" facs="tcp:102619:59"/>
                  <l>With thouſand vows and tears we ſhould have ſought</l>
                  <l>That ſad decree's ſuſpenſion to have wrought!</l>
                  <l>But we (alas!) no whiſper of her pain</l>
                  <l>Heard, till 'twas ſin to wiſh her here again.</l>
                  <l>That horrid word at once like lightning ſpread,</l>
                  <l>Strook all our ears: <hi>The Lady Rich is dead.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Heart-rending news, and dreadfull to thoſe few</l>
                  <l>VVho her reſemble, and her ſteps purſue,</l>
                  <l>That Death ſhould licence have to rage among</l>
                  <l>The faire, the wiſe, the vertuous, and the young.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The <hi>Paphian</hi> Queen from that fierce battell born</l>
                  <l>VVith goared hand, and Vail ſo rudely torn,</l>
                  <l>Like terrour did among th'Immortals breed,</l>
                  <l>Taught by her wound that God deſſes might bleed.</l>
                  <l>All ſtand amazed, but beyond the reſt</l>
                  <l>Th'Heroique Dame, whoſe happy womb ſhe bleſt,</l>
                  <l>Mov'd with juſt grief expoſtulates with heaven,</l>
                  <l>Urging that promiſe to th'obſequious given</l>
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:102619:60"/>
                  <l>Of longer life; for ne'r was pious ſoul</l>
                  <l>More apt t'obey, more worthy to controul:</l>
                  <l>A skilfull eye at once might read the race</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Caledonian</hi> Monarchs in her face,</l>
                  <l>And ſweet humilitie, her look and mind</l>
                  <l>At once were lofty, and at once were kind.</l>
                  <l>There dwelt the ſcorn of vice, and pity too,</l>
                  <l>For thoſe that did what ſhee diſdain'd to doe;</l>
                  <l>So gentle and ſevere, that what was bad</l>
                  <l>At once her hatred and her pardon had;</l>
                  <l>Gracious to all, but where her love was due</l>
                  <l>So faſt, ſo faithfull, loyall, and ſo true,</l>
                  <l>That a bold hand as ſoon might hope to force</l>
                  <l>The rowling lights of heaven, as change her courſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Some happy Angell that beholds her there,</l>
                  <l>Inſtruct us to record what ſhe was here;</l>
                  <l>And when this cloud of ſorrow's over-blown,</l>
                  <l>Through the wide world we'l make her graces known:</l>
                  <pb n="111" facs="tcp:102619:60"/>
                  <l>So freſh the wound is, and the grief ſo vaſt,</l>
                  <l>That all our art and power of ſpeech is waſt;</l>
                  <l>Here paſſion ſwayes, but there the Muſe ſhall raiſe</l>
                  <l>Eternall monuments of louder praiſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>There, our delight complying with her fame</l>
                  <l>Shall have occaſion to recite thy name,</l>
                  <l>Faire <hi>Sachariſſa,</hi> and now only fair,</l>
                  <l>To ſacred friendſhip wee'll an Altar rear,</l>
                  <l>Such as the Romans did erect of old,</l>
                  <l>Where on a Marble pillar ſhall be told</l>
                  <l>The lovely paſſion each to other bare,</l>
                  <l>With the reſemblance of that matchleſs pare.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Narciſſus</hi> to the thing for which hee pin'd,</l>
                  <l>Was not more like, then yours to her fair mind;</l>
                  <l>Save that you grac'd the ſeverall parts of life,</l>
                  <l>A ſpotleſs Virgin, and a faultleſs wife;</l>
                  <l>Such was the ſweet converſe 'twixt her and you,</l>
                  <l>As that ſhe holds with her aſſociates now.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:102619:61"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>How falſe is Hope, and how regardleſs Fate,</l>
                  <l>That ſuch a love ſhould have ſo ſhort a date!</l>
                  <l>Lately I ſaw her ſighing part from thee:</l>
                  <l>(Alas that that the laſt farewell ſhould be!)</l>
                  <l>So lookt <hi>Aſtraea,</hi> her remove deſign'd,</l>
                  <l>On thoſe diſtreſſed friends ſhee left behind.</l>
                  <l>Conſent in vertue knit your hearts ſo faſt,</l>
                  <l>That ſtill the knot in ſpight of Death does laſt.</l>
                  <l>For as your tears and ſorrow-wounded ſoule</l>
                  <l>Prove well that on your part this bond is whole:</l>
                  <l>So all we know of what they doe above</l>
                  <l>Is that they happy are, and that they love:</l>
                  <l>Let darke oblivion, and the hollow grave</l>
                  <l>Content themſelves our frailer thoughts to have;</l>
                  <l>Well choſen love is never taught to die,</l>
                  <l>But with our nobler part invades the skie;</l>
                  <l>Then grieve no more that One ſo heavenly ſhap'd</l>
                  <l>The crooked hand of trembling Age eſcap'd:</l>
                  <pb n="113" facs="tcp:102619:61"/>
                  <l>Rather ſince wee beheld her not decay,</l>
                  <l>But that ſhee vaniſh'd ſo entire away,</l>
                  <l>Her wond'rous beauty and her goodnes merit</l>
                  <l>Wee ſhould ſuppoſe that ſome propitious ſpirit</l>
                  <l>In that celeſtiall forme frequented here,</l>
                  <l>And is not dead, but ceaſes to appeare.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>To the Queen Mother up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her landing.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>GReat Queen of <hi>Europe,</hi> where thy off-ſpring wears</l>
                  <l>All the chief Crowns, whoſe Princes are thy heirs;</l>
                  <l>As welcome thou to Sea-girt Britains ſhore,</l>
                  <l>As erſt <hi>Latona</hi> (who faire <hi>Cynthia</hi> bore)</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Delos</hi> was; here ſhines a Nymph as bright,</l>
                  <l>By thee diſclos'd with like increaſe of light.</l>
                  <l>Why was her ioy in <hi>Belgia</hi> ſo confin'd?</l>
                  <l>Or why did you ſo much regard the wind?</l>
                  <pb n="114" facs="tcp:102619:62"/>
                  <l>Scarce could the <hi>Ocean</hi> (though inrag'd) have toſt</l>
                  <l>Thy Soveraign Bark, but where th' obſequious Coaſt</l>
                  <l>Payes tribute to thy bed: <hi>Romes</hi> conquering hand</l>
                  <l>More vanquiſh'd Nations under her command</l>
                  <l>Never reduc'd. Glad <hi>Berecynthia</hi> ſo</l>
                  <l>Among her deathleſs progeny did go:</l>
                  <l>A wreath of Towres adorn'd her reverend head,</l>
                  <l>Mother of all that on <hi>Ambroſia</hi> fed.</l>
                  <l>Thy God-like race muſt ſway the age to come,</l>
                  <l>Asſhee <hi>Olympus</hi> peopled with her wombe.</l>
                  <l>Would theſe Commanders of mankind obay</l>
                  <l>Their honour'd Parent, all pretences lay</l>
                  <l>Downe at your Royall feete, compoſe their jars,</l>
                  <l>And on the growing Turk diſcharge theſe wars,</l>
                  <l>The Chriſtian Knights that ſacred tombe ſhould wreſt</l>
                  <l>From Pagan hands, and triumph o'r the Eaſt:</l>
                  <l>There <hi>Englands</hi> Prince, and <hi>Gallia</hi>'s Daulphin might</l>
                  <l>Like young <hi>Rinaldo</hi> and <hi>Tancredo</hi> ſight,</l>
                  <pb n="115" facs="tcp:102619:62"/>
                  <l>In ſingle combate, by their ſwords again</l>
                  <l>The proud <hi>Argantes</hi> and fierce <hi>Soldan</hi> ſlaine;</l>
                  <l>Again might wee their glorious deeds recite,</l>
                  <l>And with your Thuſcan Muſe exalt the fight.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="song">
               <head>Song.</head>
               <l>Peace babling Muſe.</l>
               <l>I dare not ſing what you indite;</l>
               <l>Her eyes refuſe</l>
               <l>To read the paſſion which they write:</l>
               <l>She ſtrikes my Lute, but if it ſound,</l>
               <l>Threatens to hurle it on the ground;</l>
               <l>And I no leſs her anger dread,</l>
               <l>Then the poore wretch that faines him dead,</l>
               <l>While ſome fierce Lion does imbrace</l>
               <l>His breathleſs corps, and licks his face;</l>
               <l>Wrapt up in ſilent feare hee lyes,</l>
               <l>Torne all in pieces, if hee cryes.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:102619:63"/>
               <head>Of Love.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>ANger in haſty words or blowes</l>
                  <l>It ſelfe diſcharges on our foes;</l>
                  <l>And ſorrow too finds ſome relief</l>
                  <l>In teares which wait upon our grief;</l>
                  <l>So every paſſion but fond Love</l>
                  <l>Vnto its owne redreſs does move,</l>
                  <l>But that alone the wretch inclines</l>
                  <l>To what prevents his owne deſignes,</l>
                  <l>Makes him lament, and ſigh, and weep,</l>
                  <l>Diſord'red tremble, fawn and creep;</l>
                  <l>Poſtures which render him deſpis'd,</l>
                  <l>Where hee endeavours to bee priz'd.</l>
                  <l>For women borne to bee controul'd</l>
                  <l>Stoope to the forward and the bold,</l>
                  <pb n="117" facs="tcp:102619:63"/>
                  <l>Affect the haughty and the proud,</l>
                  <l>The gay, the frolick, and the loud,</l>
                  <l>Who firſt the generous ſteed oppreſt,</l>
                  <l>Not kneeling did ſalute the beaſt,</l>
                  <l>But with high courage, life and force</l>
                  <l>Approching, tam'd the unruly horſe.</l>
                  <l>Vnwiſely wee the wiſer Eaſt</l>
                  <l>Pity, ſuppoſing them oppreſt</l>
                  <l>With tyrants force, whoſe law is will,</l>
                  <l>By which they governe, ſpoile and kill;</l>
                  <l>Each Nymph but moderately faire</l>
                  <l>Commands with no leſſe rigour here.</l>
                  <l>Should ſome brave Turk, that walks among</l>
                  <l>His twenty Laſſes bright and young,</l>
                  <l>And beckens to the willing Dame</l>
                  <l>Prefer'd to quench his preſent flame,</l>
                  <l>Behold as many gallants here</l>
                  <l>With modeſt guiſe and ſilent feare</l>
                  <pb n="118" facs="tcp:102619:64"/>
                  <l>All to one femall Idoll bend,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt her high pride does ſcarce deſcend</l>
                  <l>To marke their follies, hee would ſweare</l>
                  <l>That theſe her guard of Eun̂uchs were,</l>
                  <l>And that a more Majeſtique Queen,</l>
                  <l>Or humbler ſlaves, hee had not ſeen.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>All this with indignation ſpoke</l>
                  <l>In vaine I ſtrugled with the yoke</l>
                  <l>Of mighty Love; that conqu'ring look.</l>
                  <l>When next beheld, like lightning ſtrook</l>
                  <l>My blaſted ſoule, and made mee bow</l>
                  <l>Lower then thoſe I pityed now.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>So the tall Stag upon the brink</l>
                  <l>Of ſome ſmooth ſtreame about to drink,</l>
                  <l>Surveying there his armed head,</l>
                  <l>With ſhame remembers that hee fled</l>
                  <l>The ſcorned dogs, reſolves to try</l>
                  <l>The combate next; but if their cry</l>
                  <pb n="119" facs="tcp:102619:64"/>
                  <l>Invades againe his trembling ear,</l>
                  <l>Hee ſtraight reſumes his wonted fear,</l>
                  <l>Leaves the untaſted Spring behinde,</l>
                  <l>And wing'd with fear outflyes the winde.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>To the mutable Faire.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>HEre, <hi>Coelia,</hi> for thy ſake I part</l>
                  <l>With all that grew ſo neare my heart,</l>
                  <l>The paſſion that I had for thee,</l>
                  <l>The faith, the love, the conſtancy;</l>
                  <l>And that I may ſucceſsfull prove,</l>
                  <l>Transform my ſelf to what you love.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Foole that I was, ſo much to prize</l>
                  <l>Thoſe ſimple vertues you deſpiſe!</l>
                  <l>Foole, that with ſuch dull arrowes ſtrove,</l>
                  <l>Or hop'd to reach a flying Dove!</l>
                  <pb n="120" facs="tcp:102619:65"/>
                  <l>For you that are in motion ſtill,</l>
                  <l>Decline our force, and mock our skill,</l>
                  <l>Who like <hi>Don Quixote</hi> doe advance</l>
                  <l>Againſt a windmill our vaine lance.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now will I wander through the ayre,</l>
                  <l>Mount, make a ſtoope at every Fayre,</l>
                  <l>And with a fancy unconfin'd</l>
                  <l>(As lawleſs as the the Sea or wind)</l>
                  <l>Purſue you whereſoere you fly,</l>
                  <l>And with your various thoughts comply.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The formall ſtars doe travell ſo,</l>
                  <l>As wee their names and courſes know;</l>
                  <l>And hee that on their changes looks,</l>
                  <l>Would think them govern'd by our books;</l>
                  <l>But never were the clouds reduc'd</l>
                  <l>To any art, the motion us'd</l>
                  <l>By thoſe free vapours are ſo light,</l>
                  <l>So frequent, that the conquer'd ſight</l>
                  <pb n="121" facs="tcp:102619:65"/>
                  <l>Deſpaires to find the rules that guide</l>
                  <l>Thoſe guilded ſhadows as they ſlide;</l>
                  <l>And therefore of the ſpacious ayre</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Joves</hi> royall Conſort had the care,</l>
                  <l>And by that power did once eſcape</l>
                  <l>Declining bold <hi>Ixion</hi>'s rape;</l>
                  <l>Shee with her own reſemblance grac'd</l>
                  <l>A ſhining cloud, which hee imbrac'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Such was that Image, ſo it ſmil'd</l>
                  <l>With ſeeming kindneſs, which beguil'd</l>
                  <l>Your <hi>Thirſis</hi> lately, when hee thought</l>
                  <l>Hee had his fleeting <hi>Coelia</hi> caught;</l>
                  <l>'Twas ſhap'd like her, but for the Fayr</l>
                  <l>Hee fill'd his arms with yeelding ayr.</l>
                  <l>A fate, for which he grieves the leſs,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe the Gods had like ſucceſs:</l>
                  <l>For in their ſtory, One (we ſee)</l>
                  <l>Purſues a Nymph and takes a tree;</l>
                  <pb n="122" facs="tcp:102619:66"/>
                  <l>A ſecond with a Lovers haſt</l>
                  <l>Soon overtakes whom he had chas'd,</l>
                  <l>But ſhe that did a Virgin ſeem,</l>
                  <l>Poſſeſt, appears a wandring ſtream;</l>
                  <l>For his ſuppoſed Love a third</l>
                  <l>Laies greedy hold upon a bird,</l>
                  <l>And ſtands amaz'd to find his deare</l>
                  <l>A wild Inhabitant of th'ayre.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>To theſe old tales ſuch Nymphs as you</l>
                  <l>Give credit, and ſtill make them new;</l>
                  <l>The Amorous now like wonders find</l>
                  <l>In the ſwift changes of your mind.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But <hi>Coelia,</hi> if you apprehend</l>
                  <l>The Muſe of your incenſed friend,</l>
                  <l>Nor would that hee record your blame,</l>
                  <l>And make it live; repeat the ſame,</l>
                  <l>Again deceive him and again,</l>
                  <l>And then he ſwears hee'l not complain:</l>
                  <pb n="123" facs="tcp:102619:66"/>
                  <l>For ſtill to be deluded ſo,</l>
                  <l>Is all the pleaſure Lovers know,</l>
                  <l>Who, like good Faulkners, take delight</l>
                  <l>Not in the quarrey, but the flight.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Of the taking of <hi>Sally.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>OF <hi>Jaſon, Theſeus,</hi> and ſuch Worthies old</l>
                  <l>Light ſeem the tales Antiquity has told,</l>
                  <l>Such Beaſts and Monſters as their force oppreſt,</l>
                  <l>Some places only, and ſome times infeſt;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sally,</hi> that ſcorn'd all power and lawes of Men,</l>
                  <l>Goods with their owners hurrying to their Den.</l>
                  <l>And future ages threatning with a crude</l>
                  <l>And ſalvage race ſucceſſively renew'd,</l>
                  <pb n="124" facs="tcp:102619:67"/>
                  <l>Their Kings deſpiſing with rebellious pride,</l>
                  <l>And foes profeſs'd to all the world beſide,</l>
                  <l>This peſt of mankind gives our Hero fame,</l>
                  <l>And through th'obliged world dilates his name.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Prophet once to cruell <hi>Agag</hi> ſaid,</l>
                  <l>As thy fierce ſword has Mothers childleſs made,</l>
                  <l>So ſhall the ſword make thine; and with that word</l>
                  <l>Hee hew'd the man in pieces with his ſword:</l>
                  <l>Juſt <hi>Charles</hi> like meaſure has return'd to theſe</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Pagan hands had ſtain'd the troubled Seas;</l>
                  <l>With ſhips they made the ſpoiled Merchants mourn,</l>
                  <l>With ſhips their City and themſelves are torn;</l>
                  <l>One ſquadron of our winged Caſtles ſent</l>
                  <l>O'rthrew their Fort, and all their Navy rent.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For not content the dangers to increaſe,</l>
                  <l>And act the part of tempeſts in the Seas,</l>
                  <l>Like hungry Wolves theſe Pirats from our ſhore</l>
                  <l>Whole flocks of ſheep and raviſh'd cattell bore.</l>
                  <pb n="125" facs="tcp:102619:67"/>
                  <l>Safely they did on other Nations prey:</l>
                  <l>Fooles, to provoke the Soveraign of the Sea!</l>
                  <l>Mad <hi>Cacus</hi> ſo, whom like ill Fate perſwades,</l>
                  <l>The Herd of fair <hi>Alcmena</hi>'s ſeed invades,</l>
                  <l>Who for revenge, and mortalls glad reliefe</l>
                  <l>Sack'd the dark Cave, and cruſh'd that horrid thiefe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Morocco</hi>'s Monarch wond'ring at this fact,</l>
                  <l>Save that his preſence his affaires exact,</l>
                  <l>Had come in perſon to have ſeen and known</l>
                  <l>The injur'd worlds revenger and his own;</l>
                  <l>Hither he ſends the chiefe among his Peeres,</l>
                  <l>Who in his Barke well-choſen preſents bears</l>
                  <l>To the renown'd for piety and force,</l>
                  <l>Poore Captives manumis'd, and matchleſs horſe.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:102619:68"/>
               <head>To Miſtris <hi>Braugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>FAire fellow-ſervant, May your gentle eare</l>
                  <l>Prove more propitious to my ſlighted care,</l>
                  <l>Then the bright Dame's we ſerve, for her reliefe</l>
                  <l>(Vext with the long expreſſions of my griefe)</l>
                  <l>Receive theſe plaints, nor will her high diſdain</l>
                  <l>Forbid my humble Muſe to court her train.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>So in thoſe Nations which the Sun adore</l>
                  <l>Some modeſt Perſian, or ſome weak-ey'd Moore,</l>
                  <l>No higher dares advance his dazled ſight;</l>
                  <l>Then to ſome guilded cloud, which neere the light</l>
                  <l>Of their aſcending God adorns the Eaſt,</l>
                  <l>And graced with his beams outſhines the reſt.</l>
                  <pb n="127" facs="tcp:102619:68"/>
                  <l>Thy skilfull hand contributes to our wo,</l>
                  <l>And whets thoſe Arrows which confound us ſo;</l>
                  <l>A thouſand <hi>Cupids</hi> in thoſe curles doe ſit,</l>
                  <l>Thoſe curious Nets your ſlender fingers knit:</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Graces</hi> put not more exactly on</l>
                  <l>Th'attire of <hi>Venus,</hi> when the Ball ſhe won,</l>
                  <l>Then <hi>Sachariſſa</hi> by thy care is dreſt,</l>
                  <l>When all our youth prefers her to the reſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>You the ſoft ſeaſons know, when beſt her mind</l>
                  <l>May be to pity or to love inclin'd,</l>
                  <l>In ſome well choſen houre ſupply his fear,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe hopeleſs love durſt never tempt the ear</l>
                  <l>Of that ſtern Goddeſs; You (her prieſt) declare</l>
                  <l>What offrings may propitiate the Faire,</l>
                  <l>Rich orient Pearl, bright ſtones that ne'r decay,</l>
                  <l>Or poliſh'd lines which longer laſt then they:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For if I thought ſhee took delight in thoſe,</l>
                  <l>To where the chearfull Morn does firſt diſcloſe,</l>
                  <pb n="128" facs="tcp:102619:69"/>
                  <l>(The ſhady night removing with her beams)</l>
                  <l>Wing'd with bold Love, I'd fly to fetch ſuch gems.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But ſince her eyes, her teeth, her lip excels</l>
                  <l>All that is found in Mines or fiſhes ſhels,</l>
                  <l>Her nobler part as far exceeding theſe,</l>
                  <l>None but immortall gifts her mind can pleaſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thoſe ſhining Jewels <hi>Greece</hi> and <hi>Troy</hi> beſtow'd,</l>
                  <l>The ſnowy wriſts, and lovely neck did lode</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Sparta</hi>'s Queen, but when the Town was burn'd,</l>
                  <l>Thoſe fading glories were to aſhes turn'd;</l>
                  <l>Her beauty too had periſh'd, and her fame,</l>
                  <l>Had not the Muſe redeem'd them from the Flame.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="129" facs="tcp:102619:69"/>
               <head>Puerperium.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>YOu Gods that have the power</l>
                  <l>To trouble and compoſe</l>
                  <l>All that's beneath your bower,</l>
                  <l>Calme ſilence on the Seas, on earth impoſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Faire <hi>Venus,</hi> in thy ſoft armes</l>
                  <l>The God of rage confine;</l>
                  <l>For thy whiſpers are the charmes</l>
                  <l>Which only can divert his fierce deſigne.</l>
                  <l>What though hee frowne, and to tumult doe incline?</l>
                  <l>Thou the flame</l>
                  <l>Kindled in his breaſt canſt tame</l>
                  <l>With that ſnow which unmelted lyes on thine.</l>
                  <pb n="130" facs="tcp:102619:70"/>
                  <l>Great Goddeſs, give this thy ſacred Iſland reſt,</l>
                  <l>Make heaven ſmile,</l>
                  <l>That no ſtorme diſturbe us while</l>
                  <l>Thy chiefe care our <hi>Halcyon</hi> builds her neſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Great <hi>Gloriana,</hi> faire <hi>Gloriana,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Bright as high heaven is and fertile as earth,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe beauty relieves us</l>
                  <l>Whoſe royall bed gives us</l>
                  <l>Both glory and peace,</l>
                  <l>Our preſent joy, our hopes increaſe.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="131" facs="tcp:102619:70"/>
               <head>To <hi>Phillis.</hi>
               </head>
               <l>
                  <hi>PHillis,</hi> why ſhould we delay</l>
               <l>Pleaſures ſhorter then the day?</l>
               <l>Could we (which we never can)</l>
               <l>Stretch our lifes beyond their ſpan,</l>
               <l>Beauty like a ſhadow flies,</l>
               <l>And our youth before us dies:</l>
               <l>Or would youth and beauty ſtay,</l>
               <l>Love has wings, and will away,</l>
               <l>Love has ſwifter wings then time.</l>
               <l>Change in love to heaven does climbe;</l>
               <l>Gods that never change their ſtate,</l>
               <l>Varied oft their love and hate:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Phillis,</hi> to this truth we owe</l>
               <l>All the love betwixt us two;</l>
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:102619:71"/>
               <l>Let not you and I enquire,</l>
               <l>What has bin our paſt deſire;</l>
               <l>On what ſhepheards you have ſmil'd,</l>
               <l>Or what nymphs I have beguil'd;</l>
               <l>Leave it to the planets too,</l>
               <l>What we ſhall hereafter doe;</l>
               <l>For the joyes we now may prove,</l>
               <l>Take advice of preſent Love.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>To <hi>Phillis.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>PHillis</hi>' twas love that injur'd you,</l>
                  <l>And on that rock your <hi>Thirſis</hi> threw,</l>
                  <l>Who for proud <hi>Coelia</hi> could have dy'd,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt you no leſs accus'd his pride.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:102619:71"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Fond Love his darts at random throws,</l>
                  <l>And nothing ſprings from what he ſows<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>From foes diſcharg'd as often meet</l>
                  <l>The ſhining points of arrowes fleet</l>
                  <l>In the wide ayre creating fire,</l>
                  <l>As ſoules that joyne in one deſire.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Love made the lovely <hi>Venus</hi> burne</l>
                  <l>In vaine, and for the cold Youth mourne,</l>
                  <l>Who the purſuite of churliſh beaſts</l>
                  <l>Prefer'd to ſleeping on her breaſts.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Love makes ſo many hearts the prize</l>
                  <l>Of the bright <hi>Carliſles</hi> conqu'ring eyes,</l>
                  <l>Which ſhee regards no more then they</l>
                  <l>The teares of leſſer beauties weigh:</l>
                  <l>So have I ſeene the loſt clouds powre</l>
                  <l>Into the Sea an uſeleſs ſhowre;</l>
                  <l>And the vext ſaylers curſe the rain,</l>
                  <l>For which poor ſhepheards pray'd in vain.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="134" facs="tcp:102619:72"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then <hi>(Phillis)</hi> ſince our paſſions are</l>
                  <l>Govern'd by chance, and not the care</l>
                  <l>But ſport of heaven, which takes delight</l>
                  <l>To looke upon this <hi>Parthian</hi> fight</l>
                  <l>Of Love, ſtill flying or in chaſe,</l>
                  <l>Never incountring face to face;</l>
                  <l>No more to Love wee'l ſacrifice,</l>
                  <l>But to the beſt of Deities;</l>
                  <l>And let our hearts which Love disjoyn'd,</l>
                  <l>By his kind Mother bee combin'd.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="song">
               <pb n="135" facs="tcp:102619:72"/>
               <head>Song.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVHile I liſten to thy voyce,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Chloris,</hi> I feele my life decay;</l>
                  <l>That powerfull noyſe</l>
                  <l>Calls my fleeting ſoule away.</l>
                  <l>Oh, ſuppreſs that magick ſound,</l>
                  <l>Which deſtroyes without a wound.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Peace <hi>Chloris,</hi> peace, or ſinging dye,</l>
                  <l>That together you and I</l>
                  <l>To heav'n may goe:</l>
                  <l>For all wee know</l>
                  <l>Of what the bleſſed doe above,</l>
                  <l>It that they ſing, and that they love.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="song">
               <pb n="136" facs="tcp:102619:73"/>
               <head>Song.</head>
               <l>Stay <hi>Phoebus,</hi> ſtay,</l>
               <l>The world to which you fly ſo faſt</l>
               <l>Conveying day</l>
               <l>From us to them, can pay your haſt</l>
               <l>With no ſuch object, nor ſalute your Riſe</l>
               <l>With no ſuch wonders as <hi>de Mornay's</hi> eyes.</l>
               <l>Well does this prove</l>
               <l>The errour of thoſe antique bookes,</l>
               <l>Which made you move</l>
               <l>About the world; her charming lookes</l>
               <l>Would fix your beames, and make it ever day,</l>
               <l>Did not the rowling earth ſnatch her away.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="137" facs="tcp:102619:73"/>
               <head>To <hi>Amoret.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>A <hi>Moret,</hi> the milky way,</l>
                  <l>Fram'd of many nameleſs ſtars;</l>
                  <l>The ſmooth ſtream, where none can ſay</l>
                  <l>Hee this drop to that prefers:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Amoret,</hi> my lovely ſo,</l>
                  <l>Tell me where thy ſtrength doth ly,</l>
                  <l>Where the power that charms us ſo;</l>
                  <l>In thy ſoul, or in thy ey?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>By that ſnowy neck alone,</l>
                  <l>Or thy grace in motion ſeen,</l>
                  <l>No ſuch wonders could be done;</l>
                  <l>Yet thy waſt is ſtreight and clean,</l>
                  <l>As <hi>Cupids</hi> ſhaft, or <hi>Hermes</hi> rod,</l>
                  <l>And powerfull too as either God.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="138" facs="tcp:102619:74"/>
               <head>To my Lord of <hi>Falkland.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>BRave <hi>Holland</hi> leads, and with him <hi>Falkland</hi> goes;</l>
                  <l>Who hears this told, and does not ſtraight ſuppoſe</l>
                  <l>We ſend the <hi>Graces</hi> and the <hi>Muſes</hi> forth</l>
                  <l>To civilize, and to inſtruct the North?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Not that theſe ornaments make ſwords leſs ſharp;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Apollo</hi> wears as well his Bow as Harp;</l>
                  <l>And though he be the Patron of that Spring</l>
                  <l>Where in calm Peace the ſacred Virgins ſing,</l>
                  <l>He courage had to guard th'invaded throne</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Jove,</hi> and caſt th'ambitious Giants down.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Ah! (noble Friend) with what impatience all</l>
                  <l>That know thy worth, and know how prodigall</l>
                  <pb n="139" facs="tcp:102619:74"/>
                  <l>Of thy great Soul thou art, longing to twiſt</l>
                  <l>Bayes with that Ivy which ſo early kiſt</l>
                  <l>Thy youthfull Temples, with what horrour wee</l>
                  <l>Think on the blind events of war, and thee</l>
                  <l>To Fate expoſing that all-knowing breſt</l>
                  <l>Among the throng as cheaply as the reſt,</l>
                  <l>Where Oaks and brambles (if the Copſe be burn'd)</l>
                  <l>Confounded lie to the ſame aſhes turn'd!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Some happy wind over the Ocean blow</l>
                  <l>This tempeſt yet, which frights our Iſland ſo,</l>
                  <l>Guarded with ſhips, and all the Sea our own,</l>
                  <l>From heaven this miſchief on our heads is thrown.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In a late Dream the <hi>Genius</hi> of this Land</l>
                  <l>Amaz'd I ſaw like the fair <hi>Hebrew</hi> ſtand,</l>
                  <l>When firſt ſhe felt the twins begin to jar,</l>
                  <l>And found her womb the ſeat of civill war;</l>
                  <l>Inclin'd to whoſe relief, and with preſage</l>
                  <l>Of better fortune for the preſent Age,</l>
                  <pb n="140" facs="tcp:102619:75"/>
                  <l>Heaven ſends, quoth I, this diſcord for our good,</l>
                  <l>To warm perhaps, but not to waſte our blood;</l>
                  <l>To raiſe our drooping ſpirits, grown the ſcorn</l>
                  <l>Of our proud Neighbours, who ere long ſhall mourn</l>
                  <l>(Though now they joy in our expected harms)</l>
                  <l>Wee had occaſion to reſume our Arms,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>A Lion ſo with ſelf-provoking ſmart,</l>
                  <l>His rebell tail ſcourging his nobler part,</l>
                  <l>Calls up his courage, then begins to roare,</l>
                  <l>And charge his foes, who thought him mad before.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="141" facs="tcp:102619:75"/>
               <head>Of a Lady who writ in praiſe of <hi>Mira.</hi>
               </head>
               <l>VVHile ſhe pretends to make the graces known</l>
               <l>Of matchleſs <hi>Mira,</hi> ſhe reveals her own;</l>
               <l>And when ſhe would anothers praiſe indite,</l>
               <l>Is by her glaſs inſtructed how to write.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>To one married to an old man.</head>
               <l>SInce thou wouldſt needs, bewitch'd with ſome ill charms,</l>
               <l>Be buried in thoſe monumentall arms,</l>
               <l>All wee can wiſh, is, May that earth lie light</l>
               <l>Upon thy tender limbs, and ſo Good night.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="142" facs="tcp:102619:76"/>
               <head>For the Drinking of Healths.</head>
               <l>LEt Brutes and Vegetals that cannot thinke,</l>
               <l>So far as drought and Nature urges, drinke;</l>
               <l>A more indulgent Miſtris guides our ſprights,</l>
               <l>Reaſon, that dares beyond our appetites,</l>
               <l>Shee would our care as well as thirſt redreſs,</l>
               <l>And with Divinity rewards exceſs.</l>
               <l>Deſerted <hi>Ariadne</hi> thus ſupplide,</l>
               <l>Did perjur'd <hi>Theſeus</hi> cruelty deride,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Bacchus</hi> imbrac'd from her exalted thought</l>
               <l>Baniſh'd the man, her paſſion, and his fault.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Bacchus</hi> and <hi>Phoebus</hi> are by <hi>Jove</hi> alli'd,</l>
               <l>And each by others timely heat ſuppli'd:</l>
               <l>All that the Grapes owe to his ripening fires,</l>
               <l>Is paid in numbers which their joyce inſpires.</l>
               <pb n="143" facs="tcp:102619:76"/>
               <l>Wine fills the veines, and Healths are underſtood</l>
               <l>To give our friends a title to our blood:</l>
               <l>Who naming me doth warm his courage ſo,</l>
               <l>Shews for my ſake what his bold hand would do.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>To <hi>Flavia.</hi>
               </head>
               <head>Song.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>'TIs not your Beauty can ingage</l>
                  <l>My wary Heart;</l>
                  <l>The Sun in all his Pride and Rage</l>
                  <l>Has not that Art;</l>
                  <l>And yet he ſhines as bright as you,</l>
                  <l>If brightneſs could our Soules ſubdue.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="144" facs="tcp:102619:77"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>'Tis not the pretty things you ſay,</l>
                  <l>Or thoſe you write,</l>
                  <l>Which can make <hi>Thirſis</hi> heart your Prey,</l>
                  <l>For that delight,</l>
                  <l>The graces of a well taught minde</l>
                  <l>In ſome of our own Sex we finde.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>No <hi>Flavia,</hi> 'tis your Love I fear,</l>
                  <l>Loves ſureſt Darts</l>
                  <l>Thoſe which ſo ſeldome fail him are</l>
                  <l>Headed with Hearts,</l>
                  <l>Their very ſhadow makes us yield,</l>
                  <l>Diſſemble well, and win the Field.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="145" facs="tcp:102619:77"/>
               <head>Of my Lady <hi>Iſabella</hi> playing on the Lute.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>SUch moving ſounds from ſuch a careleſs touch,</l>
                  <l>So unconcern'd her ſelfe, and we ſo much!</l>
                  <l>What Art is this; that with ſo little pains</l>
                  <l>Tranſports us thus, and o'r the ſpirit raigns?</l>
                  <l>The trembling ſtrings about her fingers croud,</l>
                  <l>And tell their joy for every kiſs aloud;</l>
                  <l>Small force there needs to make them tremble ſo;</l>
                  <l>Touch'd by that hand, who would not tremble too?</l>
                  <l>Here Love takes ſtand, and while ſhe charms the eare,</l>
                  <l>Empties his Quiver on the liſtning Deere:</l>
                  <l>Muſick ſo ſoftens and diſarms the mind,</l>
                  <l>That not an Arrow does reſiſtance find;</l>
                  <l>Thus the faire Tyrant celebrates the prize,</l>
                  <l>And acts her ſelf the triumph of her eyes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>So <hi>Nero</hi> once, with Harp in hand, ſurvey'd</l>
                  <l>His flaming <hi>Rome,</hi> and as it burn'd, he play'd.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="146" facs="tcp:102619:78"/>
               <head>The fall.</head>
               <l>SEe how the willing earth gave way</l>
               <l>To take th'impreſſion where ſhee lay!</l>
               <l>See how the mould, as loath to leave</l>
               <l>So ſweete a burden, ſtill does cleave</l>
               <l>Cloſe to th'Nymphs ſtain'd garment! here</l>
               <l>The comming Spring would firſt appeare,</l>
               <l>And all this place with roſes ſtrow,</l>
               <l>If buſie feet would let them grow:</l>
               <l>Here <hi>Venus</hi> ſmil'd to ſee blind Chance</l>
               <l>It ſelfe before her Son advance,</l>
               <l>And a faire Image to preſent</l>
               <l>Of what the Boy ſo long had meant.</l>
               <l>'Twas ſuch a chance as this made all</l>
               <l>The world into this order fall;</l>
               <pb n="147" facs="tcp:102619:78"/>
               <l>Thus the firſt Lovers, on the clay</l>
               <l>Of which they were compoſed, lay;</l>
               <l>So in their prime with equall grace</l>
               <l>Met the firſt Patterns of our Race;</l>
               <l>Then bluſh not (Faire) or on him frown,</l>
               <l>Or wonder how you both came down;</l>
               <l>But touch him, and hee'l tremble ſtraight,</l>
               <l>How could he then ſupport your waight?</l>
               <l>How could the Youth (alas!) but bend,</l>
               <l>When his whole heaven upon him lean'd?</l>
               <l>If ought by him amiſs were done,</l>
               <l>'T was that he let you riſe ſo ſoone.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="148" facs="tcp:102619:79"/>
               <head>Of <hi>Silvia.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>OUr ſighes are heard, juſt Heaven declares</l>
                  <l>The ſenſe it has of Lovers cares;</l>
                  <l>She that ſo far the reſt out-ſhin'd,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Silvia</hi> the faire, while ſhe was kind,</l>
                  <l>As if her frowns impair'd her brow,</l>
                  <l>Seems onely not unhandſome now:</l>
                  <l>So when the skie makes us endure</l>
                  <l>A ſtorme, it ſelfe becomes obſcure.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Hence 'tis that I conceale my flame,</l>
                  <l>Hiding from <hi>Flavia</hi>'s ſelfe her name,</l>
                  <l>Leſt ſhe provoking Heaven ſhould prove</l>
                  <l>How it rewards neglected Love:</l>
                  <pb n="149" facs="tcp:102619:79"/>
                  <l>Betrer a thouſand ſuch as I,</l>
                  <l>Their griefe untold, ſhould pine and die,</l>
                  <l>Then her bright Morning overcaſt</l>
                  <l>With ſullen clouds ſhould be defac'd.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>The Bud.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>LAtely on yonder ſwelling Buſh,</l>
                  <l>Big with many a coming Roſe,</l>
                  <l>This early Bud began to bluſh,</l>
                  <l>And did but halfe it ſelfe diſcloſe:</l>
                  <l>I pluck'd it, though no better grown,</l>
                  <l>Yet now you ſee how full 'tis blown.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="150" facs="tcp:102619:80"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Still as I did the leaves inſpire,</l>
                  <l>With ſuch a purple light they ſhone.</l>
                  <l>As if they had been made of fire,</l>
                  <l>And ſpreading ſo would flame anon.</l>
                  <l>All that was meant by Aire or Sun</l>
                  <l>To the young Flower, my breath has done.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If our looſe breath ſo much can doe,</l>
                  <l>What may the ſame in formes of Love,</l>
                  <l>Of pureſt Love and Muſick too,</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Flavia</hi> it aſpires to move;</l>
                  <l>When that which lifeleſs Buds perſuades</l>
                  <l>To wax more ſoft, her youth invades?</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="151" facs="tcp:102619:80"/>
               <head>To a Lady ſinging a Song of his compoſing.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>CHloris,</hi> your ſelfe you ſo excell,</l>
                  <l>When you vouchſafe to breath my thought,</l>
                  <l>That like a Spirit with this ſpell</l>
                  <l>Of my own teaching I am caught.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>That Eagles fate and mine are one,</l>
                  <l>Which on the ſhaft that made him die,</l>
                  <l>Eſpi'd a feather of his own,</l>
                  <l>Wherewith hee wont to ſoare ſo high.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Had <hi>Echo</hi> with ſo ſweet a grace</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Narciſſus</hi> loud complaints return'd,</l>
                  <l>Not for reflection of his face,</l>
                  <l>But of his voyce the Boy had mourn'd.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="152" facs="tcp:102619:81"/>
               <head>At the Marriage of the Dwarfes.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THe Signe or Chance makes others wive,</l>
                  <l>But Nature did this Match contrive;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Eve</hi> might as well have <hi>Adam</hi> fled,</l>
                  <l>As ſhe deni'd her little Bed</l>
                  <l>To him, for whom Heav'n ſeem'd to frame,</l>
                  <l>And meaſure out this onely Dame.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thrice happy is that humble Paire</l>
                  <l>Beneath the levell of all Care,</l>
                  <l>Over whoſe heads thoſe Arrows fly</l>
                  <l>Of ſad Diſtruſt and Jealouſie,</l>
                  <l>Secured in as high extream,</l>
                  <l>As if the World held none but them.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="153" facs="tcp:102619:81"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>To him the faireſt Nymphs doe ſhow</l>
                  <l>Like moving Mountains topt with Snow;</l>
                  <l>And every man a <hi>Polypheme</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Does to his <hi>Galatea</hi> ſeeme:</l>
                  <l>None may preſume her faith to prove;</l>
                  <l>He profers Death, that profers Love.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Ah <hi>(Chloris)</hi> that kind Nature thus</l>
                  <l>From all the World had ſever'd us,</l>
                  <l>Creating for our ſelves us two,</l>
                  <l>As Love has me for onely you!</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>Vpon</hi> Ben: Iohnſon.</head>
               <l>MIrrour of Poets, Mirrour of our Age,</l>
               <l>Which her whole face beholding on thy Stage,</l>
               <l>Pleas'd and diſpleas'd with her own faults, indures</l>
               <l>A remedy like thoſe whom Muſick cures:</l>
               <pb n="154" facs="tcp:102619:82"/>
               <l>Thou haſt alone thoſe various inclinations</l>
               <l>Which Nature gives to Ages, Sexes, Nations;</l>
               <l>Haſt tracked with thy all-reſembling Pen</l>
               <l>What ever Cuſtome has impos'd on Men,</l>
               <l>Or ill-got Habits (which diſtorts them ſo,</l>
               <l>That ſcarce one Brother can the brother know)</l>
               <l>Is repreſenting to the wondring eyes</l>
               <l>Of all that ſee or read thy Comedies;</l>
               <l>Who ever in thoſe Glaſſes look, may find</l>
               <l>The ſpots return'd, or graces of the mind;</l>
               <l>And by the helpe of ſo divine an Art,</l>
               <l>At leiſure view and dreſs his nobler Part.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Narciſſus</hi> cous'ned by that flattering Well,</l>
               <l>And nothing could but of his beauty tell;</l>
               <l>Had here diſcovering the deform'd eſtate</l>
               <l>Of his fond mind preſerv'd himſelfe with hate.</l>
               <l>But Vertue too, aſwell as Vice, is clad</l>
               <l>In fleſh and blood ſo well, that <hi>Plato</hi> had</l>
               <pb n="155" facs="tcp:102619:82"/>
               <l>Beheld what his high fancie once embrac'd,</l>
               <l>Vertue with colours, ſpeech, and motion grac'd.</l>
               <l>The ſundry Poſtures of thy copious Muſe</l>
               <l>Who would expreſs, a thouſand Tongues muſt uſe;</l>
               <l>Whoſe Fate's no leſs peculiar then thy Art;</l>
               <l>For as thou couldſt all Characters impart,</l>
               <l>So none can render thine, who ſtill eſcapes</l>
               <l>Like <hi>Proteus</hi> in variety of ſhapes,</l>
               <l>Who was, nor this, nor that, but all we find,</l>
               <l>And all we can imagine in mankind.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="156" facs="tcp:102619:83"/>
               <head>To Maſter <hi>George Sands</hi> on his Tranſlation of ſome part of the Bible.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>HOw bold a work attempts that Pen,</l>
                  <l>Which would enrich our vulgar tongue</l>
                  <l>With the high raptures of thoſe men,</l>
                  <l>Who here with the ſame Spirit ſung,</l>
                  <l>Wherewith they now aſſiſt the Quire</l>
                  <l>Of Angels, who their Songs admire?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What ever thoſe inſpired Soules</l>
                  <l>Were urged to expreſs, did ſhake</l>
                  <l>The aged Deepe, and both the Poles,</l>
                  <l>Their num'rous thunder could awake</l>
                  <l>Dull Earth, which does with Heaven conſent?</l>
                  <l>To all they wrote, and all they meant.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="157" facs="tcp:102619:83"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Say (ſacred Bard) what could beſtow</l>
                  <l>Courage on thee to ſoare ſo high?</l>
                  <l>Tell me (brave Friend) what help'd thee ſo</l>
                  <l>To ſhake off all Mortalitie?</l>
                  <l>To light this Torch, thou haſt climb'd higher</l>
                  <l>Then he who ſtole Coeleſtiall fier.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chloris</hi> and <hi>Hilas.</hi>
               </head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chl.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>HIlas,</hi> ô <hi>Hilas!</hi> why ſit we mute,</l>
                  <l>Now that each Bird ſaluteth the Spring?</l>
                  <l>Winde up the ſlack'ned ſtrings of thy Lute,</l>
                  <l>Never canſt thou want matter to ſing:</l>
                  <l>For Love thy breaſt does fill with ſuch a ſite,</l>
                  <l>That whatſoe'r is faire moves thy deſire.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="158" facs="tcp:102619:84"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hil.</speaker>
                  <l>Sweeteſt, you know the ſweeteſt of things</l>
                  <l>Of various flowers the Bees doe compoſe,</l>
                  <l>Yet no particular taſt it brings</l>
                  <l>Of Violet, Woodbine, Pink, or Roſe:</l>
                  <l>So Love the reſultance is of all our Graces,</l>
                  <l>Which flow from a thouſand ſeverall faces.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chl. Hilas,</speaker>
                  <l>the Birds which chaunt it in this Grove,</l>
                  <l>Could we but know the language they uſe,</l>
                  <l>They would inſtruct us better in Love,</l>
                  <l>And reprehend thy inconſtant Muſe;</l>
                  <l>For Love their breſts does fill with ſuch a fire,</l>
                  <l>That what they once do chooſe bounds their deſire.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hil. Chloris,</speaker>
                  <l>this change the Birds doe approve,</l>
                  <l>Which the warm Seaſon hither does bring;</l>
                  <l>Time from your ſelfe does further remove</l>
                  <l>You, then the Winter from the gay Spring:</l>
                  <pb n="159" facs="tcp:102619:84"/>
                  <l>Shee that like Lightning ſhin'd while her face laſted,</l>
                  <l>The Oak now reſembles which Lightning has blaſted.</l>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Vnder a Ladies Picture.</head>
               <l>SUch <hi>Helen</hi> was, and who can blame the Boy</l>
               <l>That in ſo bright a flame conſum'd his <hi>Troy?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But had like Vertue ſhin'd in that faire Greek,</l>
               <l>The amorous Shepheard had not dar'd to ſeek,</l>
               <l>Or hope for pity, but with ſilent moane</l>
               <l>And better fate had periſhed alone.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="160" facs="tcp:102619:85"/>
               <head>In anſwer of Sir <hi>John Sucklins</hi> Verſes.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>STay here fond Youth, and ask no more, be wiſe,</l>
                  <l>Knowing too much long ſince loſt Paradiſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>And by your knowledge we ſhould be bereft</l>
                  <l>Of all that Paradiſe which yet is loſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>The vertuous joyes thou haſt, thou wouldſt, ſhould ſtil</l>
                  <l>Laſt in their pride, and wouldſt not take it ill,</l>
                  <l>If rudely from ſweet Dreams, and for a toy</l>
                  <l>Thou wert awak'd<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he wakes himſelfe that does enjoy.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="161" facs="tcp:102619:85"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>How can the joy or hope which you allow,</l>
                  <l>Be ſtiled vertuous, and the end not ſo?</l>
                  <l>Talke in your ſleep, and ſhadows ſtill admire;</l>
                  <l>'Tis true, he wakes that feeles this reall fire,</l>
                  <l>But to ſleep better; for who ere drinks deep</l>
                  <l>Of this Nepenthe, rocks himſelfe aſleep.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Fruition adds no new wealth, but deſtroyes,</l>
                  <l>And while it pleaſeth much, yet ſtill it cloyes;</l>
                  <l>Who thinkes he ſhall be happier made for that,</l>
                  <l>As reaſonably might hope, he might grow fat</l>
                  <l>By eating to a Surfeit, this once paſt</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hat reliſhes? even kiſſes loſe their taſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="162" facs="tcp:102619:86"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>Bleſſings may be repeated while they cloy;</l>
                  <l>But ſhall we ſtarve, 'cauſe Surfeitings deſtroy?</l>
                  <l>And if fruition did the taſte impaire</l>
                  <l>Of kiſſes, why ſhould yonder happy Paire,</l>
                  <l>Where joyes juſt <hi>Hymen</hi> warrants all the night,</l>
                  <l>Conſume the day too in this leſs delight?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Urge not 'tis neceſſary, alas! we know</l>
                  <l>The homelieſt thing that Man-kind does is ſo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>The World is of a large extent we ſee,</l>
                  <l>And muſt be peopled, Children there muſt bee,</l>
                  <l>So muſt Bread too: but ſince there are enough</l>
                  <l>Borne to that drudgery, what need we plough?</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="163" facs="tcp:102619:86"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>I need not plough, ſince what the ſtooping Hine</l>
                  <l>Gets of my pregnant Land, muſt all be mine;</l>
                  <l>But in this nobler Tillage 'tis not ſo,</l>
                  <l>For when <hi>Anchiſes</hi> did faire <hi>Venus</hi> know,</l>
                  <l>What intreſt had poore <hi>Vulcan</hi> in the Boy,</l>
                  <l>Great-ſoul'd <hi>Aeneas,</hi> or the preſent joy?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Women enjoy'd, what ere tofore they have been,</l>
                  <l>Are like Romances read, or Scenes once ſeen:</l>
                  <l>Fruition dulls or ſpoyles the Play much more,</l>
                  <l>Then if one read, or knew the Plot before.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>Playes and Romances read and ſeen doe fall,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Opinions, yet not ſeen at all</l>
                  <pb n="164" facs="tcp:102619:87"/>
                  <l>Whom would they pleaſe? to an Heroick tale</l>
                  <l>Would you not liſten, leſt it ſhould grow ſtale?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis Expectation makes a Bleſſing deare:</l>
                  <l>Heaven were not Heaven, if we knew what it were.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>If't were not Heaven, if we knew what it were.</l>
                  <l>'T would not be Heaven to them that now are there.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>As in proſpects we are there pleaſed moſt,</l>
                  <l>Where ſomething keeps the eie from being loſt,</l>
                  <l>And leaves roome to gueſs: ſo here reſtraint</l>
                  <l>Holds up delight, that with exceſs would faint.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="165" facs="tcp:102619:87"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>Reſtraint preſerves the pleaſure we have got,</l>
                  <l>But he ne'r has it that enjoyes it not.</l>
                  <l>In goodly proſpects, who contracts the ſpace,</l>
                  <l>Or takes not all the bounty of the place?</l>
                  <l>We wiſh remov'd what ſtandeth in our light,</l>
                  <l>And Nature blame for limiting our ſight,</l>
                  <l>Where you ſtand wiſely winking, that the view</l>
                  <l>Of the faire proſpect may be alwaies new,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>They who know all the wealth they have are poore,</l>
                  <l>Hee's onely Rich that cannot tell his ſtore.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>Not he that knows the wealth he has is poore,</l>
                  <l>But he that dares not touch, nor uſe his ſtore.</l>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="166" facs="tcp:102619:88"/>
               <head>To <hi>A. H.</hi> of the different ſucceſs of their Loves.</head>
               <l>THrice-happy Paire, of whom we cannot know</l>
               <l>Which firſt began to love, or loves moſt now:</l>
               <l>Faire courſe of Paſſion, where two Lovers ſtart</l>
               <l>And run together, heart ſtill yoakt in heart!</l>
               <l>Succesfull Youth, whom Love has taught the way</l>
               <l>To be victorious in thy firſt Eſſay!</l>
               <l>Sure Love's an Art beſt practiſed at firſt,</l>
               <l>And where th'experienc'd ſtill proſper worſt</l>
               <l>I with different Fate purſu'd in vain</l>
               <l>The haughty <hi>Coelia,</hi> till my juſt diſdain</l>
               <l>Of her neglect above that Paſſion born,</l>
               <l>Did pride to pride oppoſe, and ſcorn to ſcorn.</l>
               <l>Now ſhee rolents, but all too late to move</l>
               <l>A Heart diverted to a nobler Love:</l>
               <pb n="167" facs="tcp:102619:88"/>
               <l>The Scales are turn'd, her Kingdome weighs no more</l>
               <l>Now, then my vowes and ſervice did before.</l>
               <l>So in ſome well-wrought Hangings you may ſee</l>
               <l>How <hi>Hector</hi> leads, and how the Grecians flee;</l>
               <l>Here the fierce <hi>Mars</hi> his courage ſo inſpires,</l>
               <l>That with bold hands the <hi>Argive</hi> Flee the fires;</l>
               <l>But there from Heav'n the blew ey'd Virgin falls,</l>
               <l>And frighted <hi>Troy</hi> retires within her walls:</l>
               <l>They that are foremoſt in that bloody place</l>
               <l>Turn head anon, and gives the Conquerours chace.</l>
               <l>So like the Chances are of Love and Warre,</l>
               <l>That they alone in this diſtinguiſh'd are;</l>
               <l>In Love the Victors from the vanquiſh'd ſlie,</l>
               <l>They ſlie that wound, and they purſue that die.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="168" facs="tcp:102619:89"/>
               <head>An Apologie for having loved before.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THey that never had the uſe</l>
                  <l>Of the Grapes ſurprizing joyce,</l>
                  <l>To the firſt delicious cup</l>
                  <l>All their reaſon render up;</l>
                  <l>Neither doe, nor care to know</l>
                  <l>Whether it be the beſt or no.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>So they that are to Love enclin'd,</l>
                  <l>Sway'd by Chance, not choyce or art,</l>
                  <l>To the firſt that's faire or kind,</l>
                  <l>Make a preſent of their heart;</l>
                  <l>'Tis not ſhe that firſt we love,</l>
                  <l>But whom dying we approve,</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="169" facs="tcp:102619:89"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>To Man, that was i'th' Evening made,</l>
                  <l>Stars gave the firſt delight,</l>
                  <l>Admiring in the gloomy ſhade</l>
                  <l>Thoſe little drops of light.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then at <hi>Aurora,</hi> whoſe faire hand</l>
                  <l>Remov'd him from the skies,</l>
                  <l>Heegazing towards the Eaſt did ſtand,</l>
                  <l>Shee entertain'd his eies.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But when the bright Sun did appeare,</l>
                  <l>All thoſe he'gan deſpiſe:</l>
                  <l>His wonder was determin'd there,</l>
                  <l>Hee could no higher riſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="170" facs="tcp:102619:90"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Hee neither might, or wiſh'd to know</l>
                  <l>A more refulgent light</l>
                  <l>For that, as mine your Beauties now</l>
                  <l>Imploy his utmoſt ſight.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>
                  <hi>Palamede</hi> to <hi>Zelinde Ariana.</hi> lib. 6.</head>
               <l>FAireſt piece of well form'd earth,</l>
               <l>Vrge not thus your haughty Birth,</l>
               <l>The power which you have ore us lyes</l>
               <l>Not in your Race, but in your eyes.</l>
               <l>None but a Prince! alas, that voyce,</l>
               <l>Confines you to a narrow choyce;</l>
               <l>Should you no honey vow to taſt,</l>
               <l>But what the Maſter Bees have plac't</l>
               <pb n="171" facs="tcp:102619:90"/>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n compaſs of their Cells, how ſmal</l>
               <l>A portion to your ſhare would fall?</l>
               <l>Nor all appeare among thoſe few,</l>
               <l>Worthy the ſtock from whence they grew.</l>
               <l>The ſap which at the root is bred</l>
               <l>In Trees, through all the boughs is ſpred.</l>
               <l>But Vertues which in Parents ſhine,</l>
               <l>Make not like Progreſs through the Line.</l>
               <l>'Tis not from whom, but where wee live,</l>
               <l>The place does oft thoſe Graces give.</l>
               <l>Great <hi>Iulius</hi> on the Mountaines bred,</l>
               <l>A flock perhaps or herd had led:</l>
               <l>Hee that the world ſubdu'd had been</l>
               <l>But the beſt Wreſtler on the Green:</l>
               <l>'Tis art and Knowledge which draw forth</l>
               <l>The hidden ſeeds of native worth,</l>
               <l>They blow thoſe ſparks, and make them riſe</l>
               <l>Into ſuch flames as touch the Skies.</l>
               <pb n="172" facs="tcp:102619:91"/>
               <l>To the old Hero's hence was given</l>
               <l>A Pedegree which reach'd to Heaven;</l>
               <l>Of mortall Seed they were not held,</l>
               <l>Which other Mortalls ſo excell'd:</l>
               <l>And Beauty too in ſuch exceſs</l>
               <l>As yours, <hi>Zelinde,</hi> claymes no leſs;</l>
               <l>Smile but on me, and you ſhall ſcorn</l>
               <l>Henceforth to be of Princes born.</l>
               <l>I can deſcribe the ſhady Grove,</l>
               <l>Where your lov'd Mother ſlept with <hi>Jove,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And yet excuſe the faultleſs Dame</l>
               <l>Caught with her Spouſes ſhape and name;</l>
               <l>Thy matchleſs forme will credit bring</l>
               <l>To all the wonders I ſhall ſing.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="173" facs="tcp:102619:91" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>Loves Farewell.</head>
               <l>I Reading the path to Nobler ends,</l>
               <l>A long farewell to Love I gave:</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſolv'd my Country and my Friends</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll that remain'd of me ſhould have;</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd this Reſolve no mortall Dame,</l>
               <l>None but thoſe eyes could have o'rthrowne.</l>
               <l>The Nymph, I dare, nor need not name,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o high, ſo like her ſelfe alone:</l>
               <l>Thus the Oak, which now aſpires</l>
               <l>Above the feares of private fires,</l>
               <l>Grown, and deſign'd for nobler uſe,</l>
               <l>Not to make warm, but build the houſe;</l>
               <l>Though from our meaner flames ſecure,</l>
               <l>Muſt that which falls from heaven indure.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="174" facs="tcp:102619:92" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>To <hi>Chloris.</hi>
               </head>
               <l>
                  <hi>CHloris,</hi> what eminent wee know,</l>
               <l>Muſt for ſome cauſe be valued ſo;</l>
               <l>Things without uſe, though they be good,</l>
               <l>Are not by us ſo underſtood.</l>
               <l>The early Roſe made to diſplay</l>
               <l>Her buſhes to the youthfull <hi>May,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Doth yeeld her ſweets ſince he is faire.</l>
               <l>And courts her with a gentle ayre.</l>
               <l>Our ſtars too ſhew their excellence,</l>
               <l>Not by their light, but influence;</l>
               <l>When brighter Comets ſince ſtill known.</l>
               <l>Fatall to all, are lik't by none:</l>
               <l>So your admired beauty ſtill</l>
               <l>Is by effects made good or ill.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="175" facs="tcp:102619:92"/>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Madam,</salute>
               </opener>
               <l>AS in ſome climes the warmer Sun,</l>
               <l>Makes it full Summer ere the ſpring's begun,</l>
               <l>And with ripe fruit the bending boughts can load,</l>
               <l>Before the violets dare looke abroad:</l>
               <l>So meaſure not by any common uſe,</l>
               <l>The early love your brighter eyes produce.</l>
               <l>When lately your fair hand, in womans weed,</l>
               <l>Wrapt my glad head, I wiſh't me ſo indeed,</l>
               <l>That haſty time might never make me grow,</l>
               <l>Out of thoſe favours you afford me now;</l>
               <l>That I might ever ſuch indulgence find,</l>
               <l>And you not bluſh or thinke your ſelf too kind,</l>
               <l>Who now I feare while I theſe joyes expreſs,</l>
               <l>Begin to thinke how you may make them leſs:</l>
               <l>The ſound of love makes your ſoft heart affraide,</l>
               <l>And guard it ſelf, though but a child invade,</l>
               <l>And innocently at your white breaſt throw</l>
               <l>A dart as white, a Ball of new faln ſnow.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="176" facs="tcp:102619:93"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>An Epigram</hi> On a painted Lady with ill teeth.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>VVEre men ſo dull they could not ſee</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Lyce</hi> painted, ſhould they flee</l>
                  <l>Like ſimple Birds into a Net,</l>
                  <l>So groſly woven and ill ſet;</l>
                  <l>Her own teeth would undoe the knot,</l>
                  <l>And let all goe that ſhe had got.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thoſe teeth faire <hi>Lyce</hi> muſt not ſhow,</l>
                  <l>If ſhe would bite: her Lovers, though</l>
                  <l>Like Birds they ſtoop at ſeeming grapes,</l>
                  <l>Are diſabus'd when firſt ſhe gapes;</l>
                  <l>The rotten bones diſcovered there,</l>
                  <l>Show 'tis a painted Sepulcher.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="177" facs="tcp:102619:93"/>
               <head>On a Girdle.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THat which her ſlender waſte confin'd,</l>
                  <l>Shall now my joyfull temples bind;</l>
                  <l>No Monarch but would give his Crowne</l>
                  <l>His Armes might doe what this has done,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>It is my Heavens extreameſt Spheare,</l>
                  <l>The pale which held the lovely Deare,</l>
                  <l>My joy, my griefe, my hope, my Love,</l>
                  <l>Doe all within this Circle move.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>A narrow compas, and yet there</l>
                  <l>Dwells all that's good, and all that's faire:</l>
                  <l>Give me but what this Ribban ty'd,</l>
                  <l>Take all the ſun goes round beſide.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="178" facs="tcp:102619:94"/>
               <head>On Mr. <hi>Iohn Fletchers</hi> playes.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>FLetcher,</hi> to thee we doe not only owe.</l>
                  <l>All theſe good playes but thoſe others too,</l>
                  <l>Thy wit repeated does ſupport the Stage,</l>
                  <l>Credits the laſt, and entertaines this Age,</l>
                  <l>No worthies form'd by any Muſe but thine</l>
                  <l>Could purchaſe robes, to make themſelves ſo fine,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What brave Commander is not proud to ſee</l>
                  <l>Thy brave <hi>Melantius</hi> in his Gallantrie,</l>
                  <l>Our greateſt Ladys love to ſee their ſcorne</l>
                  <l>Out done by thine, in what themſelves have worne.</l>
                  <l>The Impatient widdow ere the yeare be done,</l>
                  <l>Sees thy <hi>Aſpaſia</hi> weeping in her gowne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I never yet the Tragicke ſtraine aſſayed,</l>
                  <l>Deter'd by that inimitable Maide.</l>
                  <pb n="179" facs="tcp:102619:94"/>
                  <l>And when I venture at the Comicke ſtile,</l>
                  <l>Thy ſcornfull Lady, ſeemes to mocke my toile.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus has thy Muſe at once improv'd and marr'd,</l>
                  <l>Our ſport in playes by rendring it too hard.</l>
                  <l>So when a ſort of luſty ſhepheards throwe,</l>
                  <l>The barre by turnes, and none the reſt out goe</l>
                  <l>So farre but that the beſt are meaſuring caſts,</l>
                  <l>There emulation, and there paſtimes laſts;</l>
                  <l>But it ſome braunie Yeoman of the guard</l>
                  <l>Stepp in and toſſe the axeltrie a yard,</l>
                  <l>Or more beyond the furtheſt marke, the reſt,</l>
                  <l>Diſpairing ſtand, Their ſport is at the beſt.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="180" facs="tcp:102619:95"/>
               <head>To <hi>Chloris</hi> uppon a favour receaved.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>CHloris,</hi> ſince firſt our calme of peace</l>
               <l>Was frighted hence, this good we finde.</l>
               <l>Your favours with your feares increaſe,</l>
               <l>And growing miſchiefs make you kinde.</l>
               <l>So the fayre tree which ſtill preſerves</l>
               <l>Her fruit and ſtate whilſt no wind blows,</l>
               <l>In ſtormes from that uprightneſſe ſwerves.</l>
               <l>And the glad earth about her ſtrowes</l>
               <l>With treaſure from her yeilding boughs.</l>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:102619:95"/>
            <head>The Table.</head>
            <list>
               <item>OF the danger his Majesty (being Prince) eſcaped at the rode at St. <hi>Andere. 1</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of His Majeſties receiving of the newes of the Duke of <hi>Buckinghams</hi> death. <hi>11</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To the King on His Navy. <hi>13</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Vpon his Majeſties repairing of <hi>Pauls. 15</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To the <hi>Queene</hi> occaſioned upon ſight of her Majeſties Picture. <hi>19</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The apologie of ſleep, for not aproaching the Lady who can doe any thing but ſleepe when ſhe pleaſeth. <hi>23</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The country to my lady of Carlile. <hi>26</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Counteſſe of Carliſle in mourning. <hi>28</hi>
               </item>
               <item>An anſwer to a libell againſt her &amp;c. <hi>31</hi>
               </item>
               <item>On my lady Dorothy Sidneys Picture. <hi>33</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To Vandike. <hi>34</hi>
               </item>
               <item>At Pens-Hurſt. <hi>37</hi>
               </item>
               <item>At Pens-Hurſt. <hi>40</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To my Lord of Leiceſter. <hi>42</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To my young lady Lucy Sidney. <hi>44</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the lady who can ſleep when ſhe pleaſeth <hi>45</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the miſreport of her being painted. <hi>47</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of her paſſing through a crowd of people. <hi>48</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Song. Say lovely dreame <hi>50</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:102619:96"/>
               <item>A Song. Behold the brand of beauty toſt, <hi>52</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To Amoret. <hi>53</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The ſtory of <hi>Phoebus</hi> and <hi>Daphne</hi> aplyed &amp;c <hi>57</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of Miſtris <hi>Arden, 59</hi>
               </item>
               <item>On the diſcovery of a ladies painting, <hi>60</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To a lady from whom he receiv'd a ſilver pen. <hi>62</hi>
               </item>
               <item>On a Brede of divers colours woven by foure Ladies. <hi>64</hi>
               </item>
               <item>On the head of a Stag. <hi>65</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To a lady in retirement. <hi>66</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Miſers Speech in a Maske. <hi>68</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To my lord of <hi>Northumberland</hi> upon the death of his Lady. <hi>69</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To my lord admirall of his late ſickneſſe &amp; recovery. <hi>72</hi>
               </item>
               <item>On the frendſhip betwixt <hi>Sachariſſa</hi> &amp; <hi>Amoret. 76</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A la malade. <hi>78</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of her Chamber. <hi>80</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of loving at first ſight. <hi>81</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The ſelfe baniſhed. <hi>83</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of and to the Queene. <hi>84</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Song. Goe lovely Roſe, <hi>89</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Thirſis. Galatea. 90</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Fabula Phoebi et Daphnis. 94</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The battell of the ſummer Jſlands, in three Cantos. <hi>95</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Vpon the death of the Lady Rich. <hi>108</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To the Queene Mother upon her lauding. <hi>113</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Song. Peace babling muſe, <hi>115</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of Love. <hi>116</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To the mutable Faire. <hi>119</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:102619:96"/>
               <item>Of the taking of <hi>Sally. 123</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To Miſtris <hi>Broughton. 126</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Puerperium. 129</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To <hi>Phillis. 131</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To <hi>Phillis. 132</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Song. While I liſten to thy voyce <hi>135</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A <hi>Song.</hi> Stay <hi>Phoebus</hi> ſtay. <hi>136</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To <hi>Amoret. 137</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To my Lora of <hi>Falkland. 138</hi>
               </item>
               <item>On a Lady who writ in praiſe of <hi>Mira. 141</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To one Married to an old man. <hi>141</hi>
               </item>
               <item>For the drinking of Healths. <hi>142</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To <hi>Flavia,</hi> a Song. <hi>143</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of my Lady <hi>Iſabella</hi> playing on a Lute. <hi>145</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Fall. <hi>146</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of <hi>Silvia. 148</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Bud, <hi>149</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To a Lady ſinging a Song of his Compoſing. <hi>151</hi>
               </item>
               <item>At the Marriage of the Dwarfs. <hi>152</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Upon <hi>Ben. Johnſon. 153</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To Mr. <hi>George Sands,</hi> on his Tranſlation of ſome part of the Bible. <hi>156</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chloris</hi> and <hi>Hilas. 157</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Under a Ladyes Picture. <hi>159</hi>
               </item>
               <item>In anſwer of Sir <hi>John Sucklins</hi> Verſes. <hi>160</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To <hi>A.H.</hi> of the different ſucceſs of their Loves. <hi>166</hi>
               </item>
               <item>An Apologie for having Loved before. <hi>168</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Palamede</hi> to <hi>Zelinde. Ariana,</hi> Lib. <hi>6. 170</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:102619:97"/>
               <item>Loves Farewell. <hi>173</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To <hi>Chloris. 174</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Madam. As in ſome climes. <hi>175</hi>
               </item>
               <item>An Epigram on a painted Lady with ill teeth. <hi>176</hi>
               </item>
               <item>On a Girdle. <hi>177</hi>
               </item>
               <item>On Mr. <hi>John Fletchers</hi> Playes. <hi>178</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To <hi>Cloris</hi> upon a Favour received. <hi>180</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:102619:97"/>
            <head>Mr. <hi>WALLERS</hi> Speech in Parliament againſt the Prelates Innovations.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Mr. Speaker,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>VVEE ſhall make it appeare, the errours of Divines who would that a Monarch, can bee abſolute, and that hee can do all things <hi>ad libitum,</hi> receding not onely from their Text, (though that bee wandring too) but from the way their own profeſſion might teach them. <hi>Stare ſuper vias antiquas,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move not the ancient bounds and Land-marks, which our Fathers have ſet.</p>
            <p>If to bee abſolute, were to bee reſtrained by no Lawes; Then can no King in Chriſtendome bee ſo, for they all ſtand obleidged to the Laws Chriſtian, and we ask no more, for to this Pillar, bee our Priviledges fixt. Our Kings at their <hi>Coronation,</hi> having taken a Sacred Oath, not to infringe them, I am ſorry theſe men take no more care, for the informing of our Faith of theſe things, which they tell us for our Soules health; whileſt wee know them ſo manifeſtly in the wrong way, in that which concernes the Liberties and Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of the Subjects of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:102619:98"/>
            <p>They gain preferment, and then it is no matter, though they neither beleeve themſelves, nor are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeved by others. But ſince they are ſo ready, to let looſe the Conſcience of our Kings, wee are the more carefully to proceed for our protection againſt this Polpit-law, by declaring, and reinforcing Municipall Laws of this Kingdom.</p>
            <p>It is worthy the obſervation, how new this opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or rather this way of riſing, is even amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            <p>For, (Mr. <hi>Speaker</hi>) Mr. <hi>Hooker,</hi> who was no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fractory man, (as they term it) thinks that the firſt government was Arbitray, untill it was found, that to live by one mans will, becomes all mens miſery; theſe are his words, and that theſe were the originall of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting Laws.</p>
            <p>And (Mr. <hi>Speaker,</hi>) if wee looke farther backe, our Hiſtories will tell us, that the Prelates of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, have often been the Mediators between the King and his Subjects, to preſent and pray redreſſe of their grievances, and had reciprocally then, as much love and reverence from the people.</p>
            <p>But theſe Preachers, more active then their Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, and wiſer then the Laws, have found out a better form of Goverment.</p>
            <p>The King muſt be a more abſolute Monarch, than any of his Pedeceſſours, and to them he muſt owe it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> though in the mean time, they hazard the hearts of his People, and involve Him into a thouſand Difficulties.</p>
            <p>For ſuppoſe, this forme of Government were incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:102619:98"/>(Mr. Speaker) this is but a Suppoſition; for this five hundred years it hath not only maintained us in ſafety, but made us victorious over other Nations: But ſuppoſe, this form of Government were inonconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient; and they have another <hi>Idea</hi> of one more conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient; We all know, how dangerous Innovations are, though to the better; and what hazard thoſe Princes run, that enterprize the Change of a long eſtabliſhed Government.</p>
            <p>Now (<hi>Mr. Speaker</hi>) of all our Kings that have gone before, and of all that are to ſucceed in this happy race, why ſhould ſo pious, and ſo good a King, be expoſed to this trouble and hazard? Beſides, that King ſo diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, can never doe any great matters abroad.</p>
            <p>But (<hi>Mr. Speaker</hi>) whileſt theſe men have thus bent their Wits againſt the Law of their Country; have they not neglected their own profeſſion? What tares are grown up in the field, which they ſhould have til<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, I leave it to a ſecond conſideration? not but Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion be the firſt thing in our purpoſes and deſires: But that which is firſt in dignity, is not alwayes to preceed in order of time, for well-being, ſuppoſes a being; and the firſt impediment which men naturally, endeavour to rem ove, is the want of thoſe things, without which they cannot ſubſiſt. God firſt aſſigned unto <hi>Adam,</hi> maintenance of life, and added to him a title to the reſt of the Creatures, before he appointed a Law to obſerve.</p>
            <p>And let me tell you, that if our Adverſaries have any ſuch deſigne, as there is nothing more eaſie, then to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe Religion on a people deprived of their Liberties, ſo
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:102619:99"/>there is nothing more hard, then to do the ſame upon Free-men.</p>
            <p>And therefore (<hi>Mr. Speaker</hi>) I conclude with this motion, that there may be an Order preſently made, that the firſt thing this Houſe goes about, ſhall be the reſtoring of this Nation in generall, to the fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall and vitall Liberties, the propriety of our Goods, and freedome of our Perſons: And then We will forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with conſider of the ſupply deſired.</p>
            <p>And thus ſhall We diſcharge the truſt repoſed in us by thoſe that ſent us hither: And His Majeſty ſhall ſee, that we will make more then ordinary haſt to ſatisfie <hi>His demands;</hi> and we ſhall let all thoſe know that ſeek to haſten the matter of ſupply, that they will ſo far delay it, as they give no interruption to the Former.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:102619:99"/>
            <head>Mr. WALLERS Speech in Parliament, at a Conference of both Houſes in the painted Chamber.
<date>6. <hi>July</hi> 1641.</date>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORDS.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Am commanded by the Houſe of Commons, to preſent you with theſe Articles againſt Mr. Juſtice <hi>Crawley,</hi> which when your Lordſhips ſhall have been pleaſed to heare read I ſhall take leave (according to cuſtome) to ſay ſomething of what I have collected from the ſenſe of that Houſe concerning the crimes therein conteined.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Here the charge was read conteining his extrajudicall opinions ſubſcribed, and judgement given for Ship-mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and afterward a declaration in his charge at on aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſize, that Ship-mony was ſo inhaerent alright in the Crown, that it would not be in the power of a Parliament to take it away.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>MY LORDS, Not only my wants but my af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections render me leſſe fit for this imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: for though it has not been my happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to have the Law a part of my breeding, there is no man honours that profeſſion more, or has a greater reverence towards the grave Judges the Oracles there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. Out of Parliament all our Courts of Juſtice are go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned or directed by them, and when a Parliament is
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:102619:100"/>call'd, if your Lordſhips were not aſſiſted by them, and the Houſe of Commons by other Gentlemen of that Robe, experience tells us it might runne a hazard of being ſtyled <hi>Parliamentum indoctorum.</hi> But as all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions are obnoxious to the malice of the profeſſors, and by them moſt eaſily betrayed, ſo (my Lords) theſe Articles have told you how theſe brothers of the Coyfe are become <hi>fratres in malo;</hi> how theſe ſonnes of the Law have torne out the bowells of their mother: But this Judge (whoſe charge you laſt heard) in one ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of his excells no leſſe his Fellowes, then they have done the worſt of their predeceſſours, in this conſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piracy againſt the Common-wealth. Of the Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for Shipmoney, and thoſe extrajudiciall opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons preceding the ſame (wherein they are joyntly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd) you have already heard; how unjuſt and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitious a proceeding that was in ſo publique a Cauſe, has beene ſufficiently expreſs'd to your Lordſhips: But this man, adding deſpaire to our miſery, tells us from the Bench, that Ship-money was a Right ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haerent in the Crowne, that it would not be in the power of an Act of Parliament to take it away. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in (my Lords) he did not onely give as deepe a wound to the Common-wealth as any of the reſt, but dipt his dart in ſuch a poyſon, that ſo farre as in him lay it might never receive a cure. As by thoſe abortive opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions ſubſcribing to the ſubverſion of our propriety, before hee heard what could be ſaid for it, he preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his owne, ſo by this declaration of his he ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to prevent the Judgement of your Lordſhips too,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:102619:100"/>and to confine the power of a Parliament, the onely place where this miſchiefe might be redreſt: Sure he is more wiſe and learned, then to beleeve himſelfe in this opinion, or not to know how ridiculous it would appeare to a Parliament, and how dangerous to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and therefore no doubt but by ſaying no Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment could aboliſh this Judgement, his meaning was that this Judgement had aboliſh't Parliaments.</p>
            <p>This impoſition of Ship-mony ſpringing from a pretended neceſſity, was it not enough that it was now grown annuall, but he muſt intayle it upon the State for ever, at once making neceſſity inh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent to the Crowne, and ſlavery to the Subject? Neceſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, which diſſolving all Law is ſo much more prejudiciall to his Majeſty then to any of us, by how much the Law has inveſted his Royall State with a greater power, and ampler fortune, for ſo undoubred a truth it has ever beene, that Kings as well as Subjects are involv'd in the confuſion which neceſſity produces, that the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, thought their gods alſo obliged by the ſame, <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reamus neceſſitati quam nec homines nec dii ſuperant:</hi> This Judge then having in his charge at the Aſſize de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd the diſſolution of the Law by this ſuppos'd ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, with what conſcience could hee at the ſame Aſſize proceed to condeme and puniſh men, unleſſe perhaps hee meant the Law was ſtill in force for our deſtruction, and not for our preſervation, that it ſhould have power to kill, but none to protect us; a thing no leſſe horrid then if the Sunne ſhould burne without lighting us, or the earth ſerve onely to bury and not to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:102619:101"/>feed and nouriſh us But (my Lords) to demonſtrate that this was a ſuppoſitious impos'd neceſſity, and ſuch as they could remove when they pleas'd, at the laſt Convention in Parliament a price was ſet upon it, <hi>for twelve Subſidies you ſhall reverſe this Sentence;</hi> It may be ſaid that ſo much money would have removed the preſent neceſſity, but here was a Rate ſet upon future neceſſity. <hi>For twelve Subſidies you ſhall never ſuffer necſſity again, you ſhall for ever aboliſh that judgement;</hi> Here this myſtery is revealed, this viſour of neceſſity is pull'd off, and now it appeares that this Parliament of Judges had very frankly and bountifully preſented his Majeſty with twelve Subſidies to be leavied on your Lordſhips, and the Commons: Certainly there is no priviledge which more properly belongs to a Parliament, then to open the purſe of the Subject, and yet theſe Judges, who are neither capable of ſitting among us in the houſe of Commons, nor with your Lordſhips, otherwiſe then as your aſſiſtants, have not only aſſum'd to themſelves this priviledge of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but preſum'd at once to make a preſent to the Crowne of all that either your Lordſhips or the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of <hi>England</hi> doe, of ſhall hereafter poſſeſſe.</p>
            <p>And becauſe this man has had the boldneſſe to put the power of Parliament in ballance with the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of the Judges, I ſhall intreat your Lordſhips to obſerve by way of compariſon the ſolemne and ſafe proceeding of the one, with the precipitate diſpatch of the other. In Parliament (as your Lordſhips know well (no new Law can paſſe, or old be abrogated, till
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:102619:101"/>it has been thrice read with your Lordſhips, thrice in the Commons Houſe, and then it receives the Royall Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, ſo that 'tis like gold 7 times purified; whereas theſe Judges by this one reſolution of theirs, would perſwade his Majeſty, that by naming <hi>neceſſity</hi> he might at once diſſolve (at leaſt ſuſpend) the great Charter 32 times confirm'd by his Royal Progenitours, the petition of Right, and all other Lawes provided for the maintenance of the Right and propriety of the Subject; a ſtrange force (my Lords) in the ſound of this word <hi>neceſſity,</hi> that like a Charme it ſhould ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence the Laws, while we are piſpoyl'd of all we have: for that but a part of our goods was taken, is owing to the grace and goodneſſe of the King; for ſo much as concernes theſe Judges, we have no more left then they perhaps may deſerve to have, when your Lordſhips ſhall have paſſed Judgement upon them: This for the the neglect of their Oaths, and betraying that pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique truſt, which for the conſervation of our Lawes was repoſed in them.</p>
            <p>Now for the cruelty and unmercifulneſſe of this judgement, you may pleaſe to remember that in the old Law they were forbid to ſeeth a Kid in his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers milk, of which the received interpretation is, that we ſhould not uſe that to the deſtruction of any crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture which was intended for its preſervation; Now (my Lords) God and Nature has given us the Sea as our beſt Guard againſt our Enemies, and our ſhips as our greateſt glory above other Nations, and how barbarouſly would theſe men have let in the ſea upon
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:102619:102"/>us, at once to waſh away our Liberties, and to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelm, if not our Land, all the propriety wee have therein, making the ſupply of our Navy, a pretence for the ruine of our Nation; for obſerve I beſeech you the fruit and conſequence of this judgement, how this money has proſper'd, how contrary an effect it has had to the end for which they pretended to take it: On every County a ſhip is annually im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd, and who would not expect, but our ſeas by this time ſhould be covered with the number of our ſhips? Alas (my Lords) the daily Complaints of the decay of our Navy tels us how ill ſhip-money has maintain'd the Soveraignty of the ſea: and by the many petitions which we receive from the wives of thoſe miſerable Captives at <hi>Algier</hi> (being between 4 and 5 thouſand of our Country-men) it does evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently appeare that to make us ſlaves at home, is not the way to keepe us from being made ſlaves abroad; ſo farre has this judgement bin from reliving the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent or preventing the future neceſſity, that as it chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged our reall propriety into the ſhadow of a propriety, ſo of a ſeigned it has made a Reall neceſſity.</p>
            <p>A little before the approach of the <hi>Gaules</hi> to <hi>Rome,</hi> while the Romans had yet no apprehenſion of that danger, there was heard a voyce in the Aire, lowder then ordinary, <hi>The Gaules are come,</hi> which voyce after they had ſack'd the Citie, and beſieged the Capitoll, was held ſo ominous, that <hi>Livie</hi> relates it as a Prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy; This Anticipation of neceſſity ſeems to have been no leſſe ominous to us; Theſe Judges like ill boading
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:102619:102"/>birds have call'd neceſſity upon the State in a time when I dare ſay they thought themſelves in greateſt ſecurity; but if it ſeem ſuperſtitions to take this as an Omen, ſure I am we may look on it as a cauſe of the unfained neceſſity we now ſuffetr for what regret and diſcontent had this judgement bred among us? And as when the noyſe and tumult in a private houſe growes ſo loud, as to be heard into the ſtreets, it calls in the next dwellers either kindly to appeaſe, or to make their own uſe of the domeſtick ſtrife; ſo in all likelyhood our known diſcontents at home have been a concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent cauſe to invite our Neighbours to viſite us ſo much, to the expence and trouble of both theſe Kingdomes.</p>
            <p>And here, my Lords, I cannot but take notice of the moſt ſad effect of this oppreſſion, the ill influence it has had upon the ancient reputation and valour of the Engliſh Nation: and no wonder, for if it be true that oppreſſion makes a wiſe man mad, it may well ſuſpend the courage of the valiant: The ſame happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the Romans when for renowne in Armes they moſt excell'd the reſt of the world; the ſtory is but ſhort, 'twas in the time of the <hi>Decem-viri.</hi> (and I think the chief-troublers of our State may make up that number,) The <hi>Decem-viri,</hi> my Lords had ſubver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Lawes, ſuſpended the Courts of Juſtice; and (which was the greateſt grievance both to the Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and people) had for ſome years omitted to aſſemble the Senate, which was their Parliament; This ſayes the Hiſtorian did not onely deject the Romans, and make them deſpaire of their Liberty, but cauſed them
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:102619:103"/>to be leſſe valued by their Neighbours: The Sabines take the advantage and invade them; and now the <hi>Decem-viri</hi> are forc'd to call the long deſired Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, whereof the peopie were ſo glad, that <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtibus bello<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> gratiam habuerunt:</hi> This Aſſembly breaks up in diſcontent, nevertheleſſe the warre pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds; Forces are rais'd, led by ſome of the <hi>Decem-viri,</hi> and with the Sabines they meet in the Field; I know your Lordſhips expect the event; My Authors words of his Countrey-men are theſe, <hi>Ne quid ductu aut au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicio Decem-virorum proſpere gereretur, vinci ſe patie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bantur,</hi> They choſe rather to ſuffer a preſent diminuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their Honour, then by victory to confirme the tyranny of their new Maſters: At their return from this unfortunate expedition, after ſome diſtempers and expoſtulations of the people, an other Senate, that is a ſecond Parliament, is call'd, and there the <hi>Decem-viri</hi> are queſtioned, deprived of their Authority, impriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, baniſh'd, and ſome looſe their lives; and ſoon after this vindication of their Liberties, the Romans by their better ſucceſſe made it appeare to the world, that liberty and courage dwell alwayes in the ſame breſt, and a re never to be divorced. No doubt, my Lords, but your Juſtice ſhall have the like effect upon this diſpirited people; 'tis not the reſtitution of our an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Lawes alone, but the reſtauration of our ancient courage which is expected from your Lordſhips: I need not ſay any thing to move your juſt indignation that this man ſhould ſo cheaply give away that which your noble Anceſtors with ſo much courage and indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:102619:103"/>had ſo long maintain'd: you have often been told how carefull they were, though with the hazard of their lives and fortunes, to derive thoſe Rights and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties as entire to poſterity as they received from their Fathers: what they did with labour you may do with eaſe, what they did with danger, you may doe ſecure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the foundation of our Lawes is not ſhaken with the Engine of Warre, they are onely blaſted with the breath of theſe men, &amp; by your breath may be reſtored.</p>
            <p>What Judgements your Predeceſſors have given, and what puniſhments their Predeceſſors have ſuffer'd for offences of this nature, your Lordſhips have alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy been ſo well informed, that I ſhall not trouble you with a repetition of thoſe precedents: Onely (my Lords) ſomething I ſhall take leave to obſerve of the perſon with whoſe charge I have preſented you, that you may the leſſe doubt of the wilfulneſſe of his offence.</p>
            <p>His education in the Inns of Court, his conſtant practice as a Councellour, and his experience as a Judge (conſidered with the miſchiefe he has done) makes it appeare that this Progreſſe of his through the Law, has been like that of a diligent Spie through a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try into which he meant to conduct an enemy.</p>
            <p>To let you ſee he did not offend for company, there is one crime ſo peculiar to himſelfe, and of ſuch malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, that it makes him at once uncapable of your Lordſhips favour, and his own ſubſiſtence incompati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble with the right and propriety of the Subject: for if you leave him in a capacity of interpreting the Lawes, has he not already declared his opinion, That your
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:102619:104"/>votes and reſolutions againſt Ship-money are voyd, and that it is not in the power of a Parliament to abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh that Judgement? To him, my Lords, that has thus plaid with the power of Parliament, wee may well apply what was once ſaid to the Goat browſing on the Vine,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rode, caper, vitem, tamen hinc cum ſtabis ad aras In Tuaquod fundi cornua poſſit, erit:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hee has cropt and infring'd the priviledges of a ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd Parliament, but now it is returned he may find it has power enough to make a Sacrifice of him, to the better eſtabliſhment of out Lawes; and in truth what other ſatisfaction can he make his injur'd Country, then to confirme by his example thoſe Rights and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties which he had ruin'd by his opinion?</p>
            <p>For the proofes, my Lords, they are ſo manifeſt that they will give you little trouble in the diſquiſition; his crimes are already upon Record, the Delinquent and the Witneſſe is the ſame; having from ſeverall Seats of Judicature proclaim'd himſelfe an Enemy to our Lawes and Nation, <hi>Ex ore ſuo judicabitur.</hi> To which purpoſe I am commanded by the Knights, Citizens, and Burgeſſes of the Houſe of Commons, to deſire your Lordſhips that as ſpeedy a proceeding may bee had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt M. Juſtice <hi>Crawley</hi> as the courſe of Parliaments will permit.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:102619:104"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Mr. WALLERS SPEECH,</hi> In the Houſe of Commons, the fourth of <hi>July,</hi> 1643. being brought to the Bar, and having leave given him by the Speaker, to ſay what he could for himſelfe.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Mr. Speaker.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Acknowledge it a great mercy of God, and a great favour from you, that I am once more ſuffered to behold this Honourable Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, I mean not to make uſe of it to ſay any thing in my own defence by Juſtification or denyall of what I have done, I have already confeſſed enough to make me appeare, worthy not onely to be put out of this Houſe, but out of the World too. All my humble requeſt to you is, that, if I ſeeme to you as unworthy to live, as I doe to my ſelfe, I may have the Honour to receive my death from your owne hands, and not bee expoſed to a Tryall by the Counſell of Warre: what ever you ſhall thinke me worthy to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer in a Parliamentary way, is not like to finde ſtop any where elſe.</p>
            <p>This (Sir) I hope you will be pleaſed for your own ſakes to grant me, who am already ſo miſerable, that nothing can be added to my calamity, but to be make the occaſion of creating a Preſident to your own diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantage; beſides the right I may have to this, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider I beſeech you that the eyes of the world are upon
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:102619:105"/>you governe in chiefe, and if you ſhould expoſe your owne members to the puniſhment of others, it will be thought that you either want Power, or leiſure to chaſtiſe them your ſelves; nor let any man deſpiſe the ill conſequence of ſuch a preſident as this would be, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee ſeeth not preſently the inconveniences which may enſue: you have many Armies on Foote, and it is uncerteine how long you may have occaſion to uſe them. Souldiers and Commanders (though I know well they of the Parliaments Army, excell no leſſe in modeſly then they doe in Courage) are ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally of a Nature ready to pretend to the utmoſt power of this kind, which they conceive to be due to them, and may be too apt upon any occaſion of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content to make uſe of ſuch a Preſident as this. In this very Parliament you have not bin without ſome taſt of the experience hereof, it is now ſomewhat more than two yeares ſince you had an Army in the North, paid and directed by your ſelves, and yet you may be pleaſed to remember there was a conſiderable number of Officers in that Army, which joyned in a Petition or Remonſtrance to this Houſe, taking no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of what ſome of Members had ſaid here, as they ſuppoſed to their diſadvantage, and did little leſt; then require them of you; 'tis true, there had bin ſome tampering with them, but what has happened at one time, may wiſely be thought poſſible to fall out againe at another.</p>
            <p>Sir, I preſume but to point you out the danger; if it be not juſt, I know you will not do me the wrong
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:102619:105"/>to expoſe me to this triall; if it be juſt your Army may another time require the ſame juſtice of you, in their owne behalfe, againſt ſome other Member, whom per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps you would be leſſe willing to part with. Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity has of late forced you into untrodden paths; and in ſuch a caſe as this where you have no preſident of your own, you may not do amiſſe to looke abroad up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on other States and Senates, which exerciſe the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame Power, as you now doe here.</p>
            <p>I dare confidently ſay you ſhall finde none either An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient or Moderne, which ever expoſed any of their owne order to be tryed for his life by the Officers of their Armies abroad, for what he did, while he reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded among them in the Senate.</p>
            <p>Among the Romans the practice was ſo contrary, that ſome inferiour Officers in their Army farre from the City, having been ſentenced by their Generall or Commander in chief, as deſerving death by their Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline of Warre, have nevertheleſſe (becauſe they were Senators) appealed thither, and the cauſe has received a new hearing in the Senate. Not to uſe more words to perſwade you to take heed that you wound not your ſelves thorough my ſides in violating the Priviledges belonging to your own perſons, I ſhall humbly deſire you to conſider likewiſe the nature of my offence, (not but that I ſhould be much aſhamed to ſay any thing in diminution therof; God knowes 'tis horrid enough for the evill it might have occaſioned) but if you looke neare it, it may perhaps apeare to be rather a Civill then a Martiall crime and ſo to have
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:102619:106"/>Title to a Triall at the common law of the land; ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> may juſtly be ſome difference put between mee and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in this buſineſſe.</p>
            <p>I have had nothing to do with the other Army, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny intention to begin the offer of violence to any body, It was only a civill pretence to that which I then foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhly conceived to be the right of the ſubject. I humbly refer it to your conſiderations, and to your conſciences. I know you will take care not to to ſhed the blood of War in Peace that blood by the law of War, which hath a right to betryed by the Law of Peace.</p>
            <p>For ſo much as concerns my ſelfe and my part in this buſineſſe, (if I were worthy to have any thing ſpoken or patiently heard in my behalfe) this might truly be ſaid, that I made not this buſineſs, but found it, 'twas in other mens hands long before it was brought to me, and when it came I extended it not, but reſtrained it. For the Propoſitions of letting in part of the Kings Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, or offering violence to the Members of this Houſe, I ever diſallowed and utterly rejected them.</p>
            <p>What it was that moved me to entertain diſcourſe of this buſineſſe ſo far as I did, I will tell you ingeniouſly, and that rather as a warning for others, than that it make any thing for my ſelfe; it was only an impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the inconveniences of the preſent War, looking on things with a carnall eye, and not minding that which chiefly (if not onely) ought to have been conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, the ineſtimable value of the Cauſe you have in hand, the Cauſe of God and of Religion, and the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities you are forced upon for the maintenance of the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:102619:106"/>ſame; as a juſt puniſhment for this neglect, it pleaſed God to deſert and ſuffer me with a fatall blindneſſe, to be led on, and ingaged in ſuch Counſels as were wholly diſproportioned to the reſt of my life; This (Sir) my own Conſcience tells me was the cauſe of my failing, and not malice, or any ill habit of minde, or diſpoſition toward the Common-wealth, or to the Parliament: for from whence ſhould I have it? If you look on my Birth, you will not find it in my blood: I am of a ſtock which hath born you better fruit, if you look on my education, it hath been almoſt from my child-hood in this Houſe, and among the beſt ſort of men; and for the whole pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of my life till this time, if another were to ſpeake for me, he might reaſonably ſay, that neither my actions out of Parliament, nor my expreſſions in it, have ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured of diſaffection or malice to the Liberties of the People, or Priviledges of Parliament.</p>
            <p>Thus Sir, I have ſet before your eyes, both my perſon and my caſe, wherein I ſhall make no ſuch defence by denying, or extenuating any thing I have done, as or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily Delinquents doe, my addreſſe to you, and all my Plea ſhall onely be ſuch as Children uſe to their Parents, I have offended; I confeſſe it, I never did any thing like it before; it is a paſſage unſuitable to the whole courſe of my life beſide, and for the time to come, as God that can bring light out of darkneſſe, hath made this buſineſſe in the event uſefull to you, ſo alſo hath he to me: you have by it made an happy diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of your Enemies, and I of my ſelfe, and the evil prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples I walkt by; ſo that if you look either on what I
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:102619:107"/>have been heretofore, or what I now am, and by Gods grace aſſiſting me, ſhall alwayes continue to be, you may perhaps thinke me fit to be an example of your compaſſion and clemency.</p>
            <p>Sir, I ſhal no ſooner leave you, but my life wil depend on your breath, &amp; not that alone, but the ſubſiſtence of ſome that are more innocent. I might therefore ſhew you my Children, whom the rigour of your Juſtice would make compleat Orphanes, being already Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſs. I might ſhew you a Family, wherein there are ſome unworthy to have their ſhare in that mark of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famy which now threatens us: But ſomething there is, which if I could ſhew you, would move you more then all this<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> it is my Heart, which abhors what I have done more, &amp; is more ſevere to it ſelfe, then the ſevereſt Judge can be. A heart (Mr.Speaker) ſo a wakened by this affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and ſo intirely devoted to the Cauſe you main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that I earneſtly deſire of God to incline you, ſo to diſpoſe of me, whether for life or death, as may moſt conduce to the advancement therof.</p>
            <p>Sir, not to trouble you any longer, if I dye, I ſhall dye praying for you; if I live, I ſhall live ſerving you, and render you back the uſe and imployment of all thoſe dayes you ſhall adde to my life.</p>
            <p>After this having withdrawn himſelfe, he was called in again, and (being by the Speaker required thereto) gave them an exact account now he came firſt to the knowledge of this buſineſſ; as alſo what Lords were acquainted therwith, or had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged themſelves therein.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
